<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Food</title>
    <link>https://www.latimes.com/food</link>
    <description>Food</description>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 12:00:50 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.latimes.com/food.rss" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" />
    <item>
      <title>Hamburger Mary's brought drag brunch to L.A. in 2001. Here are 13 spots to celebrate the tradition now</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-drag-brunch-in-los-angeles-orange-county-ventura-area</link>
      <description>Kick your weekend into gear with the best drag brunches, featuring lively performances, bottomless mimosas and great food, across Los Angeles, Ventura and Orange counties.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 12:00:50 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-drag-brunch-in-los-angeles-orange-county-ventura-area</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A summery chicken potpie is the antidote for June gloom</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-08/summer-best-chicken-pot-pie-with-herbs-recipe</link>
      <description>Packed with herbs and sautéed greens and perked up with Dijon mustard and lemon, this lighter chicken potpie is just the dish for cool nights in June.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 13:00:44 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-08/summer-best-chicken-pot-pie-with-herbs-recipe</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two of L.A.'s most exciting pop-ups unite Mexican and Indian flavors at this under-the-radar taqueria</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-01/saucy-chick-rotisserie-the-goat-mafia-review-beverly-grove-smorgasburg-bill-addison</link>
      <description>Four life stories, two pop-ups, and regional Mexican and Indian flavors unite deliciously at this new taqueria on 3rd Street in Los Angeles.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 14:00:07 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-01/saucy-chick-rotisserie-the-goat-mafia-review-beverly-grove-smorgasburg-bill-addison</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What's with all the wine at Anajak Thai? Don't sleep on these bottles from its massive list</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-26/anajak-thai-wine-list-los-angeles</link>
      <description>Anajak Thai is a beloved so-L.A. restaurant, but it's the sprawling list of bottles that has enamored the Sherman Oaks destination to Southern California's wine scene.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 14:00:32 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-26/anajak-thai-wine-list-los-angeles</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The best places to eat and drink in L.A. right now, according to our food writers</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-new-restaurants-and-bars-in-los-angeles-june-2023</link>
      <description>The best new restaurants and bars to try in L.A. this month include pizza and tapas in Venice and an Italian restaurant from Evan Funke in Beverly Hills.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 15:00:03 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-new-restaurants-and-bars-in-los-angeles-june-2023</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Miles Thompson returns to the kitchen at this exclusive new pop-up in Koreatown</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-07/miles-thompson-baby-bistro-gin-rummy-moms-haus</link>
      <description>Plus, a sprawling tiki bar lands in Venice, New Orleans cuisine goes Hollywood, some of L.A.'s best bagels get a brand new space, and more.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 13:00:25 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Stephanie Breijo</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-07/miles-thompson-baby-bistro-gin-rummy-moms-haus</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-07/miles-thompson-baby-bistro-gin-rummy-moms-haus">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/65200d6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3823x2542+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F47%2Fdc%2F94a3c2be4643836a7b1d939a9dee%2Fbaby-bistro-by-stephanie-breijo-1.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/de72055/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3823x2542+0+0/resize/568x378!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F47%2Fdc%2F94a3c2be4643836a7b1d939a9dee%2Fbaby-bistro-by-stephanie-breijo-1.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6363c01/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3823x2542+0+0/resize/768x511!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F47%2Fdc%2F94a3c2be4643836a7b1d939a9dee%2Fbaby-bistro-by-stephanie-breijo-1.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8603ccb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3823x2542+0+0/resize/1024x681!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F47%2Fdc%2F94a3c2be4643836a7b1d939a9dee%2Fbaby-bistro-by-stephanie-breijo-1.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8190c13/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3823x2542+0+0/resize/1200x798!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F47%2Fdc%2F94a3c2be4643836a7b1d939a9dee%2Fbaby-bistro-by-stephanie-breijo-1.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="A bowl of chicken sausage with beans and wine at pop-up Baby Bistro from Miles Thompson and Andy Schwartz at Hotel Normandie"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/66d9fa9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3823x2542+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F47%2Fdc%2F94a3c2be4643836a7b1d939a9dee%2Fbaby-bistro-by-stephanie-breijo-1.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/fdf17ff/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3823x2542+0+0/resize/568x378!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F47%2Fdc%2F94a3c2be4643836a7b1d939a9dee%2Fbaby-bistro-by-stephanie-breijo-1.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5a2baa6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3823x2542+0+0/resize/768x511!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F47%2Fdc%2F94a3c2be4643836a7b1d939a9dee%2Fbaby-bistro-by-stephanie-breijo-1.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f0f5bc6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3823x2542+0+0/resize/1024x681!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F47%2Fdc%2F94a3c2be4643836a7b1d939a9dee%2Fbaby-bistro-by-stephanie-breijo-1.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6d6e1aa/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3823x2542+0+0/resize/1200x798!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F47%2Fdc%2F94a3c2be4643836a7b1d939a9dee%2Fbaby-bistro-by-stephanie-breijo-1.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="798"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6d6e1aa/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3823x2542+0+0/resize/1200x798!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F47%2Fdc%2F94a3c2be4643836a7b1d939a9dee%2Fbaby-bistro-by-stephanie-breijo-1.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">The new, indefinite pop-up from chef Miles Thompson and wine vet Andy Schwartz is serving dishes such as house-made chicken sausage with lemongrass-scented beans at the base of Hotel Normandie.</div><div class="figure-credit">(Stephanie Breijo / Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Miles Thompson returns to the kitchen at this exclusive new pop-up in Koreatown</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/stephanie-breijo">        Stephanie Breijo    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 7, 2023">June 7, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <b>Baby Bistro</b>After years as <p>One of L.A.s most seasonally minded chefs, Miles Thompson, recently debuted an indefinite pop-up at the base of Hotel Normandie in Koreatown with a </p>brief <p>rotating menu, a new business partner and a glimpse of whats next. Baby Bistro, his new project with wine vet Andy Schwartz, is </p>an indefinite pop-up and <p>a nod </p>of  to <p>whats </p>to come  next in store<p> when the duo open a full restaurant in Echo Park under a different, to-be-announced name.</p><p>The rising-star chef left Michaels in Santa Monica in 2018 to stage in Europe, and when he returned with plans to open his own restaurant, he began his own pop-up series before working at Konbi into late 2022 and hosting his own pop-ups there. </p>But nearing 2023  Late last year,<p> he began focusing once again on his own restaurants future.</p><p>Its exciting, its overwhelming, Thompson said of a return to a kitchen of his own. Andy and I talk a lot about not wanting to let anyone down. I've cooked in the city for</p> ,<p> like</p> ,<p> 15 years now and I've made a lot of friends and there've been some people that have followed my career. Im very hard on myself in everything that I do and I just want to make sure that everyone is having a fantastic time.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/3b/50/92e74f134a95bbc5f2a5b2992505/20230606-fo-baby-bistro-echo-park.jpg"></figure><p>Schwartz, involved in multiple small wine-import businesses and who also helped run Lolo Wine Bar</p>  in East Hollywood<p>, first worked with Thompson</p> during one of the chefs pop-ups in  at one of his <p>Konbi </p> pop-ups <p>by providing wine. When the opportunity </p> and space<p> arose to open Baby Bistro, which they refer to as a pre-restaurant restaurant, they </p>teamed up and <p>began collaborating on how Thompsons brief menu would interplay with Schwartzs wines here and in the future restaurant.</p><p>Dont expect straightforward French fare, nor Italian pastas  the concept is meant to evoke the intimate feeling of a bistro, not the </p>ideal of the <p>cuisines traditionally cooked in those spaces.</p><p>We call it a micro bistro not just because of the size, Thompson said, but because the food is influenced by the types of cooking in either mom-and-pop or chef-driven, small restaurants in Europe. The ethos of those is cooking beautiful products that are local and to cook with care and attention, not being super fancy. If you were in Europe, you would stumble into it, have an incredible meal and never remember what its called and try to figure it out for the rest of your life. Thats the idea of this restaurant.</p><p>The </p>brief <p>menu consists of only five or six items and is meant to be ordered in its entirety and shared</p>; all dishes belie a surprising amount of technique<p>. The zucchini, tonnato course  inspired by a classic veal tonnato  replaces beef with thinly sliced summer squash that chills overnight, blanched and pickled, and is dressed in a tonnato sauce made with fresh swordfish belly, all topped with bottarga, pine nuts and lemon zest. The tomato bread, anchovy miso is house-made rustic bread </p>entirely <p>hydrated by salted tomatoes, forming light pink slabs of airy bread with sieved, herbaceous garlic butter as well as fermented garlic that was packed in barley miso, topped with anchovy and </p> P<p>armesan. A fresh-bean dish, inspired by one served during his Konbi pop-up, utilizes beans, lemongrass, brown butter and Meyer lemon with a chicken sausage thats been emulsified with chicken skin instead of pork fat.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/9d/f2/67659b8e4a9581d0c27b2e8787f0/baby-bistro-by-stephanie-breijo-2.jpg"></figure><p>The wines, Schwartz said, are not conventional or traditional; hes focusing on spotlighting natural wines and making whole bottles available without much markup  and also incorporating an annual specialty of Thompsons: house-made nocino scented with lemon peel, vanilla bean and brown sugar.</p><p>Baby Bistro is a </p>charming <p>shoebox </p> of a restaurant <p>with 19 seats housed in a former barber shop, rings from the heavy chairs just visible on the black-and-white checkered floor. Due to its size, reservations fill up quickly, with three seating times per night of service currently accessed by sending a request over Instagram DM. In mid-July, Thompson will take a break for vacation</p> ,<p> then most likely return for more Baby Bistro. Baby Bistro operates Thursday t</p> hr<p>o</p> ugh<p> Saturday with seatings around 7, 9 and 11 p.m.</p>3610 W. 6th St., Los Angeles, <p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/baby_bistro_/">instagram.com/baby_bistro_</a></p><b>Gin Rummy</b><p>A tropical, tiki-leaning cocktail bar has taken over the former home of Venice restaurant Nueva. </p>, and with <p>Gin Rummy </p> servescomes <p>frozen concoctions, nonalcoholic options, large-format drinks, wing baskets</p>, and<p> tacos</p>andpies<p>. The new collaboration between </p> bar impresario<p> Jared Meisler (Roger Room, Bar Lubitsch, </p> t<p>he Friend, </p> t<p>he Little Friend) and husband-and-wife</p> team  co-owners <p>David and Patti Reiss of Reiss Co. (</p> t<p>he Brig, </p> t<p>he Alibi Room) sits next to the Little Friend and sprawls across a patio and an indoor setting with a large mahogany bar, with combined seating for roughly 200 guests. Beverage directors Danilo Kim (</p> t<p>he Alibi Room, Nueva) and Marcus Ragas (The Chestnut Club, Caboco) are overseeing</p> a program that includes<p> drinks such as banana old-fashioneds, frozen guava daiquiris, a paloma-inspired highball, four-person scorpion bowls, a mai tai made with rye and mushroom rum, and rum, mezcal and tequila flights, in addition to tiki classics. Bites such as mango habanero wings, baskets of crispy cauliflower, fish and chips, coconut shrimp, carnitas tacos and Fat &amp; Flour-made pies are also available. Gin Rummy is open 4 p.m. to 2 a.m. Monday t</p> hr<p>o</p> ugh<p> Friday </p>from 4 p.m. to 2 a.m.,<p> and noon to 2 a.m. Saturday and Sunday</p> from noon to 2 a.m<p>.</p>822 Washington Blvd., Marina del Rey, (310) 747-6050, <p><a href="https://ginrummybar.com/">ginrummybar.com</a></p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/24/a6/7ed686324273802993495e6a959b/20230606-fo-gin-rummy-bar-venice-02.jpg"></figure><b>Moms Haus Hollywood</b><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/1c/30/cc0ae6114391b3b2c72acd68da1f/20230606-fo-moms-haus-new-orleans-restaurant-van-nuys-dessert.jpg"></figure><p>A Van Nuys ode to the Big Easy has expanded to Hollywood, bringing fried po boys, gumbo, daiquiris, banana pudding and a late-night takeout window to a strip mall at the corner of Sunset and La Brea. The menu at the new Moms Haus Hollywood is led by chef Brandon Baker,</p> the founding chef also <p>of the Van Nuys location, and includes breakfast items such as griddled flapjacks in</p> a range of<p> flavors </p> <p>including bourbon peach, bananas foster and red velvet,</p> <p> along with chicken and waffles, shrimp and grits, crawfish omelets and salmon croquettes served until 2 p.m.</p><p>The new, </p> larger <p>space offers more New Orleans-inspired decor</p> as well as more square footage<p>, plus </p>room for <p>new items: grilled lobster tail, king crab in garlic butter, alligator, and charbroiled oysters during lunch and dinner served alongside classics such as smothered oxtails, fried or blackened catfish, hot links and beyond. Moms Haus Hollywood is open </p>daily from <p>8 a.m. to 10 p.m. </p> daily<p>, with a to-go window open </p> 10 p.m. to 3 a.m.<p> Thursday t</p> hr<p>o</p> ugh<p> Sunday. </p>from 10 p.m. to 3 a.m.7065 Sunset Blvd., Los Angeles, (323) 380-5473, <p><a href="https://www.eatmomshaus.com/">eatmomshaus.com</a></p><b>Pops Bagels Fairfax</b><p>Zach Liporaces beloved bagel pop-up</p> turned is now a <p>local chain </p> and <p>has expanded to Fairfax, </p>and theres more from Pops Bagels <p>with more to come. Last month Liporace launched a new outpost for his freshly baked bagels made</p> simply<p> with organic barley malt, yeast</p>,<p> and flour, plus bagel sandwiches, specials</p>,<p> and to-go tubs of sliced lox and whitefish salad. Liporace formerly based his operation out of a commissary kitchen in East L.A.; the new Fairfax location now serves as the primary bakeshop for Pops Bagels, with deliveries to Culver City and Brentwood made multiple times a day.</p><p>Im just trying to push good bagels everywhere, Liporace said. </p>I feel like <p>Everywhere seems to need them, everywhere seems to want and crave a good bagel these days  so we're just trying to stay true to my roots of simplicity and freshness and good quality.</p><p>Fairfax will also act as a kind of test kitchen for new items. Inspired by the spaces predecessor Lindy &amp; Grundy  a favorite butcher shop of Liporaces  guests might find an ode in the form of a sausage breakfast sandwich at the new Pops, plus non-bagel items such as black and white cookies, rugelach, </p> cinnamon banana bread and <p>Friday-only challah</p>, and cinnamon banana bread<p>. (On weekends, look for pumpernickel bagels and onion bialy.) Hes also hoping to expand his gluten-free menu, add bagel sandwiches such as house roast beef and turkey, seasonal schmears, bagel-of-the-month bagel flavors</p>,<p> and possibly pizza bagels. Merch and take-and-bake frozen bagels are also on offer. Pops Bagels is now open on Fairfax </p>daily from <p>7 a.m. to 3 p.m. </p> daily<p>. Another Pops Bagels is expected to open in Beverly Hills in early August with griddle space for an even larger menu</p>; Liporace is plotting further expansion in L.A. and beyond within the next few years<p>.</p>801 N. Fairfax Ave., Los Angeles, <p><a href="https://popsbagelsla.com/">popsbagelsla.com</a></p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/a3/4e/50089ccb4f5983aa4e43547b3126/pops-bagels-by-stephanie-breijo-1.jpg"></figure><b>Hibi</b><p>A casual, modern-Japanese restaurant from the team behind Kabuki is now serving tempura, sushi, pan-fried seafood udon, rice bowls and small plates in Koreatown. Hibi, meaning day to day, began as a ghost kitchen from chef-founder Solomon Lee; he teamed up with rapper-actor Rekstizzy and Kabuki to offer stalwarts such as classic maki, udon soup with shrimp tempura, gyoza and hibachi-style fried rice, but specializes in rotating, new spins on Japanese cuisine, including steak with shis</p> h<p>ito-and-miso paste, broiled unagi bowls with avocado and egg, truffled salmon carpaccio with yuzu, and a bowl of marinated chicken and cilantro served over purple rice made from Okinawa sweet potato that's imported from Japan every three days. Hibi is open </p>Monday to Saturday from <p>11 a.m. to 9 p.m. Monday through Saturday.</p>3121 W. Olympic Blvd., Suite 103, Los Angeles, <p><a href="https://www.madebyhibi.com/">madebyhibi.com</a></p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amid scrutiny, the James Beard Foundation awards 5 L.A. restaurants, chefs and writers</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-05/james-beard-awards-2023-los-angeles-winners-chefs-restaurants-media</link>
      <description>Here are all of the 2023 Los Angeles James Beard Award winners, including L.A. Times Food critic Bill Addison.</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 04:09:17 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Stephanie Breijo</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-05/james-beard-awards-2023-los-angeles-winners-chefs-restaurants-media</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-05/james-beard-awards-2023-los-angeles-winners-chefs-restaurants-media">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8e49bf7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5568x3712+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff7%2F94%2Fdb12490f446c9537f40749d290b9%2Fla-photos-1staff-465028-fo-0910-republique-dinner-mrt-020.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9e64260/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5568x3712+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff7%2F94%2Fdb12490f446c9537f40749d290b9%2Fla-photos-1staff-465028-fo-0910-republique-dinner-mrt-020.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7a7675b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5568x3712+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff7%2F94%2Fdb12490f446c9537f40749d290b9%2Fla-photos-1staff-465028-fo-0910-republique-dinner-mrt-020.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3fcef10/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5568x3712+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff7%2F94%2Fdb12490f446c9537f40749d290b9%2Fla-photos-1staff-465028-fo-0910-republique-dinner-mrt-020.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6fd2597/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5568x3712+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff7%2F94%2Fdb12490f446c9537f40749d290b9%2Fla-photos-1staff-465028-fo-0910-republique-dinner-mrt-020.JPG 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="LOS ANGELES, CA- September 10, 2019: En Croute dessert from Rpublique on Tuesday, September 10, 2019. (Mariah Tauger / Los Angeles Times)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/115fb6a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5568x3712+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff7%2F94%2Fdb12490f446c9537f40749d290b9%2Fla-photos-1staff-465028-fo-0910-republique-dinner-mrt-020.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/77c24ba/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5568x3712+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff7%2F94%2Fdb12490f446c9537f40749d290b9%2Fla-photos-1staff-465028-fo-0910-republique-dinner-mrt-020.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3b767f6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5568x3712+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff7%2F94%2Fdb12490f446c9537f40749d290b9%2Fla-photos-1staff-465028-fo-0910-republique-dinner-mrt-020.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/dfe56c5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5568x3712+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff7%2F94%2Fdb12490f446c9537f40749d290b9%2Fla-photos-1staff-465028-fo-0910-republique-dinner-mrt-020.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/37d68ba/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5568x3712+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff7%2F94%2Fdb12490f446c9537f40749d290b9%2Fla-photos-1staff-465028-fo-0910-republique-dinner-mrt-020.JPG 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/37d68ba/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5568x3712+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff7%2F94%2Fdb12490f446c9537f40749d290b9%2Fla-photos-1staff-465028-fo-0910-republique-dinner-mrt-020.JPG"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">LOS ANGELES, CA- September 10, 2019: En Croute dessert from Rpublique on Tuesday, September 10, 2019. (Mariah Tauger / Los Angeles Times) </div><div class="figure-credit">(Mariah Tauger/Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Amid scrutiny, the James Beard Foundation awards 5 L.A. restaurants, chefs and writers</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/stephanie-breijo">        Stephanie Breijo    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 5, 2023">June 5, 2023</time>                                                                            <time class="op-modified" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                            </header>                    <p>Dubbed the biggest night of the year for the culinary industry and the Oscars of food, the James Beard Foundations annual restaurant and dining awards are some of the highest accolades that chefs, restaurateurs</p>, beverage directors<p> and others </p>with<p>in the industry can garner. Following</p> months<p> weeks of </p>reports, allegations controversy  and drama<p> surrounding the foundation and its investigations into semifinalists and nominees, the awards ceremony</p>, held in Chicago,<p> took place </p> in Chicago <p>with</p> great fanfare, asides alluding to the recent turbulence, and<p> big wins for some of the countrys most recognizable culinary names and up-and-comers.</p><p>This year some of the most acclaimed </p>and beloved <p>chefs in Los Angeles took home national and regional awards  as did Los Angeles Times Food critic Bill Addison, who won a media award on Saturday.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/a0/3b/3509b9424a75b769e561ae13ba31/851347-fo-1007-anajak-thai-101-mrt-21.jpg"></figure><p>Justin Pichetrungsi, chef of <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2022-07-22/anajak-thai-sherman-oaks-restaurant-of-the-year-2022">L.A. Times restaurant of 2022</a> Anajak Thai, won best chef: California, an award he largely credits to the tutelage of his parents  and especially to his father, who cooked for 38 of Anajaks 43 years before passing the torch to his son. A number of his fellow nominees, he noted, also cook with their parents, although it isnt always easy.</p><p>There's a lot of intergenerational pain there and we're trying to heal it one dish at a time; my parents are my teachers, Pichetrungsi said before thanking his team, then added, I'd love to thank my parents because they are my greatest allies. They argue with me a lot. I have the hardest conversations with them about where the direction of the restaurant is going, where the direction of cooks are going to be going, what's the math involved in all this stuff. But they gave me the tools to do everything else, and for that I'm eternally grateful for them.</p><p>A semifinalist or nominee every year since 2015, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2019-09-18/republique-walter-margarita-manzke-hancock-park-review-bill-addison">Rpublique</a> co-owner and lauded pastry chef Margarita Manzke was finally awarded outstanding pastry chef or baker; an employee excitedly accepted the award on behalf of Manzke, who could not attend the ceremony.</p><p>Echo Park sake bar Ototo  which </p>L.A. Times Food critic Bill <p>Addison <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/newsletter/2022-03-19/seasonal-sake-tsubaki-ototo-courtney-kaplan-tasting-notes">dubbed L.A.s best sake bar</a> last year  won in the category of outstanding wine and other beverages program. It was such a surprise to be nominated, to see that the Foundation had chosen to expand the category this year to recognize sake, said co-owner Courtney Kaplan.</p> , who said she was honored to be there.<p> [Its] such a special beverage that sometimes doesnt always get the spotlight that I think it deserves.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/9a/69/23f5f3104537b84d8b3dc94e48f8/la-photos-1staff-462413-la-fo-ototo-review-addison18-mam.jpg"></figure><p>Other Los Angeles names permeated the </p>this years James<p> Beard </p>Foundation <p>awards, with multiple accolades garnered during the </p>2023<p> media-awards ceremony. </p>L.A. Times Food critic Bill<p> Addison won the Craig Claiborne distinguished restaurant review award for <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2022-04-28/ponchos-tlayudas-review-addison">Ponchos Tlayudas, a window to Oaxaca, serves one of L.A.s defining dishes</a>; <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2022-08-04/pearl-river-deli-chinatown-review-bill-addison">At Chinatowns Pearl River Deli, the menu is always changing  and worth chasing</a>; </p> and<p> <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2022-07-22/anajak-thai-sherman-oaks-restaurant-of-the-year-2022">Anajak Thai is our 2022 Restaurant of the Year.</a> It marks the second James Beard Foundation award for Addison, who won for dining and travel writing in 2017, and his first while at the Los Angeles Times.</p><p>In the media awards book segment, Bludsos Bar &amp; Que chef-founder Kevin Bludso and co-author Noah Galuten won the restaurant and professional category for Bludso's BBQ Cookbook: A Family Affair in Smoke and Soul, an L.A. Times pick for <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2022-12-21/best-cookbooks-2022">best cookbooks of 2022</a>. </p> Los Angeles BBQ history lives on through Kevin Bludso's incredible brisket, ribs, oxtail <p>Personal essays by L.A.-based writers Kyla Wazana Tompkins&nbsp;and former Good Girl Dinette owner Diep Tran also won media awards.</p><p>The months leading to this years awards have been punctuated by reports and allegations that call into question the foundations more recent initiatives, many intended to create a more diverse and equitable process and nominee pool. </p><p>Last week, the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/31/dining/james-beard-restaurants-investigation.html">New York Times revealed</a> that through one of the James Beard Foundations new investigative policies, 2023 best chef: Southeast nominee Sam Fore felt she was interrogated by the committee based on an anonymously submitted complaint: Social-media posts, including one made to raise awareness of domestic violence, were</p> examples of examined as potential <p>targeted bullying and harassment despite Fore not naming a perpetrator. The report has spurred discussions surrounding the foundations investigative process and its anonymous-tip procedure.</p><p>Fores is not the only controversy spurred by this years awards procedures. In spring, judges and multiple committee members resigned  and former winner chef John Currence smashed one of his own framed </p>foundation Beard <p>awards with a brick  when chef Timothy Hontzas was disqualified from the category of best chef: South. </p>Per the <p>The Foundations ethics committee </p> determined that, an investigation into <p>Hontzas</p>s<p> alleged </p>actions of<p> yelling at guests and employees violated the code of ethics.</p><p>I am sickened today in a way I cant even begin to explain, Currence posted to Instagram in May, the caption to a photo of his smashed award. But it is way past time to stop this cycle of insane blame and shame through arbitrary accusations and NOTHING approaching due-process and stripping people of credit they deserve based on nothing other than the opinion of one.</p><p>We are about raising people up, not calling them out, Foundation Chief Executive Claire Reichenbach </p>, CEO of the James Beard Foundation, <p>said at the </p>toward the start of tonights<p> ceremony.</p> These L.A. chefs and restaurants are finalists for the 2023 James Beard Foundation Awards<p>When it came time to announce the category in which Hontzas had previously been a finalist, presenter </p> Mairym "<p>Monti</p> "<p> Carlo took the stage. This next category  best chef: South  has brought more drama than a Mariah Carey concert, but were here for it, she said, smiling. No one mentioned </p> the controversy surrounding the way<p> Fore</p>s allegations was investigated , nor appeared to allude to the New York Times article regarding them,<p> during the announcement of best chef: Southeas</p> t, which was awarded to Terry Koval of Atlanta. <p>Earlier in the evening, chair of the awards committee Tanya Holland took the podium to share that New Orleans chef Leah Chase once told her: Be prepared to get a lot of criticism in this industry, and work with it; you will make mistakes. The important thing is where your heart is and how you move on. The universe knows Ive made numerous mistakes, said Holland</p> , who is chef of Brown Sugar Kitchen in Oakland.But, she added,<p> She has become comfortable being uncomfortable, </p> she said<p>, adding </p>and <p>that she is motivated </p>through a push <p>to make the industry better. The efforts of the foundation </p>of the last few years <p>have made a difference in the diversity of the awards nominees and winners, she said, and should be commended.</p><p>Were learning as we go, she said. Its not always smooth, but that doesnt mean were not on the right path.</p>Members of the Los Angeles Times Food section have served as judges for the awards but did not contribute to the reporting of this article.                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The new L.A. sandwiches I can't stop eating</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-05/best-sandwich-los-angeles-lorenzo-lady-and-larder</link>
      <description>Where to find the best new sandwiches in Los Angeles, including a new tiny sandwich shop in Beverly Hills and a cheese counter in Santa Monica.</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2023 16:00:39 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Jenn Harris</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-05/best-sandwich-los-angeles-lorenzo-lady-and-larder</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-05/best-sandwich-los-angeles-lorenzo-lady-and-larder">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/27c35af/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1498x952+0+0/resize/320x203!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb4%2Fcb%2F059edd274ff4adcb02b7241a412c%2Fimg-6323.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/11e1ed4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1498x952+0+0/resize/568x361!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb4%2Fcb%2F059edd274ff4adcb02b7241a412c%2Fimg-6323.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/43b4324/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1498x952+0+0/resize/768x488!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb4%2Fcb%2F059edd274ff4adcb02b7241a412c%2Fimg-6323.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/be68293/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1498x952+0+0/resize/1024x651!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb4%2Fcb%2F059edd274ff4adcb02b7241a412c%2Fimg-6323.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6125bb0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1498x952+0+0/resize/1200x763!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb4%2Fcb%2F059edd274ff4adcb02b7241a412c%2Fimg-6323.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="The Lorenzo sandwich from Lorenzo California in Beverly Hills."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/527f2a3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1498x952+0+0/resize/320x203!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb4%2Fcb%2F059edd274ff4adcb02b7241a412c%2Fimg-6323.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/dd95036/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1498x952+0+0/resize/568x361!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb4%2Fcb%2F059edd274ff4adcb02b7241a412c%2Fimg-6323.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/63e42f6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1498x952+0+0/resize/768x488!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb4%2Fcb%2F059edd274ff4adcb02b7241a412c%2Fimg-6323.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3f4e67b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1498x952+0+0/resize/1024x651!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb4%2Fcb%2F059edd274ff4adcb02b7241a412c%2Fimg-6323.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0faec13/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1498x952+0+0/resize/1200x763!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb4%2Fcb%2F059edd274ff4adcb02b7241a412c%2Fimg-6323.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="763"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0faec13/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1498x952+0+0/resize/1200x763!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb4%2Fcb%2F059edd274ff4adcb02b7241a412c%2Fimg-6323.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">The Lorenzo sandwich from Lorenzo California in Beverly Hills. </div><div class="figure-credit">(Wonho Frank Lee)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>The new L.A. sandwiches I can&#x27;t stop eating</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/jenn-harris">        Jenn Harris    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 5, 2023">June 5, 2023</time>                                                                            <time class="op-modified" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                            </header>                    <b>The new sandwiches everyone should be talking about</b><b>This new sandwich shop is making a $35 sandwich masterpiece</b><b>Where to find your new favorite sandwich</b><b>The L.A. sandwiches I can't stop eating</b><b>If you love Italian subs, this is the sandwich for you </b><b>If you love Italian subs, you might like this even better</b><b>The new Italian sandwich I can't stop eating</b><b>Is this new Italian sandwich shop better than Bay Cities? </b><p>There's no shortage of excellent sandwiches in Los Angeles. For the pastrami on double-baked rye fans, there's <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/dailydish/la-fo-re-langers-20181213-story.html">Langer's Deli</a>. If anyone tells you another pastrami sandwich is better, they're wrong. </p><p>A few years back, I put together a list of the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2020-03-14/best-italian-sub-sandwich">best Italian subs</a> in the city. It includes more than a dozen. </p><p>The <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2022-11-28/pumpkin-spice-latte-dizi-bub-and-grandmas">tuna salad sandwich</a> at Bub &amp; Grandma's in Glassell Park is a lunchtime hero. The <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2022-07-11/bone-marrow-birria-tacos-fried-mushrooms">beetroot Reuben</a> at Loam in Downtown L.A. is a revelation that will capture the hearts of both carnivores and vegetarians. </p><p>Here are two more sandwiches to add to the list of the city's best. Ideal for your next power lunch, beach picnic, or whatever situation calls for stuff between bread. </p>All the sandwiches at Lorenzo California<figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/d6/a6/22651e5e417fabb6d47a8b2df3c7/img-6442-1.jpg"></figure><p>In the fall of 2019, Renato Araujo and his wife, Cynthia Raslan, spent a month in Florence eating sandwiches. Araujo, a longtime restaurant manager in Los Angeles, was on a research trip to find the best. Earlier that year, he and his wife decided to take the money they had saved to buy a house, and open a sandwich shop</p>,<p> instead. </p><p>On one of the couple's treks to try a new sandwich, Araujo couldn't find the shop. While they walked up and down the streets of Florence, they spotted a family with a little boy. They were so taken with him, they stopped to say hello. </p><p>"He was dressed up like a gentleman," he said. "I told him, 'Man, you dressed up so nice.' I asked what his name was, and he said 'Lorenzo.'" </p><p>The family happened to be standing in front of the sandwich shop. </p><p>"We stopped to talk to the family because of the little boy," he said. "We never would have found the place. When we were wondering what to call our place, me and my wife looked at each other and both said 'Lorenzo.'" </p><p>The pandemic hit shortly after their return to Los Angeles, and their plans to open a shop were put on hold. After three years, Lorenzo California opened on Little Santa Monica in Beverly Hills in March. </p><p>The sandwiches are modeled after the ones he ate in Florence: minimal ingredients on good bread. </p><p>Federico Fernandez, co-owner and executive pastry chef at <a href="http://www.biancalosangeles.com/">Bianca</a> restaurant in Culver City, bakes the bread for the shop at 4 a.m. every morning. It's a variation on focac</p> c<p>ia, though baked into individual rectangles versus large pans that need to be cut. It's thinner, and lighter too, with a crust that cracks but doesn't quite fracture. With good extra-virgin olive oil and flaky sea salt, the rustic flavor of focac</p> c<p>ia is there, without the dense, heavy middle. </p><p>The bread is baked once a day, with enough to make about 75 sandwiches. Once they're out, that's it for the day. </p><p>Raslan takes the orders next to the deli case and Araujo slices the meats and builds the sandwiches to order. </p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/59/67/eb306dc44914b78281dcad461bb1/img-6441.jpg"></figure><p>The fennel-tinged finocchiona salame on the Salamino sandwich is shaved so thinly, it seems to melt right into the cushion of silky parmigiano sauce and sliced, oil-soaked artichokes. </p><p>The namesake sandwich, the Lorenzo, features the same parmigiano sauce, made with boiled and blended cream and parmigiano reggiano, along with roasted red peppers, toasted pistachios and pale pink sheets of mortadella. The flavors are simple</p>, and <p>direct</p> and poignant<p>, though Araujo said some purists still come in asking for sliced mortadella on bread.</p><p>The most extravagant offering is the Zola, constructed with meaty, almost smoky </p>B b<p>resaola, a drizzle of truffle honey, white onion agrodol</p> c<p>e and gorgonzola cheese. It's a whopping $35. The sticker shock is less of a shock when you account for the shower of fresh, shaved black truffle over the finished sandwich. </p><p>In the near future, Araujo plans to switch off the lights in the deli case in the evenings and open for dinner with a full menu of pasta and wine. </p>Venice Cowgirl at Lady &amp; Larder<figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/b2/a8/3f4e2efa4bce818d20774dcdb03e/venice-cowgirl.jpeg"></figure><p>More than any other sandwich in Los Angeles, the Venice Cowgirl at Lady &amp; Larder, the petite cheese shop and superette in Santa Monica, evokes a moment in time and a sense of place in the city. Its annual reappearance on the menu signals the start of summer. More than frozen desserts, salads or barbecue. </p><p>Sisters and co-owners Sarah and Boo Simms dreamed up the sandwich, as they do with all the sandwiches at the shop, as a way to frame a particular cheese. The star of the Venice Cowgirl is Cowgirl Creamery's Mt. Tam triple cream. They slice the cheese into thick tiles and layer them on a crusty Clark Street Bread baguette with habanero and apricot jam, sliced nectarines, basil, wild arugula, extra virgin olive oil and salt. </p><p>"People don't always think of sandwiches as seasonal, but for us, they are super seasonal," Sarah said during a recent call. "The Venice Cowgirl just came back, and it's only available during stone fruit season."</p><p>The nectarines may change to peaches, depending on what's available. Last week's nectarines were heavy with sunshine and sugar, ripe but not overly soft. They were the perfect counterpart to the bloomy rind cheese, with a slight firmness around the edges that turns to butter toward</p>s<p> the middle. If you happen to get a bite with more cheese than fruit, expect a wallop of raw white mushrooms. </p><p>The basil might be Thai basil, purple basil and/or green Genovese, both floral and bright. The Simms buy their pepper jelly from Suze McClellan of Ojai Jelly, who drives to L.A. to hand-deliver</p>y<p> jars. The sweet heat of the jelly reminds the sisters of the appetizers their mother would put out for company, typically a soft, young bright cheese accompanied by pepper jelly. </p><p>The specific combination made me greedy and giddy, the way I feel after an especially fruitful summer trip to the farmers market with my arms sore from heavy bags of cherries and stone fruit. There's just enough good stuff crammed between the baguette to make me want more. More nectarines. More cheese. More pepper jam. </p><p>"It has all the things you want, salty, sweet, acid, texture," Sarah said. "All the things that bring us joy in a sandwich." </p><p>The Simms started making the sandwiches during COVID, when their orders for cheese and charcuterie trays dwindled with the shutdown and subsequent cancellation of events and parties across the city. There are typically two to three varieties wrapped and ready to grab off the counter. </p><p>The Venice Cowgirl will only be around while stone fruit is in season. Get it while you can. </p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crab recipes to switch up weekday meals</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/newsletter/2023-06-04/crab-recipes-to-switch-up-weekday-meals-cooking-editorial</link>
      <description>The often-overlooked, pre-picked, jumbo lump crab meat that shines in sandwiches, salads and fried cakes is great for shaking up meals at this time of year.</description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2023 15:00:21 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/newsletter/2023-06-04/crab-recipes-to-switch-up-weekday-meals-cooking-editorial</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This South Bay sushi shop has been serving the same six items for decades — and wants to keep it that way</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-03/sakae-sushi-gardena-futomaki-south-bay</link>
      <description>Sakae Sushi has been making simple, homestyle sushi in Gardena since the 1960s. Every piece on the six-item menu is inexpensive and delicious.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 11:00:17 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-03/sakae-sushi-gardena-futomaki-south-bay</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Should we be eating bluefin tuna?</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-03/should-i-eat-bluefin-tuna-what-experts-say</link>
      <description>Served nearly everywhere to sushi lovers, whether or not we should be eating bluefin tuna still is still hotly debated among consumers and conservation experts alike.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 11:00:58 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-03/should-i-eat-bluefin-tuna-what-experts-say</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wild or farmed? Pacific or Atlantic? Here's what to know about bluefin tuna</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-03/wild-farmed-pacific-atlantic-bluefin-tuna-species</link>
      <description>The more you know about bluefin tuna, the better equipped you are to make decisions about whether to consume it.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 11:00:10 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Jean Trinh</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-03/wild-farmed-pacific-atlantic-bluefin-tuna-species</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-03/wild-farmed-pacific-atlantic-bluefin-tuna-species">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8bd1b11/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F87%2F9e%2F3a4ffbd440c3a4c4bcaaba40bb01%2Ffo-sushi-bluefin-tuna-sidebar.png 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3a0aec1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F87%2F9e%2F3a4ffbd440c3a4c4bcaaba40bb01%2Ffo-sushi-bluefin-tuna-sidebar.png 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2b63cb5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F87%2F9e%2F3a4ffbd440c3a4c4bcaaba40bb01%2Ffo-sushi-bluefin-tuna-sidebar.png 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b55f72e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F87%2F9e%2F3a4ffbd440c3a4c4bcaaba40bb01%2Ffo-sushi-bluefin-tuna-sidebar.png 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a3227dd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F87%2F9e%2F3a4ffbd440c3a4c4bcaaba40bb01%2Ffo-sushi-bluefin-tuna-sidebar.png 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Illustration of Pacific bluefin tuna"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/600b8ad/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F87%2F9e%2F3a4ffbd440c3a4c4bcaaba40bb01%2Ffo-sushi-bluefin-tuna-sidebar.png 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/bbab445/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F87%2F9e%2F3a4ffbd440c3a4c4bcaaba40bb01%2Ffo-sushi-bluefin-tuna-sidebar.png 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6f36fb6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F87%2F9e%2F3a4ffbd440c3a4c4bcaaba40bb01%2Ffo-sushi-bluefin-tuna-sidebar.png 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f8a41a0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F87%2F9e%2F3a4ffbd440c3a4c4bcaaba40bb01%2Ffo-sushi-bluefin-tuna-sidebar.png 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1709fdb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F87%2F9e%2F3a4ffbd440c3a4c4bcaaba40bb01%2Ffo-sushi-bluefin-tuna-sidebar.png 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1709fdb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F87%2F9e%2F3a4ffbd440c3a4c4bcaaba40bb01%2Ffo-sushi-bluefin-tuna-sidebar.png"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-credit">(Brandon Ly / Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Wild or farmed? Pacific or Atlantic? Here&#x27;s what to know about bluefin tuna</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" >        Jean Trinh    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="May 3, 2023">May 3, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Although bluefin tuna is commonly found at sushi restaurants throughout Los Angeles, many diners might not be aware of what it means to eat a particular species or how its sourced. The more you know about bluefin tuna, the better equipped you are to make decisions about whether to consume it.</p><p>Known for its blueish-black and silver hues and torpedo-shaped body, bluefin tunas are magnificent creatures with ravenous appetites. Large and fast, they can swim up to 43 miles per hour. There are three species of bluefin tuna, each with its own unique migration pattern, varied diet, size</p>,<p> and lifespan.</p> Should we be eating bluefin tuna? It's complicated<figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/ec/1d/547854244157a4e6bc1345a20a2d/fo-sushi-bluefin-tuna-sidebar-down2-pacific.png"></figure><p><b>Pacific bluefin tuna </b>are born in the Sea of Japan before making a</p>n over<p> 5,000-mil</p> e-plus<p> migration to the California coast, where they feed and grow for years. They travel up and down the Pacific coast between Mexico to Washington before trekking back to Japan to spawn. While Pacific bluefin tuna can live up to 26 years, </p> theirits<p> average lifespan is 15. A Pacific bluefin typically reaches maturity at 5 years </p> old<p>, and adults are about 5 feet long and 130 pounds. Predatory creatures, their diet usually consists of squid and fish like sardines and anchovies.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/c0/40/3011e28344919ed2a3750341c80b/fo-sushi-bluefin-tuna-sidebar-down1-atlantic.png"></figure><p><b>Atlantic bluefin tuna</b> spawn in the Gulf of Mexico and Mediterranean Sea and migrate across the </p> e<p>astern and </p> w<p>estern Atlantic Ocean. Theyre often fished and ranched in Spain, Malta</p>,<p> and Croatia, as well as Boston and Canada. The largest of the three species of bluefin, they can live more than 20 years and grow to 13 feet and 2,000 pounds. The adults feed on fish like herring, bluefish</p>,<p> and mackerel.</p><p><b>Southern bluefin tuna</b> spawn in the Indian Ocean and migrate across the Pacific, Atlantic and Indian oceans. Theyre fished in Australia, New Zealand, Indonesia and South Africa. They can live up to 40 years, and grow up to 8 feet long and</p>  more thanover<p> 550 pounds. They feed on fish, cephalopods (like squid and octopus), crustaceans and salps.</p><p>Monterey Bay Aquariums sustainable</p> -<p>seafood program <a href="https://www.seafoodwatch.org/">Seafood Watch</a> recommends consumers avoid eating all types of bluefin tuna, whether wild-caught or farmed</p> , but its population status is complicated and data are always in flux<p>. </p> Some experts say it is    OK  okay to eat all three species at this juncture because fish management has improved tremendously in the last decade, though Pacific bluefin regulations have only recently been proven to be more effective. LINK TO MAIN STORYOthers point to the improvement of fish management in the last several years. Dr. Victor Restrepo of<p><a href="https://www.iss-foundation.org/"> International Seafood Sustainability Foundation</a></p> says its fine to eat all three species at this juncture. However, Restrepo says he understands how some might be hesitant to eat Pacific bluefin because its fish management regulations have only been proven to be more effective recently, a contrast from Southern and Atlantic bluefin, which have had more than a decade of better fish management history.<p>Bluefin tuna can be wild-caught, farmed or ranched. Here is how they're sourced: </p><p><b>Wild: </b>There are bluefin tuna that are caught in the wild in a number of ways, from </p>utilizing <p>purse seine (a large netting), to trolling (luring through lines of bait) and harpoon gear. </p> A main issue is by -catch: fisheries incidentally also catching other important but non-target creatures from the  food web of the ecosystem.<p><b>Ranched: </b>Most of the farmed bluefin tuna are actually considered ranched. When a bluefin tuna is ranched, fish farmers will catch juvenile ones in the wild and move them into pens, where they are fattened until they reach sushi-grade quality and sold in the markets. But theyre still technically considered wild even if theyre</p> farmed ranched <p>since fisheries still pluck them from the wild stock.</p><p><b>Farmed</b>: There </p> is anare<p> effort</p>s<p> with bluefin tuna, particularly the Pacific species, called closed-cycle farming thats more like true fish farming. Fish eggs from farm-raised parents are artificially hatched into larvae in laboratories and then transferred to ocean pens. Kindai University (formerly known as Kinki University) in Japan was the first in the world to succeed in captive breeding with a fully farmed bluefin tuna in 2002. Others have followed suit, but still, its a niche product and the amount that enters the market is too small to make a major impact at the moment.</p><p>In regard to taste, farmed and ranched bluefin tuna are considered fattier than wild-caught. The flavor profiles are different as well. Since farmed bluefin tuna is typically fed pellets and sardines, the taste is different from wild tuna </p> withthat has <p>a varied diet, which often result</p> s<p> in more complex flavors.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tell your friends: 'I know a dancer who makes the best vegan sushi in L.A.'</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-03/best-vegan-sushi-in-los-angeles-yoko-hasebe</link>
      <description>Dancer and chef Yoko Hasebe launched Plant Sushi Yoko, a pickup and delivery service with the best vegan sushi in Los Angeles.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 11:00:54 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-03/best-vegan-sushi-in-los-angeles-yoko-hasebe</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dry-aged sushi? One of L.A.’s best fishmongers says 'fresh is boring'</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-04/sushi-dry-aged-fish-the-joint-los-angeles-liwei-liao</link>
      <description>The owner of the Joint talks seafood, preservation and a sprawling new facility that will bring dry-aged fish to the masses.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 12:00:40 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-04/sushi-dry-aged-fish-the-joint-los-angeles-liwei-liao</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The secret history of L.A.'s sushi revolution</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-05-03/l-a-s-sushi-revolution</link>
      <description>Sushi's norm-busting journey from culinary curiosity to mainstream L.A. offering was set in motion in the 1960s by two friends bound by a love for food.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 11:00:07 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-05-03/l-a-s-sushi-revolution</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supermarket sushi you'll actually want to eat</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-04/who-makes-the-best-supermarket-sushi-los-angeles</link>
      <description>Where to find the best supermarket sushi in Los Angeles — seared salmon nigiri, the freshest sashimi platters, hand rolls filled with negitoro and more.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 12:00:59 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-04/who-makes-the-best-supermarket-sushi-los-angeles</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grab quick, affordable sushi at 11 of the best hand roll bars in L.A.</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-hand-roll-bars-in-los-angeles</link>
      <description>The best hand roll bars in Los Angeles are part of the fabric of the city's sushi scene, serving delicious, super-fresh temaki at affordable prices.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 12:00:08 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-hand-roll-bars-in-los-angeles</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ultimate California roll lives on at this SGV fish market. (Fights at the sushi case prove it.)</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-05/best-california-roll-sushi-yama-san-gabriel-valley-fish-market</link>
      <description>An ode to the secretly best California roll, perfected over two decades at Yama Seafood in the San Gabriel Valley.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 12:00:36 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-05/best-california-roll-sushi-yama-san-gabriel-valley-fish-market</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The key to making easy sushi at home? Throw a hand roll party</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-05/sushi-party-at-home-how-to-make-a-hand-roll-temaki</link>
      <description>It's a hand roll party: This is an easy guide to making temaki sushi at home. Pile on the avocado, carrots, cucumbers, radish sprouts, spicy mayo and/or raw or tinned fish. Don't forget the salsa macha.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 May 2023 12:00:49 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-05/sushi-party-at-home-how-to-make-a-hand-roll-temaki</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 places in L.A. to find the best sushi, omakase, chirashi and more</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/the-best-sushi-bars-in-los-angeles</link>
      <description>From 20-course omakase tasting menus to snug sushi bars, here's where to find the best and freshest sushi in Los Angeles.</description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2023 12:00:17 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/the-best-sushi-bars-in-los-angeles</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What makes L.A.’s sushi scene so great? I found answers in Tokyo</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-04/tokyo-sushi-origins-los-angeles-omakase-history-chefs-rice</link>
      <description>The current generation of omakase chefs in Los Angeles are returning to the essence of the cuisine. A trip to Tokyo confirms what's been driving their pursuit for excellence.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2023 12:00:45 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-04/tokyo-sushi-origins-los-angeles-omakase-history-chefs-rice</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Los Angeles is the epicenter of sushi in America</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-03/los-angeles-is-best-sushi-city-world-america</link>
      <description>From vegan sushi to hand rolls, modest supermarket sushi to high-end omakase — the greater-than-ever scene in L.A. has what you're looking for.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 11:00:59 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-03/los-angeles-is-best-sushi-city-world-america</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bar Chelou — where things get 'weird' — serves a jolt of eccentricity to Pasadena</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-25/review-bar-chelou-pasadena-addison-weird</link>
      <description>Chef Douglas Rankin and pastry chef Raymond Morales from Silver Lake's now-closed Bar Restaurant have reunited at Bar Chelou next to the Pasadena Playhouse.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 14:00:08 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-25/review-bar-chelou-pasadena-addison-weird</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is this Koreatown upstart the future of fine dining in L.A.?</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-18/kinn-koreatown-tasting-menu-bill-addison-review</link>
      <description>What does modern Korean cooking taste like in Los Angeles? A chef with a tiny restaurant and concise tasting menu offers a compelling answer.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 14:52:27 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-18/kinn-koreatown-tasting-menu-bill-addison-review</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Power and celebrity still pulse at the Ivy, even if Bennifer has moved on</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-04-13/the-ivy-restaurant-los-angeles-review</link>
      <description>The menu at people-watching hangout the Ivy, open since 1980, is unfocused enough that it works in the restaurant's favor. But did you really come for the food?</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2023 17:25:06 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-04-13/the-ivy-restaurant-los-angeles-review</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>With a new spin on tinned fish, Saltie Girl is a standout on the Sunset Strip</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-02-26/for-tinned-seafood-lobster-roll-splurges-head-to-west-hollywood-new-seafood-sensation</link>
      <description>The new restaurant Saltie Girl in West Hollywood feels calibrated for indulgence — on lobster rolls and tinned fish.</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2023 03:09:01 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-02-26/for-tinned-seafood-lobster-roll-splurges-head-to-west-hollywood-new-seafood-sensation</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>L.A.'s next great comfort food? Find it at hidden Luyixian in Alhambra</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-02-02/luyixian-lu-rou-fan-pork-rice-bill-addison-review-alhambra</link>
      <description>Order the San Gabriel Valley newcomer's lu rou fan, glazed pork belly served with rice and a collage of condiments — just one of Luyixian's braised specialties.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 14:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-02-02/luyixian-lu-rou-fan-pork-rice-bill-addison-review-alhambra</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Find comforting Syrian breakfast at this backyard pop-up near Dodger Stadium</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-01-19/nawal-solano-canyon-syrian-circassian-pop-up-review-bill-addison</link>
      <description>Two brothers create a totally unique Syrian-Circassian culinary experience at Nawal, their weekend backyard pop-up</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2023 17:56:50 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-01-19/nawal-solano-canyon-syrian-circassian-pop-up-review-bill-addison</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>These are the 101 best restaurants in Los Angeles</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/101-best-los-angeles-restaurants-ranked-2022</link>
      <description>If you're searching for the essential food of L.A., let our critic's 2022 restaurant list be your guide! Find the best vegetarian, Italian, Mexican and more.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 04:00:36 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/101-best-los-angeles-restaurants-ranked-2022</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hall of Fame restaurants: These all-time modern classics are quintessential L.A.</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/los-angeles-hall-of-fame-restaurants-modern-classics</link>
      <description>These restaurants are so defining of what it means to eat and live in Southern California — that they’ve earned a place of honor for all time.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 04:00:08 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/los-angeles-hall-of-fame-restaurants-modern-classics</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cocktails and coffee, beer and cider, chocolate and wine: Where to get L.A.’s best drinks</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-los-angeles-cocktails-coffee-beer-cider-chocolate-tea-wine-drinks</link>
      <description>Feeling thirsty? Here are the 10 best places around Los Angeles for drinks.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 04:01:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-los-angeles-cocktails-coffee-beer-cider-chocolate-tea-wine-drinks</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The most affordable options from the 101 Best Restaurants in L.A. list</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/most-affordable-options-from-101-best-restaurants-in-los-angeles-list-2022</link>
      <description>Whether they serve burritos, rotis, pizza, bagels or curries, the deliciousness delivered at these 16 Los Angeles establishments far outweighs their cost.</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 16:00:06 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/most-affordable-options-from-101-best-restaurants-in-los-angeles-list-2022</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 of downtown L.A.'s best restaurants from the 101 guide</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/15-stellar-downtown-restaurants-from-the-2022-101-guide</link>
      <description>Bookmark this roundup of the best restaurants in downtown L.A. from L.A. Times Food's 2022 101 Restaurants guide.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 16:41:32 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/15-stellar-downtown-restaurants-from-the-2022-101-guide</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>49 rooftop restaurants and bars in L.A. to soak in the best city views</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-rooftop-restaurants-and-bars-in-los-angeles</link>
      <description>From downtown skyscrapers to the Hollywood Hills and views of the Pacific Ocean, get outdoors to enjoy the best rooftop restaurants and bars in L.A. for the summer season and beyond.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 13:00:02 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-rooftop-restaurants-and-bars-in-los-angeles</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pinkies up! 15 of the best spots to sip high tea like a royal</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/where-to-have-a-proper-tea-service-in-los-angeles</link>
      <description>From hotel courtyards to rose gardens and British pubs, these are the best places to indulge in afternoon tea service in Los Angeles and Orange County for Mother's Day or any occasion.</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 May 2023 13:00:45 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/where-to-have-a-proper-tea-service-in-los-angeles</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Where to eat and drink in L.A. right now, according to our food writers</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-new-restaurants-and-bars-in-los-angeles-may-2023</link>
      <description>Wondering where to eat in Los Angeles right now? Check out our guide to the best new restaurants and bars in L.A., from Italian cuisine to sandwich shops and barbecue.</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 13:00:22 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-new-restaurants-and-bars-in-los-angeles-may-2023</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>L.A. meets New Orleans when you put some zing in this springtime crab salad sandwich</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-01/los-angeles-new-orleans-crab-salad-sandwich-with-pickles</link>
      <description>Inspired by the sandwiches of both Galatoire's and Bub &amp; Grandma's, this tangle of crab meat on a warm buttered brioche bun has a bright, lemony vinaigrette, with pops of crunch and pickle-y punch from sugar snap peas and gherkins.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 14:05:52 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Ben Mims</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-01/los-angeles-new-orleans-crab-salad-sandwich-with-pickles</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-06-01/los-angeles-new-orleans-crab-salad-sandwich-with-pickles">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8ee94ba/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1080x720+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F35%2Ffe8c665d4468ab76b76fa5af39a7%2F1274972-fo-crab-sandwich.gif 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/99022af/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1080x720+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F35%2Ffe8c665d4468ab76b76fa5af39a7%2F1274972-fo-crab-sandwich.gif 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1e2458a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1080x720+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F35%2Ffe8c665d4468ab76b76fa5af39a7%2F1274972-fo-crab-sandwich.gif 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c9ce065/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1080x720+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F35%2Ffe8c665d4468ab76b76fa5af39a7%2F1274972-fo-crab-sandwich.gif 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/21190e2/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1080x720+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F35%2Ffe8c665d4468ab76b76fa5af39a7%2F1274972-fo-crab-sandwich.gif 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt=""                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5f7d43e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1080x720+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F35%2Ffe8c665d4468ab76b76fa5af39a7%2F1274972-fo-crab-sandwich.gif 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ae889ae/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1080x720+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F35%2Ffe8c665d4468ab76b76fa5af39a7%2F1274972-fo-crab-sandwich.gif 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/85beb93/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1080x720+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F35%2Ffe8c665d4468ab76b76fa5af39a7%2F1274972-fo-crab-sandwich.gif 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/215b487/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1080x720+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F35%2Ffe8c665d4468ab76b76fa5af39a7%2F1274972-fo-crab-sandwich.gif 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/67e2d34/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1080x720+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F35%2Ffe8c665d4468ab76b76fa5af39a7%2F1274972-fo-crab-sandwich.gif 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/67e2d34/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1080x720+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F35%2Ffe8c665d4468ab76b76fa5af39a7%2F1274972-fo-crab-sandwich.gif"        decoding="async"            ></picture>        </figure>                                                                            <h1>L.A. meets New Orleans when you put some zing in this springtime crab salad sandwich</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">Cooking</h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/ben-mims">        Ben Mims    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 1, 2023">June 1, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>In California</p>,<p> springtime, </p>always brings about a <p>burst</p> s<p> of beautiful flowers always </p>that <p>smell just as great as they look</p> . O<p>ne of my favorite things is walking through a neighborhood and getting an unexpected whiff of jasmine. Farmers markets are brimming with peas, young garlic,</p> and<p> onion shoots</p>,<p> and all sorts of first-of-the-season potatoes, fennel</p>,<p> and asparagus</p> and all other vegetables that turn us all into rabbit-like eaters that might inspire us to eat like rabbits <p>for a few months. But when I think of spring, particularly late April through early June, I always think of crab.</p><p>Growing up in the South, and when living on the East Coast, Id often take trips to New Orleans at this time of the year because the weather there is perfect;</p> this time of year,  when <p>the winter chill has </p>just <p>left but its not oppressively, humidly hot just yet. If youve been there at this time, you know that every restaurant in the city has one special on its menu: soft</p> -<p>shell crab. The crabs  almost always domestic blue crabs  molt their hard outer shells in the spring, leaving them with paper-thin exoskeletons. Theyre then plucked from the shallow waters and sold, ripe for dredging in flour and crisping up in the deep fryer. </p>In a time of <p>When instant </p>-<p>delivery</p>,<p> provid</p> esing<p> you with </p> just about <p>anything you want to eat at any time, you appreciate all the more a delicacy you can get for only a short time once a year.</p><p>And even if I eat at a restaurant there that doesnt have soft</p> -<p>shells, it's bound to have crab salad on the menu, especially if it's of the century-old-French-restaurant variety like Galatoires. I go</p>t<p> there specifically for the</p>ir<p> crab maison, a tangle of crab meat bound with mayonnaise spiked with Creole mustard and dotted with capers and scallions. The crab </p>fits the mold perfectly because it <p>is rich and the mustard, scallions and capers cut through that with a bracing punch that always wakes me up after waiting in line for an hour to get in. Its substantial but also feels light,</p> the<p> an ideal balance</p> of what you want to eat in springtime<p>.</p><p>Inspired by that salad and a renewed obsession with tuna salad sandwiches, brought about by the one at Bub &amp; Grandmas that also uses mustard  albeit the yellow Frenchs variety  Ive decided to start a new tradition of making myself a crab salad sandwich in spring. If I cant get to New Orleans for my yearly springtime crab ritual, I can at least re</p> -<p>create it in a new way for myself at home.</p><p>In lieu of mustard, though, I go with a bright, lemony vinaigrette; it has enough punch to cut through the richness of the crab without dominating the crustaceans flavor the way a yellow or Dijon mustard would. Going mayo-less is out of character for me, but in this instance it works wonderfully since the richness that mayo brings will be provided</p>brought<p>, in this sandwich, by a brioche roll toasted up with butter and some torn Castelvetrano olives. On top of the crab, those olives mix with a green, pickle-y duo of sugar snap peas and gherkins to add crunch and more pops of spring brightness.</p><p>As for the crab meat itself, it would be a nice fantasy to tell you that I boil and pick it myself, but why lie? I go to the butcher shop and buy the best that they have. And while the jumbo lump that Ive picked up from my local fishmonger was, indeed, creamier and richer than what I can find at the supermarket, I can attest that the crab from the supermarket also works fantastically well in this sandwich</p> too<p>. When you cloak the crab meat in a bright vinaigrette and pair it with plenty of crunchy spring things, its best qualities shine</p> no matter what<p>. Its a </p>treatise  treatment<p> that gives me the best of the nostalgia I have for crab in New Orleans but tailored to life in Southern California with all the fresh, veggie-forward flavors I now associate with the season.</p>Get the recipe:                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Everywhere you absolutely have to eat at Disneyland and California Adventure</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/the-best-places-to-eat-at-disneyland-and-california-adventure-anaheim</link>
      <description>From classic Disneyland bites like giant turkey legs and Dole Whip to barbecue and Cajun cuisine, this is your ultimate guide to the best places to eat at Disneyland Anaheim parks.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2023 12:00:04 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/the-best-places-to-eat-at-disneyland-and-california-adventure-anaheim</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The best cocktails, wine, beer and more to try at the Disneyland Resort</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-bars-breweries-alcohol-drinks-disneyland-california-adventure</link>
      <description>These are the best restaurants and bars that serve cocktails, beer and wine across Disneyland, California Adventure, Downtown Disney and Disneyland hotels.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2023 12:00:44 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-bars-breweries-alcohol-drinks-disneyland-california-adventure</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 spots to hit for the ultimate food and bar crawl at Downtown Disney</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-restaurants-bars-food-drinks-at-downtown-disney-anaheim</link>
      <description>These are your best dining and drinking options at Downtown Disney, including breweries, burgers, Italian food and a luxury bowling alley, with new locations of Porto's Bakery and Din Tai Fung coming soon.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2023 12:00:36 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/best-restaurants-bars-food-drinks-at-downtown-disney-anaheim</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Napa Rose is Disneyland’s top fine-dining destination. But does its magic need a refresh?</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-04-20/napa-rose-disneyland-fine-dining-review-bill-addison</link>
      <description>The flagship restaurant of Disney's Grand Californian Hotel brings charm to fine dining, but it needs an update to capture California's magic.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2023 12:00:08 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-04-20/napa-rose-disneyland-fine-dining-review-bill-addison</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 fast, affordable and delicious food finds at Disneyland and California Adventure</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/most-affordable-food-at-disneyland-and-california-adventure</link>
      <description>Save money on your Disneyland visit with these quick and affordable dining options that won't break the bank, including churros, popcorn, corn dogs and more.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2023 12:00:24 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/list/most-affordable-food-at-disneyland-and-california-adventure</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The plant-based restaurant boom</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/newsletter/2023-06-03/plant-based-vegan-restaurant-boom-love-life-tasting-notes-tasting-notes</link>
      <description>Plus, Saucy Chick meets the Goat Mafia, a reprieve for Jamie Lee Curtis' favorite steakhouse and a 'Succession' fan's search for 'Peter's special cheese' in Tasting Notes.</description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 14:00:42 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/newsletter/2023-06-03/plant-based-vegan-restaurant-boom-love-life-tasting-notes-tasting-notes</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Horses restaurant owners agree to resolve divorce drama</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-08/horses-restaurant-owners</link>
      <description>The Sunset Boulevard restaurant caught the food world's attention when Elizabeth Johnson made allegations about husband and co-owner Will Aghajanian.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 17:34:34 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Noah Goldberg</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-08/horses-restaurant-owners</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-08/horses-restaurant-owners">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6302f60/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4501x3215+0+0/resize/320x229!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F20%2Fc2%2F81daf6164de8a44ab253bc0e6eef%2F887692-fo-horses-restaurant-review-chef-51-gmf-2.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9656a64/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4501x3215+0+0/resize/568x406!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F20%2Fc2%2F81daf6164de8a44ab253bc0e6eef%2F887692-fo-horses-restaurant-review-chef-51-gmf-2.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/68ff7af/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4501x3215+0+0/resize/768x548!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F20%2Fc2%2F81daf6164de8a44ab253bc0e6eef%2F887692-fo-horses-restaurant-review-chef-51-gmf-2.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0b6a14c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4501x3215+0+0/resize/1024x731!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F20%2Fc2%2F81daf6164de8a44ab253bc0e6eef%2F887692-fo-horses-restaurant-review-chef-51-gmf-2.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/527579f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4501x3215+0+0/resize/1200x857!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F20%2Fc2%2F81daf6164de8a44ab253bc0e6eef%2F887692-fo-horses-restaurant-review-chef-51-gmf-2.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="LOS ANGELES, CA - DECEMBER 23, 2021: Chef Will Aghajanian preps food before dinner service at Horses restaurant on December 23, 2021 in Los Angeles, California.(Gina Ferazzi / Los Angeles Times)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d17558b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4501x3215+0+0/resize/320x229!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F20%2Fc2%2F81daf6164de8a44ab253bc0e6eef%2F887692-fo-horses-restaurant-review-chef-51-gmf-2.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c73e45b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4501x3215+0+0/resize/568x406!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F20%2Fc2%2F81daf6164de8a44ab253bc0e6eef%2F887692-fo-horses-restaurant-review-chef-51-gmf-2.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2238083/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4501x3215+0+0/resize/768x548!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F20%2Fc2%2F81daf6164de8a44ab253bc0e6eef%2F887692-fo-horses-restaurant-review-chef-51-gmf-2.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/92bd617/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4501x3215+0+0/resize/1024x731!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F20%2Fc2%2F81daf6164de8a44ab253bc0e6eef%2F887692-fo-horses-restaurant-review-chef-51-gmf-2.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/71d5d6d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4501x3215+0+0/resize/1200x857!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F20%2Fc2%2F81daf6164de8a44ab253bc0e6eef%2F887692-fo-horses-restaurant-review-chef-51-gmf-2.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="857"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/71d5d6d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4501x3215+0+0/resize/1200x857!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F20%2Fc2%2F81daf6164de8a44ab253bc0e6eef%2F887692-fo-horses-restaurant-review-chef-51-gmf-2.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">LOS ANGELES, CA - DECEMBER 23, 2021: Chef Will Aghajanian preps food before dinner service at Horses restaurant on December 23, 2021 in Los Angeles, California.(Gina Ferazzi / Los Angeles Times)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Gina Ferazzi/Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Horses restaurant owners agree to resolve divorce drama </h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/noah-goldberg">        Noah Goldberg    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 8, 2023">June 8, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>The co-owners of the trendy restaurant Horses that was thrown into chaos over traded allegations of animal abuse and domestic violence settled their dispute this week, </p> with the husband-wife duo agreeing to conditions stipulated by their divorce attorneys<p>. </p><p>The hip</p>,<p> Sunset Boulevard restaurant caught the attention of the food world last month when <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-05-17/horses-chef-kittens-killing-restaurant-wife-hollywood-divorce-filing">The Times reported allegations</a> made by Elizabeth Johnson in court documents that her husband and co-owner, Will Aghajanian, had killed numerous family cats and physically abused her. Aghajanian denied the claims and said that it was Johnson who abused animals and assaulted him.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/7d/3f/c6958acd48eab56c0deccef18a2c/891115-fo-horses-feature-53-gmf.jpg"></figure><p>Johnson requested and was granted a domestic violence restraining order in the family court case in December, while Aghajanian's request for a restraining order was not granted by a judge. </p><p>The duo resolved their family court case Monday, with their lawyers stipulating to conditions by which the husband and wife would abide. </p><p>Aghajanian and Johnson "are enjoined and restrained from harassing, attacking, striking, threatening, assaulting (sexually or otherwise)" each other, according to the document. </p>Aghajnaian  Aghajanian<p> is also required to stay at least 100 yards from the family's dogs  Pancho, Javi and Spud. </p><p>The pair must also remain 100 yards from each other, though the judge said that can be lowered to 10 feet when they are working at Horses or their other restaurant Froggy's</p> , &nbsp;<p>which was supposed to open soon in New York.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The unwanted Uber Eats deliveries are back — and recipients are so over the free fries</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-07/uber-eats-deliveries-return-la-mystery-scam</link>
      <description>A fresh run of unsolicited Uber Eats deliveries in Highland Park has vexed residents, with mystifying conveyances from McDonald's, Starbucks and other restaurants.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 12:00:32 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Daniel Miller</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-07/uber-eats-deliveries-return-la-mystery-scam</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-07/uber-eats-deliveries-return-la-mystery-scam">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/480e6db/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6172x3976+0+0/resize/320x206!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F84%2F97%2F8aa3fb344a5f9ffdba785be63dec%2F1304122-me-0602-uber-eats-mystery-highland-park-cmh-03.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d1360de/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6172x3976+0+0/resize/568x366!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F84%2F97%2F8aa3fb344a5f9ffdba785be63dec%2F1304122-me-0602-uber-eats-mystery-highland-park-cmh-03.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d29267a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6172x3976+0+0/resize/768x495!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F84%2F97%2F8aa3fb344a5f9ffdba785be63dec%2F1304122-me-0602-uber-eats-mystery-highland-park-cmh-03.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/fea9dcd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6172x3976+0+0/resize/1024x660!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F84%2F97%2F8aa3fb344a5f9ffdba785be63dec%2F1304122-me-0602-uber-eats-mystery-highland-park-cmh-03.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d07a6ac/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6172x3976+0+0/resize/1200x773!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F84%2F97%2F8aa3fb344a5f9ffdba785be63dec%2F1304122-me-0602-uber-eats-mystery-highland-park-cmh-03.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Richie Kulchar with an unwanted Uber Eats order and his dog Molly at home in Highland Park."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/788a874/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6172x3976+0+0/resize/320x206!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F84%2F97%2F8aa3fb344a5f9ffdba785be63dec%2F1304122-me-0602-uber-eats-mystery-highland-park-cmh-03.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6d08862/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6172x3976+0+0/resize/568x366!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F84%2F97%2F8aa3fb344a5f9ffdba785be63dec%2F1304122-me-0602-uber-eats-mystery-highland-park-cmh-03.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/136481c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6172x3976+0+0/resize/768x495!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F84%2F97%2F8aa3fb344a5f9ffdba785be63dec%2F1304122-me-0602-uber-eats-mystery-highland-park-cmh-03.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/31b7a36/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6172x3976+0+0/resize/1024x660!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F84%2F97%2F8aa3fb344a5f9ffdba785be63dec%2F1304122-me-0602-uber-eats-mystery-highland-park-cmh-03.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b8b23cf/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6172x3976+0+0/resize/1200x773!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F84%2F97%2F8aa3fb344a5f9ffdba785be63dec%2F1304122-me-0602-uber-eats-mystery-highland-park-cmh-03.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="773"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b8b23cf/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6172x3976+0+0/resize/1200x773!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F84%2F97%2F8aa3fb344a5f9ffdba785be63dec%2F1304122-me-0602-uber-eats-mystery-highland-park-cmh-03.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">HIGHLAND PARK-CA-JUNE 2, 2023: Richie Kulchar, who has gotten several unwanted Uber Eats orders in recent days, is photographed with one of those orders and his dog Molly at home in Highland Park on June 2, 2023. (Christina House / Los Angeles Times)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Christina House/Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>The unwanted Uber Eats deliveries are back  and recipients are so over the free fries</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">For L.A. Times Subscribers</h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/daniel-miller">        Daniel Miller    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 7, 2023">June 7, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>The phone calls had stopped. So had the emails. Weeks went by. </p><p>The story seemed over.</p><p>Then a message flashed on my computer screen.</p><p>"Its starting again  ," the May 11 email from Highland Park resident Alison Perrine said.</p><p>She didn't have to say more. </p><p>It had been nearly two months since residents in the Northeast L.A. neighborhood last received <a href="https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-03-15/la-unwanted-uber-eats-mcdonalds-starbucks">unwanted food from Uber Eats</a>.</p><p>Her follow-up confirmed the return of an L.A. mystery: "Weve had 3 deliveries ... of a single order of McDonalds fries."</p><p>Starting in late February, bewildered </p> Highland Park <p>residents had been inundated with unsolicited orders ferried by drivers from Uber Eats. Now,<b> </b>I realized I'd be returning to Range View Avenue, the street<b> </b>at the center of the </p> whodunit<p>. </p><p>The first time around, errant meals piled up at front gates and on doorsteps amid a deluge that lasted a few weeks. Several people received more than 10 deliveries; one person got about 30, another about 40. Some residents were bemused, others annoyed. The unsolicited deliveries were in the names of other people, and mostly came from McDonald's and Starbucks. The food was paid for  and sometimes came with tips for the drivers, who, recipients said, mostly seemed undisturbed.</p><p>It was an odd (and rich) caloric tapestry. One order included four McDonalds McGriddles (two sausage, two chicken). Another consisted of a lone Starbucks iced matcha tea latte with a mocha drizzle. That concoction was far more complex than the beverages that most people received: kid-size cartons of milk and bottles of water  sometimes only one per order. It was these deliveries  the simplest of drinks in the smallest of quantities  that seemed to really weird people<b> </b>out.</p> A tasty L.A. mystery: Unwanted Uber Eats food deliveries vex Highland Park neighborhood<p>But residents said they hadn't received any additional unsolicited food in the weeks after The Times on May 15 published </p>an online<p> a <a href="https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-03-15/la-unwanted-uber-eats-mcdonalds-starbucks">story on their experience.</a> That is, until Perrine told me about the reemergence of the phenomenon.</p><p>Her note reignited the low-stakes </p> mystery<p>, which has highlighted the degree to which anonymity is woven into transactions carried out on the platforms of food delivery services, which have <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2020-09-19/the-state-of-food-delivery">grown dramatically</a> since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic. The free fast-food dispatches have led the denizens of Range View to develop a host of theories that would explain the bizarre situation. Others have weighed in too, including residents in Westwood Hills, where a <a href="https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-04-06/la-uber-eats-deliveries-mystery-driver-scam">similar episode unfolded</a> in late January and early February.</p><p>People in that tony Westside community posited that the unwanted orders were the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-04-06/la-uber-eats-deliveries-mystery-driver-scam">work of a burglary ring</a> that was casing houses by sending them food to see if anyone was home. No crime has been linked to the deliveries.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/46/6d/d7660bbf430b9e4eab6a819c40f7/1304122-me-0602-uber-eats-mystery-highland-park-cmh-09.jpg"></figure><p>As various hypotheses were cast aside  including one that speculated<b> </b>the orders were <a href="https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-03-15/la-unwanted-uber-eats-mcdonalds-starbucks">part of an experiment</a> conducted by a college psychology class and another that suggested they were the work of scammers phishing for <a href="https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-04-06/la-uber-eats-deliveries-mystery-driver-scam">drivers' Uber Eats login credentials</a>  a leading theory emerged. It centers on the deliveries being the ploy of criminals who are testing stolen credit cards by making small charges with them via Uber Eats.</p><p>I planned to ask residents about that during a visit to the neighborhood on May 31. But first I placed an Uber Eats order. I parked on Range View under a sky lidded with clouds and </p> chose<p> a coffee and a juice from Starbucks  the sort of small, inexpensive selection that's typical of the undesired </p> deliveries<p>. My aim was to talk </p> to <p>the courier transporting the drinks. The Uber Eats app said her name was Wysper and I hoped for some answers  the sort that the company hadn't yet provided. </p><p>A spokeswoman for Uber, the San Francisco-based parent of Uber Eats, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-04-06/la-uber-eats-deliveries-mystery-driver-scam">previously told The Times</a> that the company was investigating the matter and had banned some accounts from the platform while taking other unspecified steps to prevent misuse of the service. The reports of unsolicited deliveries are concerning, the Uber spokeswoman said in an April statement. We ... will not hesitate to take additional action if the unsolicited orders continue.</p><p>Asked to comment for this story, an Uber spokesman replied with that statement from April. </p> He did not answer a handful of questions, including one inquiring about the source of the offending orders.<p>Perhaps Wysper would have some insight?</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/97/40/782a2fc641ea9da93b26a09ce9d8/la-unwanted-uber-eats-mcdonalds-starbucks-7.jpg"></figure><p>A few minutes later, a red Nissan Versa pulled up to the curb and a smiling woman stepped out of the car with a Starbucks bag. She explained her name was Wysper Samone. I launched into a spiel about the situation.</p><p>"Oh, wow," said Samone, offering what figures to be the only appropriate response when a </p> Starbucks run <p>unexpectedly turns into an interview.</p><p>Samone said she hadn't made other deliveries on Range View and wasn't aware of the strange orders in Highland Park. But she did say<b> </b>that something similar had happened near Pico Rivera. She seemed busy, so I wished her well.</p><p>I reached Samone the next day by telephone and asked if she had a theory that would explain the phenomenon. But she demurred.</p><p>"I just pick up </p> and<p> deliver," Samone said. "That's all."</p>'Low-tier' criminals?<p>There was one house I knew I had to visit. </p><p>Back in March, there'd been a sign on its front door that exhorted Uber Eats couriers to "NOT LEAVE ANY ORDERS!"</p><p>Richie Kulchar opened his door, saw my Starbucks </p> bag<p> and started to laugh. He thought I was a neighbor inquiring about the new deliveries. That would have made sense: Three residents on Range View told The Times that they had received multiple orders in recent days; two other people who lived nearby, Perrine included, said </p>that<p> they had gotten several deliveries in mid-May. </p><p>"Every day it's one milk in a bag," said Kulchar, a commercial producer and director who lives on Avenue 50 near Range View. "I'm a pro at this now, I'm checking my credit cards, my Uber Eats account  none of it is showing up on there."</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/df/dc/c880bd554e78a6657421116aaa9f/1304122-me-0602-uber-eats-mystery-highland-park-cmh-06.jpg"></figure><p>At first, Kulchar said, he was amused by the situation. But after </p> enduring<p> five </p> deliveries<p> from May 26 to May 30, he's not laughing.<b> </b>The orders are often brought by couriers who pound on his front door, upsetting his dog, Molly.</p><p>"Now, I'm just annoyed with Uber Eats," Kulchar said. "I throw it away, which is a bummer because I really don't like wasting an unopened milk. But what am I going to do, stock it in my fridge?"</p><p>Kulchar believes the </p> deliveries<p> are the byproduct of "low-tier" criminals attempting to validate stolen credit card numbers. Range View resident <a href="https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-03-15/la-unwanted-uber-eats-mcdonalds-starbucks">Kelsey McManus agrees</a>. </p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/15/81/23c59dd04c20af2c655af32c0668/la-me-unwanted-uber-eats-delivery-01.jpg"></figure><p>She<b> </b>speculated that the effort could be AI-driven, noting that when some Uber Eats drivers have attempted to telephone the people who've placed the orders, the calls go to "nonexistent numbers." </p><p>We joked about using ChatGPT to solve the mystery. But when I queried the AI, it said that it couldn't "investigate specific incidents."</p><p>Asked if the unsolicited orders were part of an effort by criminals to test stolen credit card numbers, a spokesman for Uber said that it was a possibility the company was investigating. </p><p>Computer security and e-commerce expert </p>Dr.<p> Clifford Neuman wondered if the offending orders were placed by new Uber Eats accounts that were used just once, or whether they came from long-standing ones that made the purchases routinely. He also raised the issue of credit card charge-backs. </p><p>"You would think now </p> ... <p>months after this started, you would have gotten the charge-backs  which Uber would know about  when people saw it on their credit card statements," said Neuman, director of the USC Center for Computer Systems Security. </p><p>The Times asked Uber whether the unwanted orders have resulted in charge-backs and for information about the accounts making the purchases. </p> A spokesman said Uber could not share details of bad actors' methods and the company's response to them, because doing so would reveal internal processes to the offending parties.A 'boring-ass' prank?<p>A gnawing desire to "to know the answer</p>,<p>" has stuck with McManus.</p><p>"When you first tell people, they all go, 'Oh, it's a prank,'" </p>"<p> she said. "But it seems so much more systemic than that."</p><p>In an era of popular television shows built around elaborate reality-distorting ruses  among them Amazon Freevee's "Jury Duty" and HBO's "The Rehearsal"  the notion that the unwanted deliveries are part of a made-for-TV stunt has come up. But there's no evidence this is the case. </p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/92/ce/72a50b1b40debd4d1c3839a4fc00/1304122-me-0602-uber-eats-mystery-highland-park-cmh-08.jpg"></figure><p>Some residents think</p>,<p> maybe this is a prank of the more old-fashioned sort: one masterminded by college students.</p><p>Occidental College is<b> </b>just down the road from the affected portion of Range View, an eclectic stretch of about 25 houses and apartment buildings between Avenue 49 and Avenue 50. There is even a fraternity house on the block.</p><p>Wanting to ask the frat brothers if they had the inside scoop, I trudged up the front stairs of the house, snaking past a </p>front <p>yard teeming with overgrown weeds and discarded cans of Modelo Especial and Michelob Ultra. But no one was home  the </p>school<p> semester had ended. Another dead end.</p><p>Kulchar, in any case, doubted the theory.</p><p>"That's the most boring-ass prank that a college student could pull," he said.</p> Who's sending mystery Uber Eats orders to L.A. neighborhoods? The plot thickens<p>Walking past discarded ketchup packets that lined the stairs of the frat house, I was reminding of something </p> mentioned by <p>L.A.-based horror writer Lisa Morton, who called the whole episode a "cosmic comedy."</p><p>"Nothing really harmful is happening to these people, but it is beyond annoying and somewhat disturbing," said Morton, who contributed an unnerving short story to the 2021 anthology <a href="https://www.akashicbooks.com/catalog/speculative-los-angeles/" target="_blank">"Speculative Los Angeles,</a>" which offers largely bleak and futuristic visions of the city. "Maybe they have moved past it and accepted that it is going to be uncomfortable. Maybe that's how it is with these dystopian things we confront."</p><p>There was certainly something dystopian about the food waste generated by the ordeal. Some residents said they've eaten the free </p> fare<p> or donated it, but several others, Kulchar included, have been throwing it away. Morton gets it.</p><p>Food cloaked in mystery  mystery food, if you will  doesn't necessarily go down so easily. </p><p>"If I were getting this food, I'd be freaked out," she said. "I wouldn't eat it."</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>He fed farmworkers during the pandemic. Now chef Juan Sanjuan wants to make 'magic' in L.A.</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-03/he-fed-farmworkers-during-the-pandemic-now-chef-juan-sanjuan-wants-to-make-magic-in-la</link>
      <description>The son of restaurant owners from Jalisco, Mexico, distributed burritos to essential workers during the COVID outbreak. Now he wants to help other chefs who lost everything.</description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 12:30:56 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Alejandro Maciel</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-03/he-fed-farmworkers-during-the-pandemic-now-chef-juan-sanjuan-wants-to-make-magic-in-la</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-03/he-fed-farmworkers-during-the-pandemic-now-chef-juan-sanjuan-wants-to-make-magic-in-la">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/96310d0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1536x2048+0+0/resize/320x427!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffc%2Fec%2F23a9b2c44fe0ad5679367c1f7ae9%2Fjuan1.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/cdbec32/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1536x2048+0+0/resize/568x757!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffc%2Fec%2F23a9b2c44fe0ad5679367c1f7ae9%2Fjuan1.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/103e1b9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1536x2048+0+0/resize/768x1024!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffc%2Fec%2F23a9b2c44fe0ad5679367c1f7ae9%2Fjuan1.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/38c7549/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1536x2048+0+0/resize/1024x1365!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffc%2Fec%2F23a9b2c44fe0ad5679367c1f7ae9%2Fjuan1.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0caae7f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1536x2048+0+0/resize/1200x1600!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffc%2Fec%2F23a9b2c44fe0ad5679367c1f7ae9%2Fjuan1.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="El chef Juan Sanjuan en una de las jornadas de distribucin de alimentos durante la pandemia."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c221f1c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1536x2048+0+0/resize/320x427!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffc%2Fec%2F23a9b2c44fe0ad5679367c1f7ae9%2Fjuan1.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4c2f736/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1536x2048+0+0/resize/568x757!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffc%2Fec%2F23a9b2c44fe0ad5679367c1f7ae9%2Fjuan1.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/562b81c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1536x2048+0+0/resize/768x1024!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffc%2Fec%2F23a9b2c44fe0ad5679367c1f7ae9%2Fjuan1.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/bbbca74/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1536x2048+0+0/resize/1024x1365!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffc%2Fec%2F23a9b2c44fe0ad5679367c1f7ae9%2Fjuan1.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5b4c6b6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1536x2048+0+0/resize/1200x1600!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffc%2Fec%2F23a9b2c44fe0ad5679367c1f7ae9%2Fjuan1.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="1600"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5b4c6b6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1536x2048+0+0/resize/1200x1600!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffc%2Fec%2F23a9b2c44fe0ad5679367c1f7ae9%2Fjuan1.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">El chef Juan Sanjuan en una de las jornadas de distribucin de alimentos durante la pandemia.</div><div class="figure-credit">(Chefs Supporting Chefs)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>He fed farmworkers during the pandemic. Now chef Juan Sanjuan wants to make &#x27;magic&#x27; in L.A.</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">Jobs, Labor &amp; Workplace,Mexico &amp; the Americas,Immigration and the Border</h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/espanol/autor/alejandro-maciel">        Alejandro Maciel    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 3, 2023">June 3, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Chef Juan Sanjuan is known far and wide for his spectacular Mascota, Jalisco-style green pozole. Others of us know him for his powerful bravado voice that rates with the best of professional mariachis. </p><p>Still others, however, know him for his generous heart that led him to help thousands of people during the COVID pandemic.</p><p>Through his nonprofit organization <a href="https://chefssupportingchefs.org/contact" target="_blank">Chefs Supporting Chefs</a>, he managed to distribute burritos to workers considered <a href="https://online.ucpress.edu/msem/article/38/1/114/119824/Esenciales-pero-vulnerablestrabajadores-agricolas" target="_blank">essential</a> but who in practice were left with nothing.</p><p>It was very painful to see them suffering, so together with a group of chefs with whom I had worked on other projects, we decided to go to the agricultural fields to bring them some food and fun, recalls Sanjuan.</p><p>This effort was transformed into a true production line that came to produce up to 20,000 burritos a day that were handed out in<a href="https://www.latimes.com/espanol/california/articulo/2020-10-19/opinion-los-trabajadores-agricolas-son-los-que-mas-sufren-con-la-crisis-climatica" target="_blank"> various agricultural fields</a> in the Central Valley.</p><p>Some heated up the tortillas, others dished up the beans, others the meat or chicken, and so on, until we finished, exhausted but happy. We would set up an entire kitchen in a few hours, says Sanjuan.</p><p>&nbsp;</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/d4/80/464aa1d848abadf58a4259c01c46/578890.la.farm.workers.coronavirus26.JPG"></figure><p>Sanjuan, born in Montebello</p>  in the San Gabriel Valley,California, <p>knows exactly what he's talking about. Since he was a child he has been related to the gastronomic industry. His family founded the well-known <a href="https://www.gloriashp.com/contact-reservations" target="_blank">Gloria's Restaurant &amp; Bar,</a> which is a true Mexican food institution in Southern California.</p><p>My parents, who are originally from <a href="https://www.awaygowe.com/mascota-jalisco-visitor-guide/" target="_blank">Mascota, Jalisco</a>, taught me everything, from washing dishes and cooking to accounting. It was my turn, at 12 years old, to call the IRS to tell them that tomorrow we would send them the check," he says with a laugh.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/45/28/2e226845483fa1eb8dbc86542d02/62021924-2714962028518834-9210196365680836608-n.jpg"></figure><p><b>&nbsp;</b></p><p>Sanjuan fell ill with COVID in December 2021 and thought that he </p> mightcould <p>die when his <a href="https://www.bannerhealth.com/es/healthcareblog/teach-me/blood-oxygen-level-what-you-need-to-know" target="_blank">oxygen levels</a> dropped below 84 points.</p><p>I felt so bad that I prepared the documents expressing my last will, says Sanjuan.</p> Fortunately,Miraculously, <p>three months later he began to recover, and by April he managed to start walking.</p><p>The disease made him realize the fragility of life and that his own </p>life <p>had to have a higher meaning.</p><p>Facing death so closely had a very profound impact on me, he says, remembering the feeling of oxygen deprivation, exhaustion and faltering mental clarity.</p><p>He became certain that helping others was part of his mission, and realized how Chefs Supporting Chefs could fulfill it.</p><p>"It was something like a mystical revelation," he tells me with conviction.</p><p>One of the sectors most affected by the pandemic was the restaurant industry. <a href="https://time.com/6129713/restaurants-closing-covid-19/" target="_blank">Thousands of restaurants closed,</a> and chefs who had been laid off</p> from their jobs<p> and </p>who <p>had to do anything to survive could be found everywhere.</p><p>Some owners and workers quit the profession, while others began to develop small projects, such as <a href="https://la.eater.com/2020/10/26/21526105/los-angeles-food-trucks-pandemic-coronavirus-survival-covid-19" target="_blank">food trucks </a>or lunch boxes.</p><p>Juan Sanjuan was looking to start a new restaurant, so when he received a call from a friend offering him a place at 1111 W.</p> est<p> Olympic Boulevard</p>, in downtown Los Angeles,<p> he knew this was the summons he was waiting for.</p><p>"My restaurant is going to be called Experiencia 1111. I see it as something mystical," he says, explaining that at this new restaurant he'll serve all kinds of authentic Mexican dishes. I am not a fusion chef or what is considered 'haute cuisine.' My thing is traditional dishes with traditional flavors."</p><p>But it is not only the restaurant that he is interested in establishing. He wants to create a</p> pueblo mgico<p>, a <a href="https://www.gob.mx/sectur/articulos/pueblos-magicos-206528" target="_blank">magical town,</a> in the heart of Los Angeles.</p><p>I asked the owner of the premises, who also owns the alley that is in front of what will be the restaurant, to rent it to me. It's a space that's about 280 feet long by 60 feet wide, and that's where Chefs Supporting Chefs comes in."</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/3c/da/b93da83f484f803e9afb9e052488/la-sp-street-festival-0014.JPG"></figure><p>His idea is that in the alley, which is located </p> a couple of blocks west of the<p> <a href="https://www.lalive.com/" target="_blank">LA Live </a>complex, he'll create a Mexican-style market where street vendors can offer their products in a professional and hygienic manner.</p><p>All that generation of chefs that was greatly affected by the pandemic have started their own lunch box businesses, and it is they that we want to support, says Sanjuan.</p><p>Chefs Supporting Chefs will help them get permits from the department of health, put them in contact, through other nonprofit organizations with which we are working, such as the <a href="https://www.new-wbc.org/programs/ready-open-serve/" target="_blank">New Women's Business Center</a>, so that they can obtain loans and economic and business advice," </p> Sanjuan continues<p>. "We will help you register as a business and teach you the basics of bookkeeping and tax preparation. In the case of those merchants who do not have </p>a <p>social security numbers, they will be helped to obtain an ITIN."</p><p>Through T-Mobile, </p> Chefs Supporting Chefses correcto?<p> obtained 100 tablets for the street vendors who participate in this project to develop their social networks. A group of students will support them with digital marketing strategies.</p><p>And since one problem that street vendors face is assault, all transactions will be electronic.</p><p>Because the project requires funds to be able to offer these services for free or at a very low cost, there are plans to stage a series of cultural, gastronomic and musical events at the proposed market.</p><p>We want to bring a piece of Mexico to the heart of Los Angeles, says Sanjuan. Imagine a plaza where you can get barbecue, que mole, enchiladas, pan dulce or traditional desserts.</p><p>Part of the project's aim is to attract other organizations of street vendors, such as those on Avenida 26, to settle there and help establish a night market with a wide variety of regional dishes, in addition to the farmers market, where the same producers can sell their goods.</p><p>Cooking is exciting and requires exceptional talent. But that's only part of the business, says Sanjuan. The other part, the less fun part is how to run the business, pay taxes, get permits. Many times the success or failure of the company depends on that."</p><p>"That's why we want Chef Supporting Chefs to take care of that so they can get ahead, so they can build their Mexican dream of having a business in this country."</p><p>And that is only the beginning of a project that he plans to launch on July 11.</p><p>From his point of view, the model of the proposed market can be replicated throughout the city. "Where there is vacant land, we can put up a market, so that vendors can rotate from one place to another."</p><p>But his biggest goal is to help chefs who lost everything during the pandemic to get ahead, so they don't have to work for someone else.</p><p>"If you think it's less work, you're wrong, because having a business requires a sacrifice of 24 hours a day," says Sanjuan. "But what I can assure you is that, at the end of the day, one can go to sleep with the satisfaction of knowing that we are building our own future.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Padma Lakshmi to leave 'Top Chef' to focus on her 'Taste the Nation,' other projects</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2023-06-02/padma-lakshmi-leaves-top-chef-taste-the-nation</link>
      <description>Padma Lakshmi is leaving her "Top Chef" hosting duties after 19 seasons on the Bravo reality show. She wants to  focus on "Taste the Nation" and other projects.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2023 20:24:52 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Jonah Valdez</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2023-06-02/padma-lakshmi-leaves-top-chef-taste-the-nation</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2023-06-02/padma-lakshmi-leaves-top-chef-taste-the-nation">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b445e2a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1334+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbd%2F09%2F19ce93e943b1b704ee1ad714a7a5%2Fnup-198811-02061.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ae725a5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1334+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbd%2F09%2F19ce93e943b1b704ee1ad714a7a5%2Fnup-198811-02061.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/224c7cc/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1334+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbd%2F09%2F19ce93e943b1b704ee1ad714a7a5%2Fnup-198811-02061.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a83a4dc/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1334+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbd%2F09%2F19ce93e943b1b704ee1ad714a7a5%2Fnup-198811-02061.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b41fa7b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1334+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbd%2F09%2F19ce93e943b1b704ee1ad714a7a5%2Fnup-198811-02061.JPG 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="TOP CHEF -- Episode 2001 -- Pictured: (l-r) Tom Colicchio, Padma Lakshmi, Gail Simmons -- (Photo by: David Moir/Bravo)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/33e665e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1334+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbd%2F09%2F19ce93e943b1b704ee1ad714a7a5%2Fnup-198811-02061.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/73eee8e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1334+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbd%2F09%2F19ce93e943b1b704ee1ad714a7a5%2Fnup-198811-02061.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5ad6ae1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1334+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbd%2F09%2F19ce93e943b1b704ee1ad714a7a5%2Fnup-198811-02061.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/589f621/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1334+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbd%2F09%2F19ce93e943b1b704ee1ad714a7a5%2Fnup-198811-02061.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8796e5c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1334+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbd%2F09%2F19ce93e943b1b704ee1ad714a7a5%2Fnup-198811-02061.JPG 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8796e5c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1334+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbd%2F09%2F19ce93e943b1b704ee1ad714a7a5%2Fnup-198811-02061.JPG"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">TOP CHEF -- Episode 2001 -- Pictured: (l-r) Tom Colicchio, Padma Lakshmi, Gail Simmons -- (Photo by: David Moir/Bravo)</div><div class="figure-credit">(David Moir/Bravo)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Padma Lakshmi to leave &#x27;Top Chef&#x27; to focus on her &#x27;Taste the Nation,&#x27; other projects</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/jonah-valdez">        Jonah Valdez    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 2, 2023">June 2, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/books/jacketcopy/la-ca-jc-padma-lakshsmi-20160403-story.html">Padma Lakshmi</a> announced Friday that she will be leaving "<a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2022-04-21/top-chef-houston-jackson-kalb-restaurant-wars">Top Chef</a>" after hosting the Bravo reality competition show for the </p>past  last<p> 19 seasons.</p><p>During her 17-year run on the cooking series, the former fashion model and cookbook author offered her own blend of warmth and steely expertise for contestants and judges, earning her </p> more than a dozen 13<p> Primetime Emmy </p>award <p>nominations</p> and one win<p> for hosting and executive producing. </p><p>"After much soul searching, I have made the difficult decision to leave 'Top Chef,'" Lakshmi wrote in a note <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/Cs_nY3RM64A/?hl=en">posted      Friday   to her Instagram account</a>. "Having completed a glorious 20th season as host and executive producer, I am extremely proud to have been part of building such a successful show and of the impact it has had in the worlds of television and food."</p> That time Padma Lakshmi ate desert woodrat on 'Taste the Nation'<p>After calling the show's cast and crew "like family to me," Lakshmi said she "will miss working alongside them," but shared that she felt "it's time to move on and need to make space for '<a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/awards/story/2021-06-15/padma-lakshmi-taste-the-nation">Taste the Nation</a>,' my books and other creative pursuits."</p><p>Famously known as <a href="https://youtu.be/p-P5-7eV9GE?t=53">the only person who eats everything</a> made on 'Top Chef' (a contractual obligation), Lakshmi took over hosting duties </p>on <p>for the show's second season in 2006. She'd later serve as a judge and executive producer.</p><p>"Think of all the food that I have eaten," Lakshmi said in jest during a March interview on "<a href="https://youtu.be/44Vni02T2BU">Live With Kelly and Ryan</a>" to promote the 20th season. "It's a high</p> -<p>class problem to have, but it is a problem." She'd later estimate on "Jimmy Kimmel Live" her caloric count at about <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UMvsaHAs0f0&amp;ab_channel=JimmyKimmelLive">eight to nine thousand calories</a> a day during filming of the show. </p> 'Top Chef's' Padma Lakshmi hopes ex Salman Rushdie has 'swift healing' after attack<p>The finale of her final season, "<a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2023-03-08/top-chef-world-all-stars-bravo">Top Chef: World All-Stars</a>," which features winners and other contestants from previous international seasons, will air </p>on Thursday,<p> June 8. </p><p>After she made the announcement that </p> she wouldshe'd <p>finally <a href="https://youtu.be/mlXg_bu9ykE">pack her knives and go</a>, fellow "Top Chef" alum</p> s<p> celebrated Lakshmi's time on the show by showering her with well wishes online.</p><p>"End of an era and an incredible run," commented <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2023-01-06/ryan-seacrest-andy-cohen-new-years-eve-feud">Andy Cohen</a> beneath Lakshmi's post. "You were such an amazing partner and a BRILLIANT host. I have such great memories of our TC days." The "Watch What Happens Live" host also was an executive producer on "Top Chef." </p> 'Top Chef: World All-Stars' takes on London and celebrates a milestone season <p>Australian chef and Season 19 winner Buddha Lo<b> </b>wrote, "I feel honored to be a part of your magical journey."</p><p>"Love you Padma!" </p>said <p>actor Jesse Tyler Ferguson, who was a guest judge on the show</p> , said<p>. "I'm so glad that your show brought us together as friends."</p><p>"Thanks for making everything so special," gushed Bay Area chef </p> Monique Feybesse<p>, who was a contestant on Season 19. "Making us nervous whenever you came in the room and also proud to know we were cooking for you."</p> Padma Lakshmi explains why she left her knives packed when writing 'Love, Loss, and What We Ate' <p>In recent years, Lakshmi divided her time between "Top Chef" and filming her Hulu series</p>,<p> "Taste the Nation," in which she travels throughout the United States, visiting immigrant communities to highlight their food and cultures. Her show, which won a James Beard award for long-form visual media in 2022, released its second season for streaming last month. Earlier this year, Lakshmi was named to Time's 100 most influential people.</p><p>The La Puente native <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/awards/story/2021-06-15/padma-lakshmi-taste-the-nation">told The Times in 2021</a> that while filming "Taste the Nation," she embraced the freedoms from the cutthroat, competitive environment of "Top Chef," which has allowed her to more freely express her personality. </p><p>"When I got to Hulu, I said, 'Im tired of seeing women [being] careful about what they say, dressing a certain way, being coquettish. Men get to let it all hang out,'" she said. "I didnt want my appearance to be an issue. I wanted that to disappear. I wanted the opportunity to be my full self. I have a potty mouth. I eat till I explode. I have little filter. Like it or not, thats how it is when you hang out with me."</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The official fast-food burger power rankings</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2022-10-14/fast-food-burger-power-rankings</link>
      <description>One man's opinion on the best (and worst) fast-food burger chains.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 13:00:31 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2022-10-14/fast-food-burger-power-rankings</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Starbucks, Dunkin' and more: Who has the best frozen coffee drink?</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-01-05/starbucks-frappuccino-ice-blended-coffee-bean-showdown</link>
      <description>Our columnist evaluates sweet, frozen coffee drinks from Krispy Kreme, Starbucks, Dunkin' Donuts, the Coffee Bean &amp; Tea Leaf, Peet's Coffee, Panera Bread, McDonald's and Dutch Bros.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 14:00:31 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2023-01-05/starbucks-frappuccino-ice-blended-coffee-bean-showdown</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I tried every smoothie at Erewhon, including Hailey Bieber's $17 skincare smoothie</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2022-07-05/every-smoothie-at-erewhon-hailey-bieber-harrys-berries-coconut-cloud-guide-to-the-best</link>
      <description>Nowhere but the L.A. Times will you find smoothie content like this. Nowhere!</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 12:00:37 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2022-07-05/every-smoothie-at-erewhon-hailey-bieber-harrys-berries-coconut-cloud-guide-to-the-best</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The official Ben &amp; Jerry's ice cream power rankings</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2020-05-05/official-ben-jerrys-ice-cream-power-rankings</link>
      <description>One opinion on the best (and worst) Ben &amp; Jerry's flavors</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 14:00:21 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Lucas Kwan Peterson</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2020-05-05/official-ben-jerrys-ice-cream-power-rankings</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2020-05-05/official-ben-jerrys-ice-cream-power-rankings">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e5ffd6c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F31%2F694a80aa43058e285a7a855fe98e%2Fpowerrankingsicecream.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/dc83df8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F31%2F694a80aa43058e285a7a855fe98e%2Fpowerrankingsicecream.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/449a2ee/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F31%2F694a80aa43058e285a7a855fe98e%2Fpowerrankingsicecream.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/eb12e3e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F31%2F694a80aa43058e285a7a855fe98e%2Fpowerrankingsicecream.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/bfcaf28/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F31%2F694a80aa43058e285a7a855fe98e%2Fpowerrankingsicecream.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Ben &amp; Jerry&#x27;s ice cream, ranked."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c44e083/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F31%2F694a80aa43058e285a7a855fe98e%2Fpowerrankingsicecream.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/af54bb3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F31%2F694a80aa43058e285a7a855fe98e%2Fpowerrankingsicecream.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3cd5c3b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F31%2F694a80aa43058e285a7a855fe98e%2Fpowerrankingsicecream.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7da1eea/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F31%2F694a80aa43058e285a7a855fe98e%2Fpowerrankingsicecream.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1f184c8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F31%2F694a80aa43058e285a7a855fe98e%2Fpowerrankingsicecream.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1f184c8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F31%2F694a80aa43058e285a7a855fe98e%2Fpowerrankingsicecream.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">Ben &amp; Jerrys ice cream, ranked.<br></div><div class="figure-credit">(Martina Ibez-Baldor and Jade Cuevas / Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>The official Ben &amp; Jerry&#x27;s ice cream power rankings</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/lucas-kwan-peterson">        Lucas Kwan Peterson    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="May 5, 2020">May 5, 2020</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Hows everyones first year of quarantine going? Ive firmly moved into the </p>B<p>bargaining zone of the Kbler-Ross five stages of grief: </p><p> How many times will I eat pizza this week, three or four? Are showers on the table? Maybe. Would I pay someone $20 for a hug right now? Likely more. As you can see, in quarantine, absolutely anything is negotiable.</p><p>It is in that spirit that I bring you the infallible, completely factual and 100% correct <b>Ben &amp; Jerrys Ice Cream Power Rankings</b>. Yes, even our nations most adored 420-loving capitalists must eventually fall under the tires of the Power Rankings cement truck. Were dealing with ice cream only </p>during<p> for the purposes of these rankings, folks</p>,<p>  nothing lite, no fro-yo, and none of your fancy nut milks. You kids stay off my lawn!</p><p>Ive ranked these by taste, of course, as well </p> as<p> a metric that honors the various states of incapacitation when we devour an entire pint at 2 a.m.: </p><p> If this ice cream were a person, how stoned would it be? One more thing: Unlike most Power Rankings, where there are items that clearly fall into Good and Bad categories, nearly all of these ice creams were good. But they must, alas, be ranked  in that, there shall be no bargaining.</p>1) Peanut Butter Half Baked<p>Im not much of a cookie dough guy, but I cant deny the greatness of this ice cream. Chocolate and peanut butter ice creams converge in a maelstrom of calor-rific glory and are peppered with brownie and peanut butter cookie dough chunks. Of course chocolate and peanut butter go together like Cheech and Chong; I found that the stickiness of the brownie bits offsets the graininess of the cookie dough.</p><p>To make a 1998 Bulls analogy  Jordan and Pippen are like the two </p>different<p> ice creams. They hold it all together and do most of the work. Kukoc and Rodman are like the brownie and cookie dough chunks. Luc Longley is the  spoon? The United Center is the freezer. Phil Jackson is your conscience, telling you not to eat too much. Defensive specialist Randy Brown is the part of your brain thats honestly just happy to be along for the ride and wants you to keep going even when Phil says to take a break.</p><p>Look, I didnt say the analogy was perfect.</p>2) New York Super Fudge Chunk<p>If theres one thing we loved about Ben </p>and &amp;<p> Jerrys when we </p>first<p> discovered it as kids, and what we still love about it</p> now<p>, its all the </p>stuff<p>. Every pint of Ben </p>and &amp;<p> Jerrys is just loaded with chunks of </p>stuff<p>.</p><p>New York Super Fudge Chunk is that ideal, perfected: Every cubic inch is so full of something that is not ice cream  pecans, walnuts, almonds, fudge chunks  its frankly a wonder they dont market this as frozen trail mix. But this is why we love Ben </p>and &amp;<p> Jerrys: We want to chew our ice cream, not merely lick it.</p>3) Phish food<p>This entry goes out to L.A. Times Food editor Peter Meehan, who was and maybe still is, the biggest Phish fan I know. You see, its Meehans fault that I purchased the Phish album </p> "<p>Junta</p> "<p> in high school, in an effort to be cooler than I was</p>,<p> and sat for hours at home trying to make sense of lyrics like,</p>I look into the finance boxJust to check my statusI look into the microscopeSee Golgi Aapparatus<p>While Phish never really clicked with me, this ice cream certainly does. Chocolate ice cream with marshmallow, caramel and fudge fish leave this just a few nuts away from perfection  but then itd just be Rocky Road, wouldnt it? Instead of what it is: an exceptional-tasting ice cream with smooth, creamy textures that let you linger and get lost inside, like a Trey Anastasio guitar solo. By far the most stoner-y of the line-up.</p>4) Americone Dream<p>The waffle cone bits make this. The smell of sweet dough appeals to anyone whos been to a state fair or inside a Blue Bottle, and this flavor, modeled on the persona of </p> "<p>Report</p> "<p>-era Stephen Colbert, manages to capture some of that magic. The light, crunchy sweetness of the fudge-covered bits are as wistful and nostalgic as the times we thought it was funny to watch a pretend right-wing blowhard spew hatred and misinformation. Remember those days?</p>5) Cherry Garcia<p>One of the OG flavors, Cherry Garcia is still one of the best. Fun story: The flavor originated when a woman named Jane Williamson </p><a href="https://www.benjerry.com/whats-new/2015/cherry-garcia-story">sent a postcard</a><p> to the Burlington office in 1986 suggesting the flavor. It debuted the following year</p>,<p> and became one of the companys most popular flavors. The woman got a years supply of ice cream in thanks.</p><p>While she should have gotten a fat check, frankly, at least the ice cream is still good. Ben &amp; Jerrys doesnt do much in the fruit arena, and its nice to see this flavor endure. Cherry ice cream with fat cherry chunks and flecks of chocolate? Put American Beauty on repeat and hook me up.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dd/8d/fa5d68a24e9aa926bb2966f61f6f/powerrankingsicecreamq1.jpg"></figure>6) Mint Chocolate Cookie<p>Any kind of mint/chocolate combo is going to be a winner, so Ill use this space to pose the question: Whats better, cookies or chips? Im actually a chip person, because of the texture, but I see the position of those on team cookie. Unearthing a cookie is more enjoyable and exciting than the pervasiveness of chips, and again plays into Ben &amp; Jerrys M.O. of packing their pints full of huge chunks.</p><p>A classic, irrefutable flavor combination, if not the most innovative.</p>7) Chip Happens<p>Marketed as, A cold mess of chocolate ice cream with fudge chips and crunchy potato chip swirls, the guys took a slight gamble on this flavor that largely pays off. They didnt put entire potato chips into the pints but instead mashed the chips and spread them throughout the mixture.</p><p>The chips stay pretty remarkably crunchy and retain most of their salty, potatoey flavor. If youve ever enjoyed dipping hot fries into a Wendys Frosty, take this for a spin.</p>8) Chocolate Therapy<p>Remember Cathy? No, not from when you had co-workers and regular human contact, the one from the comic strip whos always saying, Ack! I feel like this is an ice cream Cathy might enjoy, as would the inner Cathy in each and every one of us. It says, We heard you liked chocolate, so we put chocolate in your chocolate.</p><p>Chocolate ice cream is swirled with chocolate pudding ice cream  an important distinction  that is dotted with chocolate cookies. The creaminess of the regular ice cream contrasts subtly with the more viscous pudding cream. The difference is small but essential</p>,<p> and will make you want to slide right into your favorite pair of sweatpants.</p>9) Peanut Butter Cup<p>Can you possibly go wrong with peanut butter ice cream and huge peanut butter cups? Nope. The massive cups are a chunky reminder of why this brand became popular in the first place. I like to imagine, back in 1978 when Ben &amp; Jerrys was founded, two guys in a Burlington basement ripping a </p>four<p>4-foot bong and cramming whatever food they could find into their gullets. After stuffing themselves with peanut butter and chocolate and washing it down with some local full-fat milk, the idea struck them for this particular flavor of shame salve. Wouldnt want it to go down any other way.</p>10) Vanilla<p>A surprise flavor rounding out the top ten: Good old, plain-ass vanilla. Ben &amp; Jerrys is actually one of the best out there. It even has the tiny bean flecks that give the ice cream a distinct psychological edge. Wow, real flecks of vanilla bean? you ask yourself. Theyre not messing around! Ideal in a root beer or Coke float.</p><p>This falls extremely low on the stoner scale  right now I find a sobering pint of pure vanilla is needed to confront every fresh new workday.</p>11) The Tonight Dough<p>Love or hate Jimmy Fallon, he seems like a man who tries extremely hard at everything he does. His namesake ice cream, while good, does the same: Its trying to be too much to too many people. Caramel ice cream </p>and<p> chocolate ice cream </p>and<p> chocolate cookies </p>and<p> chocolate chip cookie dough </p>and<p> peanut butter cookie dough? Just... </p><p> tone it down a little, dude. Youve made it. You can relax.</p>12) Chocolate Fudge Brownie<p>A flavor that is, unlike some presidents, unimpeachable. Sticky chocolate brownies in chocolate ice cream  theres nothing I would change.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/6a/70/87067b7249cf869a4774eca18548/powerrankingsicecreamq2.jpg"></figure>13) Cannoli<p>Who knew? Cannoli: Good for ice cream, good for </p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yHzh0PvMWTI">running errands</a><p> with Clemenza and Rocco. This mixture uses mascarpone instead of the usual ricotta</p>,<p> and comes through with a rich, custard-like flavor. The chocolate-covered pastry shell bits could be a little crisper, but they manage to capture the spirit of the Sicilian confection.</p>14) Oat of this Swirled<p>This ended up being a winner for the most part, but not for the reasons advertised  this wasnt particularly oaty. This is ultimately a cinnamon ice cream, with tasty, satisfyingly spicy cookie swirls. The choice of laying the toppings down in a field of brown sugar ice cream was an inspired one; </p><p> it gives the pint a lovely, slightly caramelized quality.</p>15) Everything But The <p>I wish theyd just finish the sentence. Kitchen sink? Trash can lid? Refrigerator door? Ellipses dont belong in the names of food. Regardless, this ice cream is a good mess, but its still a mess. Cramming peanut butter cups, toffee chunks, white chocolate pieces and fudge-covered almonds all together means no one element gets the chance to shine. Given the MedMen-icated state youre likely in when you crack this pint open, it probably doesnt matter.</p>16) Chocolate Chip Cookie Dough<p>Not my fave, but a classic nonetheless. Something about the gritty, sandy texture of cookie dough has always rubbed me the wrong way. </p><p> Id far rather somebody else did the work, baked the cookies</p>,<p> and put </p>those<p> in my ice cream. Nevertheless, I understand the appeal, and that as a snacky shortcut, it makes sense. Ben &amp; Jerrys makes as good </p>as<p> a version as you can hope to find.</p>17) Chunky Monkey<p>Honestly, I was prepared to put this flavor at </p>number one No. 1<p>  or at least in the top five. But after trying a few bites, I just couldnt do it: The banana flavor is off. It lacks the dense, almost booze-y sweetness of a real overripe banana, veering instead into Laffy Taffy/Runts territory. Its about as close to a banana as grape soda is to a grape. While the chocolate chunks and walnuts are ultimately satisfying, the very raison detre of the pint, the titular monkeys aspect, is a somewhat disappointing mirage.</p>18) Half Baked<p>Whats not to like? Cookie dough and brownie chunks make for a winning combination, and the ice cream proves better than the </p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XLScUvabSr4">Dave Chappelle comedy</a><p> of the same name. It ranks highly in the stoned category, naturally, though I dont know it gives the unmedicated a strong reason to reach across the freezer aisle.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/9d/11/29bd530a4366a87ee51417b0e0a5/powerrankingsicecreamq3.jpg"></figure>19) Gimme SMore<p>Ah, wilderness! Who among us doesnt remember getting picked on by older kids in Scouts and then promptly drowning our sorrows in a delicious smore seasoned with wet, salty tears? In my case, I could never quite perfect the marshmallow. Id soon lose my patience while trying to slowly roast it and then hold the thing directly on the fire, resulting in a charred outside and nearly raw center.</p><p>Still, the flavor of graham crackers, chocolate and marshmallow takes me back. It doesnt quite capture the trauma of growing up, but at least its delicious.</p>20) Salted Caramel Core<p>This is the best of the core ice creams, which is a Ben &amp; Jerrys variation Ive never quite jibed with. Why place all of the good stuff in one centralized, predictable area? Half the fun of ice cream is the randomized chaos of not knowing exactly what youre going to get in a given bite.</p><p>The core ice creams ruin that fun, like a deconstructed Caesar salad: Heres a romaine leaf, theres a wedge of cheese, a piece of toasted bread there and an egg over there. Its too clever for its own good.</p><p>Then again, maybe you just want to eat the entire core? In that case, I can see a point to the approach. The salted caramel could be a little more salty, but it goes nicely with the sweet cream ice cream and chewy blondie bits.</p>21) Pistachio Pistachio<p>There are better pistachio ice creams out there. This one has nice plump nuts scattered throughout, but the flavor of the ice cream proper is off. </p><p> It tastes a little like almond extract. Nevertheless, the dads out there will love it, leading to its low score on the stoner scale.</p>22) Vanilla Caramel Fudge<p>This one is smooth baby, smooth, and should probably be ranked higher than it is  I just have an affinity for </p>stuff<p> and this doesnt have any </p>stuff<p> in it. What it lacks in the chunk department</p>thicc-ness<p>, though, it makes up for </p> in<p> slick, sticky sweetness. The caramel and fudge meld </p>together<p> in a dreamy, seamless way to produce an entirely new ice cream topping, fudgamel, where you're not quite sure where one stops and the other takes over. If you give yourself over to this ice cream, you may never come back from the edge.</p>23) Milk &amp; Cookies<p>Inoffensive and, in theory, a totally fun and charming ice cream flavor. Who doesnt love milk and cookies? What this flavor doesnt really take into account, though, is that the pleasure of milk and cookies derives primarily from 1) the contrast of a hot cookie with cold milk and/or 2) the soaking of a cookie in the milk, leading to a pleasantly sodden cookie.</p><p>Here, neither of those sensations come</p> s<p> through. The cookies are crisp, and somewhat grainy, and do little to evoke any Santa-esque memories.</p>24) Brownie batter core<p>Does too much of a good thing exist? The answer is obviously no, but if it did, this would be it. The brownie core here is so slick and sweet, so intense, that it simply overwhelms. Its very fudgy and extremely rich, but after a spoonful or two, it has me missing the chewiness of the regular Ben &amp; Jerrys brownies.</p>25) Justice ReMixd<p>With just the slightest bit of pep in the brownies and a cinnamon-loaded bun dough, youre on the express train to Spice City, next stop, Seasoning Station! This flavor, which was created to benefit </p><a href="https://www.benjerry.com/flavors/justice-remixd-ice-cream/">criminal justice reform</a><p>, doesnt quite capture the magic of a fresh cinnamon bun or a spicy cup of hot chocolate, but its more than adequate.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/7d/94/4626d4024333b629e22eca16b06b/powerrankingsicecreamq4.jpg"></figure>26) Caramel Chocolate Cheesecake<p>This is the best of Ben &amp; Jerrys cheesecake offerings I tried, and it quite nearly works. But the cheesecake needs to be much more tangy and assertive; Right now it sort of limps along like an injured animal. Caramel and chocolate will make anything taste good, but the cheesecake, the ostensible star of the show, needs to step more into the spotlight.</p>27) Chocolate Chip Cookie Dough Core<p>Again with the cores. Would you order a bag of Cheetos that was separated into two compartments: Plain, unflavored corn puffs and pure, cheese powder? I mean, maybe you would. Maybe I would</p>,<p> too.</p>Okay OK<p>, I definitely would. But thats not the point: </p>l<p>Like Beatles albums, ice cream is meant to be consumed as a whole, not cherry-picked for your favorite bits. Otherwise you could just buy a tube of cookie dough, right?</p>28) Coffee Toffee Bar Crunch<p>I feel like once they had to take Heath bar out of the name, this flavor really tanked. The toffee chunks just arent buttery enough; </p><p> they taste mostly of sugar. The coffee ice cream lacks the deep, rich earthiness youll find in some of the bolder and better coffee ice creams on the market.</p><p>Think of it in terms of an improv 101 class. Make bold choices! Fully commit! Many times, that in and of itself can make the difference between hackneyed character and something truly worthy of a self-taped audition. This ice cream needs to give itself a pep talk in the hallway and give it another shot.</p>29) Netflix &amp; Chillld<p>With its ready-for-Tinder name, this had the potential to be the sexiest of the entries. Peanut butter ice cream with pretzels and fudge brownies should be knock-it-out-of-the-park good! But the pretzels are chalky and dry and the brownies are tacky, not chewy, landing this somewhere near the Gatorade cooler in the dugout. Just goes to show that money can buy you more content than youll be able to watch in 100 lifetimes, but it cant get you a great ice cream flavor.</p>30) Strawberry Cheesecake<p>Cheesecake needs to be tangy; Fruity ice cream needs to be fruity. This wasnt particularly </p>...<p>either</p>?<p>.</p><p>What are you up to, strawberry cheesecake ice cream? Did you come to play? Or did you come to </p>half-assedly<p> half-heartedly jog up and down the court and knock down a couple of early shots but, when push comes to shove, give up, fake an injury and go home? I suspect the latter, and Im a little disappointed in you.</p>31) Caramel Chocolate Cheesecake Truffles<p>I cant tell the</p>e<p> difference between this and the regular Caramel Chocolate Cheesecake, but this has graham cracker-coated cheesecake truffles instead of regular cheesecake chunks. Why they made an entirely separate flavor with such a minute distinction is lost on me, but it wasnt a good idea. This is the inferior product. The cheesecake has very little tang, and the graham cracker makes the bits taste slightly dusty. Pass.</p>32) Wake &amp; No Bake Cookie Dough Core<p>The only flavor that I actively didnt enjoy. The no-bake cookie dough in this wink-wink-nudge-nudge cleverly-named creation is sickly sweet with a terrible rabbit-food texture. Its sandy and pasty like a Clif </p>b<p>Bar, with the density and distressing flavor to match.</p><p>But to Ben Cohen and Jerry Greenfield, I say: Youre allowed a couple of misses </p>here  now<p> and again, guys. Cheers to keeping a largely very good track record of delicious, chunktastic stable of flavors over the course of </p>the last<p> four decades.</p> Ben &amp; Jerry's Power Rankings                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The official Trader Joe's frozen food power rankings</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2020-03-17/official-trader-joes-frozen-food-power-rankings</link>
      <description>One man's opinion on the best (and worst) Trader Joe's frozen food on the market.</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Mar 2020 12:00:37 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Lucas Kwan Peterson</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2020-03-17/official-trader-joes-frozen-food-power-rankings</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2020-03-17/official-trader-joes-frozen-food-power-rankings">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d3be2fa/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1500x1000+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F95%2F07e6cf3343a28b733036b88e1fe5%2Ftraderjoespower.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7721c0c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1500x1000+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F95%2F07e6cf3343a28b733036b88e1fe5%2Ftraderjoespower.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/16e314f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1500x1000+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F95%2F07e6cf3343a28b733036b88e1fe5%2Ftraderjoespower.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8ff9ce3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1500x1000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F95%2F07e6cf3343a28b733036b88e1fe5%2Ftraderjoespower.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9284125/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1500x1000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F95%2F07e6cf3343a28b733036b88e1fe5%2Ftraderjoespower.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Trader Joe&#x27;s frozen food, ranked."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/be32473/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1500x1000+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F95%2F07e6cf3343a28b733036b88e1fe5%2Ftraderjoespower.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/32a2190/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1500x1000+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F95%2F07e6cf3343a28b733036b88e1fe5%2Ftraderjoespower.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4c23be2/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1500x1000+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F95%2F07e6cf3343a28b733036b88e1fe5%2Ftraderjoespower.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/cb5cd26/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1500x1000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F95%2F07e6cf3343a28b733036b88e1fe5%2Ftraderjoespower.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/60e21e8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1500x1000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F95%2F07e6cf3343a28b733036b88e1fe5%2Ftraderjoespower.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/60e21e8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1500x1000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F95%2F07e6cf3343a28b733036b88e1fe5%2Ftraderjoespower.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Trader Joes frozen food, ranked.</div><div class="figure-credit">(Martina Ibez-Baldor &amp; Lucas Kwan Peterson)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>The official Trader Joe&#x27;s frozen food power rankings</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/lucas-kwan-peterson">        Lucas Kwan Peterson    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="March 17, 2020">March 17, 2020</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>2020, if you haven't noticed, isn't going particularly well. Social distancing and self-quarantining are two gerunds we've all become very familiar with over the last weeks, and as far as food goes, it means one thing: You're eating at home more. Whether you're <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2020-03-13/coronavirus-los-angeles-restaurants-closures">getting takeout from your favorite restaurants</a> or scouring the CVS shelves for beans and hand sanitizer, </p> we're all eating more meals on the couch.you're more likely to be plopping onto the couch to enjoy your next meal.<p>Which brings us to Trader Joes</p>. T, <p>, the place for </p> m<p>illennials who dont like to cook</p>,<p> but do like to drink. <a href="https://www.latimes.com/obituaries/story/2020-02-29/la-me-joe-coulombe-trade-joes-dead" target="_blank">Joe Coulombe</a>, who died last month at 89, ingeniously created a chain where each branch </p> somehowsomeone how <p>seems as friendly as a small-town grocery store. Hand-written signs, the signature Aloha-shirt uniform, the fact that employees are actually, you know, reasonably helpful and friendly. Their little </p><a href="https://miro.medium.com/max/6528/1*3VC8Ah3bB9TkVP7ZzzZBCg.jpeg">Fearless Flyer</a><p> newsletter, looking cribbed straight from the Farmers Almanac, as old-timey as a shop that spells the word shoppe, might distract you from the fact that the chain was sold in 1979 to the Albrecht family, founders of the multi</p>-<p>billion-dollar German behemoth </p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aldi">Aldi.</a><p>I have a Martin Luther-esque list of grievances about the store</p> :(<p>Why is it Trader Joe's-branded everything? Do you expect me to believe that yogurt </p>and<p> those peanut butter pretzels </p>and<p> that fried rice all came out of </p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Tsdmqhn50uM">one magical factory</a><p> in Monrovia? Why can't you buy, like, </p> normal grocery<p> store things </p>?  l<p>ike aluminum foil?</p>), B<p>ut those are for another time. People are stressed out, and people gotta eat.</p><p>Here are the scientifically proven and totally correct <b>Trader Joes Frozen Food Power Rankings</b>, freshly wiped down this morning with the last can of Clorox wipes on earth. I have tried no fewer than 37 different Trader Joes frozen food products (Did I omit your favorite? Im sure I did!), which I have ranked based on two metrics: 1) Taste and 2) Laziness Factor  how easy was the prep and clean</p>-<p>up? (Factors in oven time if thats recommended. A higher ranking means its easier.) As Trader Ming would say, <a href="https://chinese.yabla.com/chinese-english-pinyin-dictionary.php?define=%E6%85%A2%E6%85%A2%E5%90%83" target="_blank"></a>!</p>1) Matre Pierre Tarte dAlsace<p>This very good take on an Alsatian tarte flambe or a </p> f<p>lammkuchen will make you feel like youre a kid in eastern France, getting annexed all over again. Its a crispy, buttery dough base layer smeared with crme frache and sprinkled with Gruyere cheese and little batons of ham.</p><p>This has been a staple of the T.J. frozen food pantheon for as long as I can remember, and for good reason: The flaky crust combines impeccably with the delicate onions, nutty cheese and sweet-smoky ham. Also: Matre Pierre? Wheres Trader Jacques?</p>2) Korma fish curry<p>Hey. This is a winner. Are those mustard seeds in that rice? Is the fish  a swai (a freshwater shark catfish) fillet  flaky and tender? Is that just the right balance of heat in the creamy, coconut-ty, tamarind-tinged sauce? The answer to all of these is a resounding yes, as is my response to the question, should I buy this?</p>3) Korean-style beef short ribs<p>These marinated flaps of L.A. galbi (so-named because Koreans who moved to Los Angeles had to adjust to how meat was butchered in the U.S.</p>,<p> and brought that flanken-style across-the-bone cut back to Korea) compellingly balance sweet and savory. The brown sugar in the marinade helps with the caramelization to the meat, offsetting the funky rice wine and garlicky thrust, but without getting into sticky teriyaki territory. The prep and clean</p>-<p>up is a little tough, but its worth it to feel like youve landed a seat at a totally decent Hawaiian lunch counter somewhere.</p>4) Cauliflower gnocchi<p>Slow clap. Count me as a member of the </p><a href="https://vimeo.com/182093290">Sarcastic Clapping Family of Southampton</a><p>, because Im duly impressed. I had my doubts about this product because of its popularity</p>,<p> (one of the best</p>-<p>selling items, according to the Trader Joes crew leader I spoke to at my local store</p>,<p>), but I was surprised how good these are.</p><p>Unlike the prep of other frozen T.J. gnocchi, wherein you just toss the little suckers into a hot pan, these cauliflower gnocchi are steamed back to life first before they get crisped up in the pan. The extra step results in a mouthfeel that could </p>nearly<p> convince you that they werent from the freezer.</p><p>If youre generally a fan of </p> the<p> bitter pepperiness of </p>Brassica oleracea<p>, which includes cabbage and Brussels sprouts, youre going to like these. Served with cheese sprinkled on top, they conjure broccoli, but youll probably be happier dousing them in sauce  TJs jarred arrabiata or its frozen turkey bolognese arent bad choices.</p>5) Butter chicken with basmati rice<p>Butter chicken isnt as complex or interesting as some (many?) other Indian dishes, but it, like kung pao chicken, has broad appeal. And this is an earthy, satisfying, faithful representation of the dish.</p><p>Butter chicken was supposedly created in </p><a href="https://www.hindustantimes.com/delhi-news/vadiya-khao-refugees-taught-delhi-how-to-eat-out-in-style/story-Y5sG96AYWu7gQ9e5V6TXxN.html">the kitchen of Moti Mahal</a><p>, a Delhi restaurant that opened in 1947. The sauce in this rendition has a tomato-inflected creaminess and some slight smokiness to give it depth. Would I like it if the sauce werent quite so thin? I would, but I cant carp about the flavor. The rice holds up well, even after half an hour in the oven.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/d0/b8/aec4aa6a402992d1620b683085bb/traderjoespower1.jpg"></figure>6) Chicken &amp; mushroom pelmeni<p>I enjoyed these  but I am a fan of pelmeni. These cute, aural Russian dumplings  pelmeni comes from a word that translates to ear bread  are stuffed with a bouncy-textured filling that almost crosses the line into rubbery but manages not to go too far. Theres a nice dill flavor to the dish, which cuts the salt and umami of the chicken and mushroom filling.  !</p>7) Fiery chicken curry<p>Described as a <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/dailydish/la-dd-goan-food-20151214-story.html" target="_blank">Goan</a>-inspired recipe with turmeric rice the fiery chicken mostly delivers. The sweet and sour tomato-based sauce, flavored with tamarind, lulls you into satiation before a sneaky heat comes over and backhands you. Its slightly more herbal and bitter than some of the other T.J. curries and good if you want a little extra kick.</p>8) Chicken cilantro mini wontons<p>Cute is </p> an<p> operable descriptor for these tiny, adorable little meat pockets. Theyre not that different than most of the other T.J. dumpling offerings, but theres an added herbal tanginess to the filling imparted by the cilantro. You do, of course, have to not be one of those people who thinks cilantro tastes like soap.</p>9) Palak paneer<p>Whats with the Indian food at Trader Joes? Its better than any other category of frozen food in the store by, like, a metric ton. This palak paneer, spiced with fenugreek and turmeric, has the right amount of heat in the creamy, slightly grassy spinach. Cheese cubes, swimming in the sea of green, add a pleasing squeak.</p>10) Burrata, prosciutto &amp; arugula flatbread<p>In an interesting prep experience, you completely remove the prosciutto package before backing the flatbread, then add the somewhat skimpy meat portion to the completed product. The cheese mixture is sharp and tangy, but the arugula, after sitting in a hot oven, essentially has all the oomph of spinach, totally lacking any peppery sharpness. The ham imparts needed salt and the overall flavor is good, with an above-average crust, but Tombstone isnt quaking in their boots over it.</p>11) Spanikopita<p>In the hard to mess up category, its still important to acknowledge when something is done right. Frozen phyllo dough crisps up awesomely in the oven, and the slick, cheesy spinach filling is no better or worse than we need it to be. Serve these up at a little dinner party for your friends and make them think youre fancier and more skilled in the kitchen than you are. (Actually, they wont be fooled and will 100% know you got these from Trader Joes but hey, its not like they invited </p>you<p> over!)</p>12) Joes Diner Mac N Cheese<p>This doesnt look like much going into the oven, and it doesnt look like much coming out, either: a tray of lumpy, alabaster slop. But it has </p> the<p> pleasing graininess that only thiamin</p> e<p> mononitrate has, as well as satisfying gooey stretchiness. Its souped-up cafeteria fare, better than Kraft or Velveeta, but not quite Diner in its quality or evocation of warmth and comfort.</p>13) Trader Giottos gnocchi al gorgonzola<p>To Trader Giotto I ask this: Perch? Perch non dai pi sapore? This gnocchi gets a passing grade, barely, because the combination of cheesy-creamy-salty is rarely a bad one. But it lacks teeth  and the punch and funk  that the word gorgonzola promises.</p><p>Speaking of teeth, the bite on these frozen gnocchi is off. They are bouncy and squeaky, like a dog chew toy or a racquetball. Thankfully the prep on these, like a lot of the pastas, is easy: </p>  D<p>ump the contents of the bag in a pan and stir.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/d6/ef/55e613f5458c8f0e55c9ac0b682d/traderjoespower2.jpg"></figure>14) Channa masala<p>This version of the Indian chickpea dish is heavy-handed with the cumin and a little too sweet, but its filling and robustly spiced. Its one of the weaker entries in the (extremely strong) Indian food lineup at T.J., though the chickpeas dont reconstitute as nicely as they should. Instead of tender, the texture is mealy and grainy, like an old French fry. Opt instead for one of the comparably excellent fish or chicken curries.</p>15) Trader Giottos authentic Italian penne arrabiata<p>If your foodie fantasies tend to be spicy, reads the packaging, Trader Giottos Italian penne arrabiata may just be the pasta of your dreams! May is </p> the<p> operative word here, and its doing an awful lot of lifting in this sentence. Are we so lazy as a society that we cant boil pasta, open a jar of marinara and throw some chile flakes in it? Apparently so. The sauce is bright and a little spicy but Im slightly afraid of the greater societal implications of this frozen dinner.</p>16) Chicken gyoza potstickers<p>The La Brea Tar Pits literally translates to The The Tar Tar Pits. I mention this because gyoza are dumplings and potstickers are dumplings and so the name of this product is, effectively, chicken dumplings dumplings. Why the redundancy? Are they trying to cover their SEO bases by name</p> -<p>checking both Japanese and Chinese foodstuffs?</p><p>Like the Beatles album Yellow Submarine these are not going to be anyones favorite, but theyll do in a pinch when nothing else is around. And they stay together in the pan, which is a win for any bag of frozen dumplings. Fry for best results.</p>17) Yellow jackfruit curry with jasmine rice<p>A reasonable vegan option  coconut-ty, creamy and somewhat spicy  but the eggplant in the mix dominates and it could use a little more of the meaty jackfruit.</p>18) Trader Giottos linguine with pesto &amp; tomatoes<p>Im slightly shocked by the look of most of T.J.s pasta dishes while theyre still in frozen form: The sauce is frozen separately into about a dozen silver-dollar-sized discs and scattered throughout the icy pasta. The effect is that it looks like play food, something that would be scattered around the floor of a childs toy kitchen.</p><p>The pesto</p> is<p> has an aggressive basil flavor and a slight grassiness. It needs more of another ingredient to balance that out  more cheese? Butter? Pine nuts? Giotto could have done better with this one, but itll do in a pinch.</p>19) Tempura shrimp with soy dipping sauce<p>Ten little shrimp soldiers come lined up side-by-side in </p>styrofoam plastic foam<p> packs. Heated, they lack the delicate, intricate structure and lightness of better-battered tempura. The sauce is overly gloppy and sweet.</p><p>Is it unrealistic to expect more from Trader Joes freezer case? Probably, but if we cant put high standards on our multi</p>-<p>billion</p> -dollar<p> conglomerates, where can we?</p>20) Trader Giottos linguine with clam sauce<p>While not sharp or garlicky enough, it doesnt overtly offend. Like many of the T.J. pastas,</p>  they<p> come in frozen pasta nests that are cooked and slowly unravel in the pan. There are a few springy clams in there, but this pasta alle vongole misses any of the rich brininess you want from the dish. When the linguini hits your plate</p>,<p> and it dont taste too great, thats a-disappointment!</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/28/31/4f9683f94db9bdb1390be322f6c7/traderjoespower3.jpg"></figure>21) Scallion pancakes (pa jeon)<p>Theres a lot thats wrong here, the main thing being that these conflate the Chinese <a href="https://www.latimes.com/food/dailydish/la-dd-scallion-pancake-20160430-story.html">cong you bing</a>, scallion pancake, with the Korean pajeon. Pajeon are made with a batter, not dough, so theyre a lot different than most Westerners ideas of what scallion pancakes are and will probably lead to a lot of confused shoppers.</p><p>This doesnt taste terrible, but it suffers the problem most undistinguished pajeons suffer: </p> <p>too bready</p>,<p> and not enough green onion. The batter should serve the veggies</p>,<p> and not the other way around</p> ; <p> give me a pancake thats completely green and lousy with scallions, and Ill show you a happy man.</p>22) Peruvian style chimichurri rice<p>Im not sure why chimichurri, a condiment most typically seen alongside </p> ArgentineArgentinian<p> food, is attributed to Peru in this frozen offering. Then again, Im not sure why they use the wrong accents on crme frache on the packaging</p>,<p> either. (Crme fraiche, or CRAY-m fresh, is how Trader Joes spells it).</p><p>Is that overly pedantic? Sure, but I am a man who just ate 37 frozen dinners. The chimichurri in question isnt particularly chimichurri-like, totally lacking in any allium wallop. Instead, it leans mild, peppery and cilantro-y  more of a mild, creamy aji sauce. The prep is easy</p>,<p> and the overall tomato flavor doesnt offend, but it tastes like someone dumped too much citric acid into this, giving the dish a punchy but unconvincing feel.</p>23) Cuisine Adventures French onion soup<p>I was psyched to see that this was even an option  frozen French onion soup? The greatest of all soups with none of the work? My next reaction was to wonder exactly how this was going to work. It turns out you get a frozen cylinder of soup, vacuum</p> -<p>packed in plastic. You unwrap the soup lump and place it directly into a cup or bowl, and then bake.</p><p>In theory, this is ingenious. In practice, it falls short. The cheese is rubbery, the broth is so-so, and the croutons are practically nonexistent, having almost completely disintegrated in the soup after 40 minutes in the oven. Is disappointing French onion soup better than none at all?</p>24) Trader Joes potato pancakes<p>I love a good latke, but I want to actively feel the shreds of potato breaking between my teeth  not the mushiness of bready batter. They crisp up promisingly in the pan, but the mealiness inside is real.</p>25) Trader Mings Mandarin Orange Chicken<p>One of the crew members at my local store asserted that this is the most popular item it sells. But why? Its not awful, but it lacks the appeal and craveability of its cooler cousin at Panda Express, to which comparisons will inevitably be drawn. The sauce on this dark meat chicken is a little too tangy, a little too sharp  It almost crosses the line into stomach acid territory. The breading on the meat is, thankfully, not overly thick, but thats not enough to get this into my reusable bag.</p><p>Oh, and one more thing: The name of this product can go straight to hell. </p>Trader Mings?<p> The racism is less offensive than the inaccuracy. Anyone with a modicum of knowledge of Chinese knows that the name clearly should be, if anything, Trader Zhous.</p>26) Chicken chilaquiles rojo<p>The sauce is average, the chicken in these has a forcemeat quality, but the real issue is with the chips that are crumbled to bits right out of the package and dissolve to practically nothing in the cooking process. I also enjoy how the cooking instructions tell you to cook this until an internal temperature of 165 F has been reached, which is a sneaky bit of legalese. If youre eating frozen chilaquiles, what are the chances youre using a reliable instant-read thermometer?</p>27) Stacked eggplant Parmesan TheThis<p> box on this stacked eggplant parm makes a lot of promises and doesnt deliver on any of them. The eggplant is cut far too thick  I dont need to feel like Im eating a steak. The eggplant should be thin enough to nicely caramelize and almost (but not quite) fall apart. Instead, this eggplant is stacked like a Big Mac in a soup of tomato-bread mush. Theres not nearly enough cheese and a sharp, reedy basil flavor overpowers everything.</p>28) Chicken Chile Verde Burritos<p>I usually use the oven over a microwave but I went the radioactive route on this dish because, </p>thirty 30<p> minutes to heat up a burrito? Do I look like Methuselah?</p><p>But I fear no appliance would have helped these burritos, which are filled with a slurry that has the taste and consistency of turkey jook. Thats not a problem per se, but it isnt what I signed up for. I dont get much chili flavor, and the gummy tortilla is far too thick and dominates the proceedings.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/76/cc/65d809fa4a819bf1a00120e9685b/traderjoespower4.jpg"></figure>29) Mini vegetable samosas<p>Cumin mush are the two operative words in this, the sole disappointing T.J. Indian food I tried during this tasting. They crisp up somewhat decently in the oven, but are filled with an over-cuminated pulp thats hard to get excited about.</p>30) Beef shepherds pie<p>The shepherd has sheep, which is why their pies are usually filled with lamb. I imagine the people from TJs corporate probably felt a gamier meat like lamb would be a hard sell, so they went with beef instead. Does it help? Not really. Theres a</p> n<p> Armed Forces-like chipped beef quality to meat, the veggies arent substantial enough to get anyones attention and the mashed potato covering the top has a funny, grainy texture. You hate to see it.</p>31) Chipotle vegetable quesadillas<p>While not overtly offensive, the casing of these quesadillas is about five times thicker than it needs to be, more pita than tortilla. The insides are an uninspiring glop of queso mixed with vegetables, and the chipotle is AWOL.</p>32) Mushroom &amp; black truffle flatbread<p>Truffles AND mushrooms? Why? The truffle taste is ... so powerful. I was curious as to how anything containing more than a modicum of truffle could cost just $4.49, so I checked the ingredient list. They sneakily list Latin fungus names on the back without explaining what all of them are  Tuber aestivum (summer truffle), but also Agaricus </p> bisporusbisporous<p> (portobellos) and Pleurotus ostreatus (oyster mushrooms).</p><p>Theres none of the sweet nutty aroma you want from a truffle, and the overall flavor is one of old porcinis. Get a rich aunt to take you out to a fancy restaurant where they have the real deal.</p>33) Trader Giottos pizza margherita<p>This screams bad buffet or subpar 7-Eleven. While theres only a seven-minute bake time, you end up with a stiff crust covered in a pasty sauce and plasticky discs of cheese that dont melt properly. Pass.</p>34) Creamy spinach &amp; artichoke dip<p>The dip comes in a cylinder, much like the French onion soup, and, much like the French onion soup, it misses the </p>the <p>mark. Its far too thin and runny, and tastes like a weak cream of spinach soup from Corner Bakery. Wheres the cheese? Wheres </p> the<p> heft? This subpar offering limps along and coasts on name alone, a little like the Biden campaign thus far.</p>35) BBQ chicken pizza<p>An institutional foam cracker covered in sad ketchup and some stray chicken. Theres absolutely none of the zing or brightness you need in a good BBQ chicken pizza. Next!</p>36) Honey walnut shrimp<p>Oh, these are bad. These are real bad. Think pineapple, sour milk</p>,<p> and shellfish. Imagine a big bowl of church-basement ambrosia. Now imagine someone spiked that with a bunch of warm shrimp. HARD PASS.</p>37) Philly cheesesteak bao buns<p>Marry an ancient bao bun recipe with one of Americas favorite foods, it says on the package. The fluffy bao bun is the perfect vehicle for every beefy, cheesy bite, it says on the package. ALL LIES. The bao is as stiff and humorless as Mitch McConnell, and the insides filled with a slick, vile concoction that looks like the inside of a newborns diaper and only passingly resembles food.</p><p>Any resemblance to a cheesesteak is purely coincidental. Let this be a lesson to those who like to throw darts at a board, pick two random names, and combine them into some sort of fusion-esque food  sometimes two rights make a wrong!</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The official instant ramen power rankings</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2019-11-05/instant-ramen-power-rankings-lucas-peterson</link>
      <description>One man’s opinion on the best (and worst) instant ramens.</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Nov 2019 15:00:40 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/food/story/2019-11-05/instant-ramen-power-rankings-lucas-peterson</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
