<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Housing &amp; Homelessness</title>
    <link>https://www.latimes.com/homeless-housing</link>
    <description>Housing &amp; Homelessness</description>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 12:00:46 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.latimes.com/homeless-housing.rss" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" />
    <item>
      <title>State reaches settlement over pandemic rent relief: What tenants and landlords need to know</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/homeless-housing/story/2023-06-09/state-reaches-settlement-over-pandemic-rent-relief-what-tenants-and-landords-need-to-know</link>
      <description>A year after tenant advocates sued the state housing department, a settlement requires it to disburse rent debt relief funds to eligible tenants.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 12:00:46 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Charlotte Kramon</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/homeless-housing/story/2023-06-09/state-reaches-settlement-over-pandemic-rent-relief-what-tenants-and-landords-need-to-know</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/homeless-housing/story/2023-06-09/state-reaches-settlement-over-pandemic-rent-relief-what-tenants-and-landords-need-to-know">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9bad2ea/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcf%2F47%2F394ccb854662bd2e6d5799d6e016%2Fla-photos-1staff-535885-me-anti-eviction-protest-03-mjc.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/30994dd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcf%2F47%2F394ccb854662bd2e6d5799d6e016%2Fla-photos-1staff-535885-me-anti-eviction-protest-03-mjc.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/457d8c5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcf%2F47%2F394ccb854662bd2e6d5799d6e016%2Fla-photos-1staff-535885-me-anti-eviction-protest-03-mjc.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/909fbdf/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcf%2F47%2F394ccb854662bd2e6d5799d6e016%2Fla-photos-1staff-535885-me-anti-eviction-protest-03-mjc.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/82e1c1c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcf%2F47%2F394ccb854662bd2e6d5799d6e016%2Fla-photos-1staff-535885-me-anti-eviction-protest-03-mjc.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="LOS ANGELES, CA - MAY 05: A housing rights and anti-eviction protest outside the office of attorney Dennis Block in Valley Village on Tuesday, May 5, 2020, attracted about 35 protesters. Block has evicted more than 200,000 tenants since 1976, according to the AIDS Healthcare Foundation, the parent of nonprofit Housing is a Human Right and Healthy Housing Foundation, the organizers of the protest. (Myung J. Chun / Los Angeles Times)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e23ecc8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcf%2F47%2F394ccb854662bd2e6d5799d6e016%2Fla-photos-1staff-535885-me-anti-eviction-protest-03-mjc.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b9cc7ef/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcf%2F47%2F394ccb854662bd2e6d5799d6e016%2Fla-photos-1staff-535885-me-anti-eviction-protest-03-mjc.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/80bb250/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcf%2F47%2F394ccb854662bd2e6d5799d6e016%2Fla-photos-1staff-535885-me-anti-eviction-protest-03-mjc.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d1e1526/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcf%2F47%2F394ccb854662bd2e6d5799d6e016%2Fla-photos-1staff-535885-me-anti-eviction-protest-03-mjc.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f63ca52/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcf%2F47%2F394ccb854662bd2e6d5799d6e016%2Fla-photos-1staff-535885-me-anti-eviction-protest-03-mjc.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f63ca52/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcf%2F47%2F394ccb854662bd2e6d5799d6e016%2Fla-photos-1staff-535885-me-anti-eviction-protest-03-mjc.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">LOS ANGELES, CA - MAY 05: A housing rights and anti-eviction protest outside the office of attorney Dennis Block in Valley Village on Tuesday, May 5, 2020, attracted about 35 protesters. Block has evicted more than 200,000 tenants since 1976, according to the AIDS Healthcare Foundation, the parent of nonprofit Housing is a Human Right and Healthy Housing Foundation, the organizers of the protest. (Myung J. Chun / Los Angeles Times)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Myung J. Chun/Myung J. Chun/Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>State reaches settlement over pandemic rent relief: What tenants and landlords need to know </h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/charlotte-kramon">        Charlotte Kramon    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Tenant</p><p>s</p> '<p> rights advocates and the California Department of Housing and Community Development reached a <a href="https://publiccounsel.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/CA-Rent-Relief_Housing-is-Key_ERAP_Signed-Settlement.pdf">settlement</a> this week to address processing delays and denials in rent relief applications for eligible tenants, meaning more renters could soon get financial aid. </p><p>During the pandemic, California tasked the department with administering more than <a href="https://www.latimes.com/homeless-housing/story/2021-08-31/new-rent-relief-is-on-the-way-in-la-heres-how-to-apply">$5 billion</a> in state and federal funds to assist vulnerable tenants with rent relief through Californias </p> COVID-19Covid-19<p> Emergency Rental Assistance Program. The agency closed the application portal at the end of March 2022. </p><p>A surge in <a href="https://www.latimes.com/homeless-housing/story/2022-03-17/rental-assistance-in-california-how-to-apply-deadlines">denials beginning after the closure</a> propelled advocates to sue, alleging that eligible renters were rejected and left without financial aid. By July, around <a href="https://nationalequityatlas.org/ca-rental-assistance">30%</a> of applicants had been denied assistance from the program, even though</p> <p><a href="https://nationalequityatlas.org/CARentalAssistance">93%</a> were likely </p> <p>eligible for debt relief, according to </p> the <p>National Equity Atlas, an organization that reports on racial and economic equity.</p><p>The way the program was set up was not responsive to the population it was meant to serve, </p> said <p>Faizah Malik, senior staff attorney at Public Counsel, a nonprofit law firm that helped represent the community advocacy organizations that sued the state.</p><p>Tenant advocates <a href="https://wclp.org/press-release-lawsuit-filed-against-ca-hcd-for-violating-due-process-rights-in-emergency-rental-assistance-program/" target="_blank">sued</a> the housing department </p> in June 2022<p> for distributing funds through an application process they characterized as muddled with barriers for low-income and vulnerable individuals unfamiliar with navigating government bureaucracy. Tenants found long waits, language and technological barriers, and vague explanations if they were denied assistance, according to lawyers involved in the settlement. The settlement requires the department to make several changes to its system for pending relief applications and </p> to <p>provide tenants with the information they need to appeal.</p><p>More than <a href="https://publiccounsel.org/litigation/acce-v-hcd/" target="_blank">100,000</a> households are waiting to hear whether they will receive rent relief, according to a data analysis by Public Counsel.</p><p>"Ultimately, the petitioners and [the Department of Housing and Community Development] chose to settle the litigation to move the program forward with the shared goal of assisting Californians, department officials said in a</p>n emailed<p> statement to </p> T<p>he </p>Los Angeles<p> Times. We are committed to working with our partners to bring resolution and support to those remaining in the application pipeline.</p><p>The settlement comes as </p> the city of <p>Los Angeles' </p>Citys <p><a href="https://housing.lacity.org/highlights/renter-protections" target="_blank">first rent repayment period ends on Aug. 1</a>  the deadline for tenants to pay rental debt accumulated between March 2020 and September 2021.</p><p>According to the complaint, tenants often received rent relief denials that amounted to a few words, such as nonresponsive, inconsistent</p>,<p> or unverifiable information. Without more detailed explanations, tenants werent sure why they were denied or how to appeal successfully, the advocates suing the state said.</p><p>Applicants who did not speak English received little assistance, while others were denied for a single missing document from the long list of papers required for verification, Malik said. Many tenants do not have formal leases, she added, which also caused denials.</p><p>Low-income older adults who are not used to dealing with online technology similarly found the application process insurmountably difficult, said Cynthia Strathmann, executive director of Strategic Actions for a Just Economy, one of the organizations that sued the state. These individuals often didnt have emails or laptops, struggled to remember their passwords and didnt know how to log in to their portals.</p><p>The housing department's call center provided little, if any, help, Malik said: Tenants would call dozens of times, and nobody would answer. People who did answer did not always have authority to enter the portal.</p><p>Whats more, many tenants were evicted after they applied for funding but before they received it, said Madeline Howard, </p> s<p>enior </p> a<p>ttorney at Western Center on Law &amp; Poverty, one of the law groups that helped file</p>d<p> the lawsuit. The state had no mechanism to track people who were evicted while awaiting assistance, Howard added.</p><p>Valeria De La Luz said she accumulated over $30,000 in rent debt during the pandemic. The Los Angeles resident, who </p>only <p>speaks </p> only <p>Spanish, applied for rental assistance in November 2021. She was approved, she said, but the next day the decision switched to a denial due to insufficient evidence that she qualified. De La Luz submitted an appeal in March 2022, but has yet to hear from the housing department.</p><p>I dont feel safe at home, De La Luz said in an interview with </p> T<p>he </p>LA <p>Times.</p><p>On top of mounting debt and debacles with her landlord, De La Luz said she lost her job due to the pandemic and has been diagnosed with several health issues. She says she hesitates to receive the surgery she needs because she has no safe place to recover.</p><p>I do have some peace and quiet</p> .<p> I feel a little bit of a relief, but I am not calling this a win because I still have not gotten the funds that I was promised, De La Luz said. I know that Im not the only one.</p><p>Landlords, especially those who manage</p>d<p> small properties and are eligible for the relief, are also celebrating the settlement after losing several years of rental income during the pandemic. Debra Carlton, </p> e<p>xecutive </p> v<p>ice </p> p<p>resident of the California Apartment Ass</p>ociatio<p>n</p> .<p>, said she still expects some landlord applicants will receive denials. </p><p>It's been much harder on the smaller owners who can't balance it out with other tenants, she said. </p><p><b>The </b></p> <b>s</b><p><b>ettlement</b></p><p>Tenants who applied for the rental aid before the end of March 2022 and were denied by June 7 of that year or who have pending applications should expect to receive an update about their applications in the coming months, according to a </p>press  news <p>release</p> from June 5<p>.</p> <p><a href="https://publiccounsel.org/ca-rent-relief/">For many tenants</a>, </p> t<p>he housing department is required to issue new, more detailed denial notices. Applicants who are denied assistance will have 30 days to appeal.</p><p>Additionally, the settlement requires the state agency to make the appeals process easier, fix language barriers, and conduct an audit of denials from March to May 2022 due to "non-responsiveness." The department is also required under the legal agreement to fund local, community-based programs to help tenants navigate the appeals process.</p><p>Howard said that plaintiff lawyers and their clients will meet with the housing department every two weeks for three months, and then monthly to ensure that there is open communication in case problems arise.</p><p>In a February court filing, the housing department said it had some $300 million in state and federal funds left to administer.</p><p>Despite the settlement, rent debt left over from the pandemic will remain a source of stress, eviction</p>,<p> <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-10-28/rising-homelessness-in-the-latino-community">and homelessness</a>, Malik said, as renters have still been accruing debt after the application portal closed in March 2022.</p><p>This settlement doesn't mean that this issue is gone, she said.</p>For <p>Tenants and landlords with pending applications</p>, you<p> can access Public Counsel's FAQ at <a href="https://publiccounsel.org/ca-rent-relief/" target="_blank">www.carentrelief.org</a> or call Housing </p> I<p>s Key's call center at </p> (<p>833</p> )<p> 343-2122. To check your portal and update your information, visit <a href="https://hornellp-ca.neighborlysoftware.com/CaliforniaCovid19RentRelief/Participant">https://hornellp-ca.neighborlysoftware.com/CaliforniaCovid19RentRelief/Participant</a>.</p> Times staff writer Hannah Wiley contributed to this report.                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pandemic aid saved millions of Americans from eviction, and the data proves it</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-06-09/pandemic-aid-saved-millions-of-americans-eviction</link>
      <description>Millions of renters benefited from temporary programs such as the federal Emergency Rental Assistance Program during the COVID-19 pandemic.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 17:55:22 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Jennah Haque</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-06-09/pandemic-aid-saved-millions-of-americans-eviction</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-06-09/pandemic-aid-saved-millions-of-americans-eviction">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c7b5c3c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2F10%2F3c313b0a49ea9648f482aff12035%2Fla-photos-1staff-810342-na-0716-dc-building-mugs-kkn-10050.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/59461f9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2F10%2F3c313b0a49ea9648f482aff12035%2Fla-photos-1staff-810342-na-0716-dc-building-mugs-kkn-10050.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/44c3ae8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2F10%2F3c313b0a49ea9648f482aff12035%2Fla-photos-1staff-810342-na-0716-dc-building-mugs-kkn-10050.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/357d351/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2F10%2F3c313b0a49ea9648f482aff12035%2Fla-photos-1staff-810342-na-0716-dc-building-mugs-kkn-10050.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c3904c1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2F10%2F3c313b0a49ea9648f482aff12035%2Fla-photos-1staff-810342-na-0716-dc-building-mugs-kkn-10050.JPG 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="WASHINGTON, DC - JULY 16: The U.S. Treasury Building, photographed on Friday, July 16, 2021 in Washington, DC. (Kent Nishimura / Los Angeles Times)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/28ca678/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2F10%2F3c313b0a49ea9648f482aff12035%2Fla-photos-1staff-810342-na-0716-dc-building-mugs-kkn-10050.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7e64743/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2F10%2F3c313b0a49ea9648f482aff12035%2Fla-photos-1staff-810342-na-0716-dc-building-mugs-kkn-10050.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/71da351/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2F10%2F3c313b0a49ea9648f482aff12035%2Fla-photos-1staff-810342-na-0716-dc-building-mugs-kkn-10050.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6a5d6f6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2F10%2F3c313b0a49ea9648f482aff12035%2Fla-photos-1staff-810342-na-0716-dc-building-mugs-kkn-10050.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d93dbf4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2F10%2F3c313b0a49ea9648f482aff12035%2Fla-photos-1staff-810342-na-0716-dc-building-mugs-kkn-10050.JPG 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d93dbf4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2F10%2F3c313b0a49ea9648f482aff12035%2Fla-photos-1staff-810342-na-0716-dc-building-mugs-kkn-10050.JPG"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">WASHINGTON, DC - JULY 16: The U.S. Treasury Building, photographed on Friday, July 16, 2021 in Washington, DC. (Kent Nishimura / Los Angeles Times)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Kent Nishimura/Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Pandemic aid saved millions of Americans from eviction, and the data proves it</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" >        Jennah Haque    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Edwin Bautista was a senior at the University of Texas at Austin and part-time technician at a consulting firm when inflation started to ravage his spending power. After his rent surged past $1,000 a month in early 2021 he feared he would have to move out  until he got a $7,300 lifeline from the federal <a href="https://www.latimes.com/homeless-housing/story/2023-06-09/state-reaches-settlement-over-pandemic-rent-relief-what-tenants-and-landords-need-to-know">Emergency Rental Assistance Program</a>.</p><p>That kept him in his apartment and even helped him build a small nest egg. Now graduated and working full time, hes a <a href="https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2022-03-29/buying-a-socal-house-the-great-home-hunt-guide">first-time home buyer</a>.</p><p>Bautista is one of millions of renters who benefited from temporary programs put in place during the COVID-19 pandemic, including restrictions on evictions, income support  and the rental assistance program. One of the most ambitious investments in emergency housing in the nations history, it has disbursed $46 billion in aid to state and local governments since early 2021 and kept millions of people in their homes, according to an analysis of government data by Bloomberg News.</p><p>With rents still climbing and the economy at risk of a recession, housing advocates are urging the Biden administration to keep helping tenants. That will be hard under legislation signed into law last weekend that suspended the nations borrowing limit as it clawed back unused pandemic aid and imposed caps on future increases in the federal budget.</p><p>We are facing an affordable housing crisis in this country, yet Republican lawmakers are insisting on slashing funding for and jeopardizing the future of critical housing affordability programs that support working families, Sen. Tina Smith (D-Minn.) said in a statement.</p> State reaches settlement over pandemic rent relief: What tenants and landlords need to know <p>Surveys conducted by the U.S. Census Bureau show that, on average, 48.46 million people reported being caught up on their rent during the first quarter of this year, 4.7 million more than before the Emergency Rental Assistance Program was put in place as the economy was reeling from shutdowns. Even though the estimated number of renters in the country increased during the period, the number of people behind on their rent fell.</p><p>These policies drove eviction filing rates to historic lows," </p>according to <p>a <a href="https://evictionlab.org/covid-era-policies-cut-eviction-filings-by-more-than-half/">report</a> from the Eviction Lab </p> stated<p>. Eviction filings were cut by more than half </p> inof<p> 31 cities they sampled, largely due to COVID-era policies, according to the lab, a housing research group at Princeton University.</p><p>Nevertheless, Republicans have shown little appetite for continuing pandemic-era programs, including for rent assistance, as they seek to reduce the federal budget deficit.</p><p>Progressives attempts to make crisis programs permanent, even after an emergency ends, is just another example of Democrats spending taxpayer money we dont have, Rep. Patrick McHenry (R-N.C.), a key negotiator on the debt limit bill, said in a statement. Now its time to end this program.</p><p>The Treasury Department let states, counties and cities use the emergency rent aid in one of three ways: on direct assistance to households, housing stability measures and administrative expenses. About $33 billion of the $46 billion was used for direct assistance to more than 7 million households, according to a Bloomberg evaluation of Treasury data.</p> L.A. County supervisors propose adopting permanent rental protections<p>States, on average, sent 70% of their used funds directly to tenants and landlords, and those that spent most of the money for direct assistance tended to help more tenants get up to date on their rent  suggesting the program was having the desired effect. California, for example, used more than 75% of the $5.6 billion allocated to it from the rental assistance program for direct aid to tenants and landlords. The result: an average of 986,000 more renters were caught up on rent than before the program was established. New York saw about 440,000 residents catch up, or almost 10% of the tenants in the state.</p><p>North Dakota spent less on rental payments and it is one of four states  Louisiana, South Carolina and Georgia are the others  that saw the number of tenants behind on rent grow.</p><p>Direct assistance was limited to renters with an income below 80% of the areas median income and who were able to demonstrate that they were at risk of homelessness and </p>and<p> were suffering a financial hardship because of the pandemic.</p><p>Bautista, the former University of Texas student, met the eligibility </p> requirements<p>. He now works as a management assistant for a low-income housing coalition. On the side, he doles out affordable housing advice to college students and recent grads.</p><p>Im not supposed to be where I am today, he said. This program changed my life.</p> Medical bills pushed a Santa Monica family into poverty. They're not alone<p>The Treasury Department and state governments were criticized&nbsp;for dispersing money too slowly at the programs onset. Some states even had their funding reallocated.</p><p>The Treasury said it tracked some information</p> ,<p> like the number of dollars distributed, the number of households served</p>,<p> and the demographics of its applicants. However, program administrators said they didn't have the bandwidth to measure or poll whether recipients were able to catch up on rent while it was dispersing funds.</p><p>We faced a race with time. Experts were projecting a tsunami of evictions if we did not get the emergency rental payments flowing before the eviction moratorium ended, Gene Sperling, a senior White House advisor and coordinator of the Biden administrations American Rescue Plan, said in a statement. The fact that we actually saw eviction rates go below historic averages was proof we did get payments out in time.</p><p>Data on evictions is hard to come by, said Peter Hepburn, associate director of the Eviction Lab. There are more than 3,000 independently operated county courts that handle evictions, many of which often keep documents sealed, undigitized or both.</p><p>The lab credits the pandemic measures for preventing at least 800,000 evictions in 31 U.S. metropolitan areas it studied.</p><p>The rental assistance program itself has been a godsend and a blessing for everyone who has been able to use those funds to remain housed, said Mark Fessler, deputy director of litigation and training at the nonprofit South Carolina Legal Services.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thousands of Southern California workers authorize the largest hotel strike in modern U.S. history</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-06-09/southern-california-hotel-workers-approve-potential-strike</link>
      <description>Hotel workers in Los Angeles and Orange counties voted to authorize a strike during the height of tourism season if talks don't result in a new contract.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 12:00:35 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-06-09/southern-california-hotel-workers-approve-potential-strike</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Renters dominate California — but they are struggling to survive</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-07/california-housing-2nd-lowest-rate-of-solo-occupancy-2nd-highest-rate-of-renting</link>
      <description>New census data reveals over a quarter of U.S. households had solo occupants in 2020, more than three times the 1940 estimate and more than twice the 1960 level.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 13:00:31 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Terry Castleman</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-07/california-housing-2nd-lowest-rate-of-solo-occupancy-2nd-highest-rate-of-renting</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-07/california-housing-2nd-lowest-rate-of-solo-occupancy-2nd-highest-rate-of-renting">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5dde130/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F04%2Fbc%2F89fedba349668e7d18f860797629%2F1304825-me-overcrowding-story-07-mjc-2.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d41e3b3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F04%2Fbc%2F89fedba349668e7d18f860797629%2F1304825-me-overcrowding-story-07-mjc-2.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0dfc63b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F04%2Fbc%2F89fedba349668e7d18f860797629%2F1304825-me-overcrowding-story-07-mjc-2.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c2c9d4f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F04%2Fbc%2F89fedba349668e7d18f860797629%2F1304825-me-overcrowding-story-07-mjc-2.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ed7a00e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F04%2Fbc%2F89fedba349668e7d18f860797629%2F1304825-me-overcrowding-story-07-mjc-2.JPG 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="LOS ANGELES, CA - JUNE 02: Evelyn Arceo works as a baker at Universal Studios and said that she bakes the cakes for the company parties celebrating their profits but she lives in a crowded apartment with her four children. Her three oldest children share this room. Her youngest will usually sleep with her in the living room. Photographed on Friday, June 2, 2023. (Myung J. Chun / Los Angeles Times)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6b8a56a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F04%2Fbc%2F89fedba349668e7d18f860797629%2F1304825-me-overcrowding-story-07-mjc-2.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/dbe977d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F04%2Fbc%2F89fedba349668e7d18f860797629%2F1304825-me-overcrowding-story-07-mjc-2.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2ec790e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F04%2Fbc%2F89fedba349668e7d18f860797629%2F1304825-me-overcrowding-story-07-mjc-2.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/370016e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F04%2Fbc%2F89fedba349668e7d18f860797629%2F1304825-me-overcrowding-story-07-mjc-2.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a2645e3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F04%2Fbc%2F89fedba349668e7d18f860797629%2F1304825-me-overcrowding-story-07-mjc-2.JPG 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a2645e3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6720x4480+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F04%2Fbc%2F89fedba349668e7d18f860797629%2F1304825-me-overcrowding-story-07-mjc-2.JPG"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">LOS ANGELES, CA - JUNE 02: Evelyn Arceo works as a baker at Universal Studios and said that she bakes the cakes for the company parties celebrating their profits but she lives in a crowded apartment with her four children. Her three oldest children share this room. Her youngest will usually sleep with her in the living room. Photographed on Friday, June 2, 2023. (Myung J. Chun / Los Angeles Times)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Myung J. Chun/Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Renters dominate California  but they are struggling to survive</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/terry-castleman">        Terry Castleman    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 7, 2023">June 7, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Evelyn Arceo holds down a full-time job as a baker at Universal Studios Hollywood, earning $19 an hour. But even when she gets a few hours of overtime at the theme park, the single mother of four can barely afford the rent of her one-bedroom apartment in Panorama City.</p><p>On her salary, buying a home is out of the question.</p><p>Already, her monthly rent of $1,300 is "just too expensive at this point," Arceo said, with late fees of $40 to $50 compounding her financial plight. "I don't think I've ever been on time on my rent." </p><p>Arceo's situation is common in California, which is among the nation's leaders in renter-occupied housing</p> units<p>. In the Golden State, 45.5% of housing units were occupied by renters in 2020, a small increase from the 44% rate </p>of renters<p> in 2010, according to newly released data by the U.S. Census </p> Bureau<p>. </p><p>California was second only to New York, where 49.7% of the housing units are renter occupied. The District of Columbia was an outlier, at 61.7%. </p><p>Nationwide, the rate of renter-occupied housing units  36.9%  is at its highest point since 1970.</p><p> "The growth of renter-occupied units continues to outpace the growth of owner-occupied units," the Census Bureau said in a statement.</p><p>The states with the lowest renter rate  and therefore the highest owner-occupied rates  were West Virginia, at 27.4%, and Maine, at 28.9%.</p><p>Hans Johnson, a demographer at the Public Policy Institute of California, said the new data were </p>was <p>"not shocking." California's high rate of renters can be attributed mostly to "the high cost of housing," Johnson said.</p><p>The annual income needed to buy a home in Los Angeles rose last year </p>to <p>beyond $220,000, according to a study by <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-12-01/you-need-earn-more-than-220000-year-buy-house-in-los-angeles">the residential real estate firm Redfin</a>. With higher mortgage interest rates and inflation cutting into household incomes, the ability to own a home is increasingly </p>beyond  out of<p> reach for </p>more <p>residents in Los Angeles, where the median annual household income in 2020 was just over $65,000.</p><p>High housing costs are also a factor in putting California near the bottom in another category: the rate of single-occupancy households.</p><p>New data from the <a href="https://www.census.gov/newsroom/press-releases/2023/2020-census-demographic-profile-and-dhc.html">Census Bureau</a> show that more than a quarter of all households in America  27.6%  had just one occupant in 2020. The rate of solo occupancy is more than three times the recorded level in 1940, 7.7%.</p><p>A Times analysis found that California ranked 49th of the 50 states in the rate of single-occupant dwellings, with 23% of households occupied by just one person  a rate that has remained steady for about 20 years. Only Utah had a lower rate, at 20%.</p><p>North Dakota had the highest rate of single occupancy, 32.8%. The District of Columbia's rate was an astronomical 43.7%.</p><p>In states </p>outside  other than <p>California, "where rents are much lower or the opportunity to buy a house is better, it's not as difficult for a single worker" to live alone, Johnson said.</p><p>Another factor is California having a "larger immigrant population than in the rest of the U.S.," according to Johnson. "It is more common for immigrant families to live in multigenerational households," he said.</p><p>Utah has the lowest rate of single-occupant homes because the state has a high marriage rate and an uncommonly high number of children per household, Johnson said. He attributed those trends partially to Mormon residents, who make up well over half of the state's population.</p><p>The increase in people living alone coincides with higher social isolation, a worrying trend outlined by U.S. Surgeon Gen. Dr. Vivek Murthy in a <a href="https://www.hhs.gov/about/news/2023/05/03/new-surgeon-general-advisory-raises-alarm-about-devastating-impact-epidemic-loneliness-isolation-united-states.html">recent report</a>.</p><p>Our epidemic of loneliness and isolation has been an underappreciated public health crisis that has harmed individual and societal health. Our relationships are a source of healing and well-being hiding in plain sight  one that can help us live healthier, more fulfilled and more productive lives,&nbsp;Murthy said.</p><p>Such isolation increases the risk of premature death by more than 60% and includes higher risks of heart disease, stroke and dementia, according to the report.</p><p>To counter the increased isolation, "communities must design environments that promote connection," the report said, and "invest in institutions that bring people together."</p><p>While more Americans are living alone, Arceo, 32, worries about providing her children a home where they can enjoy some space for themselves.</p><p>With a 14-year-old son in the throes of adolescence and a 12-year-old son entering that stage, "they need their privacy," she said.</p><p>"It's insane to say that I work for this company and can't afford to give my kids a proper living," Arceo said.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/8e/4e/0c89fd614ee4a79b2e3a3b347c41/1304825-me-overcrowding-story-04-mjc-2.JPG"></figure><p>She has worked as a baker for the theme park for eight years, but Arceo notes that "I was homeless for the first year working at Universal," when she was forced to live with her then-three children in hotels, friends' homes, wherever they could.</p><p>With the bakery short-staffed, she has recently picked up "at least an hour of overtime a day," but it hasn't been enough, forcing her "to choose whether I pay my car insurance or my rent," she said.</p><p>Johnson, the demographer, pointed to possible hope on the horizon. He noted that California <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-03-25/california-census-data">has reported a steady decline in population</a> since 2020  starting at the beginning of the pandemic. The drop has coincided with the construction of more housing, primarily in the state's suburbs and exurbs.</p><p>"If California continues to lose people and build housing, at some point it should make a dent in the housing deficit."</p><p>A construction surge is not likely to make enough of a difference to change the conditions for low-wage workers like Arceo.</p><p>Looking to the future, she doesn't see many options. </p><p>"I can't afford to move," she said. </p>"The conditions of the apartment are not good at all," with mold from January's rains still not removed despite repeated complaints to her landlord.                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>String of eviction notices leads to growing concerns about Skid Row receiver</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/homeless-housing/story/2023-06-07/concern-growing-over-skid-row-receiver-following-eviction-notices</link>
      <description>Tenants at Skid Row Housing Trust buildings were issued eviction notices that the city attorney's office deemed illegal. The receiver overseeing the properties has rescinded them.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 12:00:28 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Liam Dillon</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/homeless-housing/story/2023-06-07/concern-growing-over-skid-row-receiver-following-eviction-notices</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/homeless-housing/story/2023-06-07/concern-growing-over-skid-row-receiver-following-eviction-notices">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1514961/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3600x2400+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F50%2Ff9%2F871193e945f9ba3d94ec337efb65%2F1266563-me-0310-skid-row-housing-trust-017-ik.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a5a75ca/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3600x2400+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F50%2Ff9%2F871193e945f9ba3d94ec337efb65%2F1266563-me-0310-skid-row-housing-trust-017-ik.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2506e14/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3600x2400+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F50%2Ff9%2F871193e945f9ba3d94ec337efb65%2F1266563-me-0310-skid-row-housing-trust-017-ik.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/36b32c4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3600x2400+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F50%2Ff9%2F871193e945f9ba3d94ec337efb65%2F1266563-me-0310-skid-row-housing-trust-017-ik.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5433ce9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3600x2400+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F50%2Ff9%2F871193e945f9ba3d94ec337efb65%2F1266563-me-0310-skid-row-housing-trust-017-ik.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="LOS ANGELES, CA - MARCH 10: Due to a recent fire boarded up and closed Skid Row Housing Trust property Dewey Hotel on Friday, March 10, 2023 in Los Angeles, CA. (Irfan Khan / Los Angeles Times)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/cbcf567/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3600x2400+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F50%2Ff9%2F871193e945f9ba3d94ec337efb65%2F1266563-me-0310-skid-row-housing-trust-017-ik.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1e437a8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3600x2400+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F50%2Ff9%2F871193e945f9ba3d94ec337efb65%2F1266563-me-0310-skid-row-housing-trust-017-ik.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e8f74bb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3600x2400+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F50%2Ff9%2F871193e945f9ba3d94ec337efb65%2F1266563-me-0310-skid-row-housing-trust-017-ik.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/64a5f27/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3600x2400+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F50%2Ff9%2F871193e945f9ba3d94ec337efb65%2F1266563-me-0310-skid-row-housing-trust-017-ik.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/befa565/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3600x2400+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F50%2Ff9%2F871193e945f9ba3d94ec337efb65%2F1266563-me-0310-skid-row-housing-trust-017-ik.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/befa565/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3600x2400+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F50%2Ff9%2F871193e945f9ba3d94ec337efb65%2F1266563-me-0310-skid-row-housing-trust-017-ik.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">LOS ANGELES, CA - MARCH 10: Due to a recent fire boarded up and closed Skid Row Housing Trust property Dewey Hotel on Friday, March 10, 2023 in Los Angeles, CA. (Irfan Khan / Los Angeles Times)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Irfan Khan/Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>String of eviction notices leads to growing concerns about Skid Row receiver</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">California Politics </h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/liam-dillon">        Liam Dillon    </a></address><address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/doug-smith">        Doug Smith    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 7, 2023">June 7, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>A spate of eviction notices issued at properties owned by Skid Rows largest nonprofit landlord is prompting Los Angeles city officials to demand answers from the person they installed to oversee the buildings.</p><p>City Atty. Hydee Feldstein Soto deemed the eviction notices illegal and</p> <p>said </p>that <p>the apparent blunder is contributing to an erosion of the citys confidence in Mark Adams, the receiver <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-04-07/skid-row-housing-trust-buildings-placed-under-receivership">appointed by a Los Angeles Superior Court judge in April</a> to fix 29 buildings owned by Skid Row Housing Trust after <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-03-26/skid-row-housing-trust-collapse-los-angeles-homeless-housing">its financial collapse</a> earlier this year.</p><p>These are formerly unhoused tenants, they are incredibly vulnerable, they rely on critical supportive services, Feldstein Soto said. Its unacceptable that those notices went out, period.</p><p>The notices</p>, <p> sent by </p> Beach Front Property Management, <p>the </p>property management<p> firm Adams hired</p>, <p> told residents they had three days to pay overdue rent or leave their apartment or else the firm would initiate eviction proceedings that could include additional financial damages and harm to the tenants credit rating.</p><p>One eviction notice reviewed by The Times showed that the tenant owed $56.</p><p>Feldstein Sotos office <a href="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/15/88/bbfe3ddd4601a5e1f2b83f02a38d/los-angeles-city-atty-feldstein-soto-letter-to-receiver-adams-6-6-23.pdf" target="_blank">sent Adams a letter Tuesday</a> telling him that the notices were prohibited under city laws, including a recently passed measure that does not allow landlords to evict tenants who are only one month behind on rent. It also reminded Adams that he had pledged in court documents never to evict a tenant for overdue rent only.</p><p>The citys letter tells Adams that he </p>needs  has 48 hours<p> to provide a written accounting of how many notices went out and who authorized them</p> within 48 hours<p>.</p><p>In an email to The Times, Adams said that the notices were a mistake and sent without his approval. He said he<b> </b>distributed <a href="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/17/51/b1cd45ec4f93bf252fa37f05fa3a/receiver-adams-letter-to-skid-row-housing-trust-tenants-6-5-23.pdf" target="_blank">a letter rescinding them</a> to all 1,500 Skid Row Housing Trust tenants on Monday.</p><p>Solely because of failure to pay rent, I will not seek to evict anyone, Adams said in the letter.</p><p>Adams said he didnt know how many tenants had received the eviction notices, and that any further similar action taken by Beach Front Property Management</p>, the firm Adams hired,<p> would be grounds for its termination. A spokesperson for the firm referred comment to the receiver.</p><p>The eviction notices are the latest example of concerns about Adams performance from city officials and the trusts tenants.</p><p>Two residents of the Boyd Hotel who received eviction notices told The Times that conditions there had changed little, and in some ways grown worse, in the two months of the receivership.</p><p>Only one of the four bathrooms on their floor works reliably, they said. A second is in and out of service, and the maintenance crew has locked the other two, they said. Their case managers have been laid off, and people from the street continue to enter the building at all hours to use the bathrooms, sleep, use drugs or buy contraband.</p><p>This spring, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-03-30/la-receivership-skid-row-housing-trust-buildings">the city pushed for Adams to be put in charge</a> of the properties after the nonprofit housing provider had largely abandoned them in squalid conditions. Many tenants are elderly, disabled or suffering from mental health and drug problems.</p><p>Under a receivership, Adams would have the authority to borrow money to pay for repairs and upgrades to the trusts residential hotels and other low-income apartment complexes, putting them on solid financial footing  ultimately to allow other affordable housing providers to take over.</p><p>Feldstein Soto has said that the trusts rapid disintegration required the city to turn to Adams, who has handled 300 receiverships over more than two decades, as the only one who could handle the situation despite not fully vetting his resume beforehand.</p><p>A Times review of <a href="https://www.latimes.com/homeless-housing/story/2023-05-17/skid-row-housing-trust-mark-adams-receiver">Adams record published last month</a> found that in some cases, tenants faced the risk of eviction, property owners lost their houses and multiple judges determined he inflated his fees by six-figure amounts. Additionally, in two cases comparable in size and scope to the trust matter, Adams left years before they were resolved and, in court filings, omitted key facts about his involvement in them.</p><p>Feldstein Soto continued to maintain that the situations urgency pointed toward Adams as uniquely qualified to address it. But she said shes been unimpressed by Adams performance.</p><p>A $1.3</p> -<p>million loan Adams has received came with a 15% interest rate, violating an agreement the city had with the receiver not to exceed 10% interest when borrowing money, a deputy city attorney<b> </b>said at a court hearing last month. Feldstein Soto said </p>that <p>the city also has been spot checking trust properties and found that there isnt always management and security on site, contrary to Adams assertions.</p><p>We believed that this receiver had both the liquidity and the experience and expertise to quickly get on top of and manage the situation, Feldstein Soto said. I think it's fair to say we've been disappointed.</p><p>In court, an attorney representing Adams said that lenders required the higher interest rate after investors in some of the trust's better properties expressed a desire to remove them from the receivership, making the deal more risky for them. Through a spokesperson, Adams said that there is 24/7 security at every site and that he never pledged to have round-the-clock management.</p><p>The two tenants at the Boyd, a 112-year-old residential hotel with 61 units, said theyve been withholding</p> their<p> rent because they have long</p> -<p>standing legal claims against Skid Row Housing Trust over conditions at the building.</p><p>Maintenance crews, they said, are beginning to repair or replace clogged sinks in individual rooms but that drains are still chronically backed up and mold is growing in showers in shared bathrooms on each floor. Some people, they said, block the drains intentionally to use the showers for laundry.</p><p>The two male residents spoke to </p> T<p>he Times anonymously, one to respect his 12-step program and the other out of concern his job would be jeopardized.</p><p>They said the receiver has staffed the building with guards from three </p>different <p>security firms, but they have not stopped non-residents from entering the hotel at all hours to use the bathrooms, sleep, do drugs or buy contraband.</p><p>There's been people that have been living there that are not on a lease or not attached to anybody, one said.</p><p>At first the guards were throwing the interlopers out but then stopped, they said.</p><p>One man said a homeless person who had struck him with a steel baton several months ago has returned after his release from jail.</p><p>They said that a tenant on their floor runs a store out of his unit selling cigarettes, beer and liquor, and street people come to his door at all hours.</p><p>One of the residents emailed The Times a photo Tuesday of trash and feces in a hallway that he said was left by a non-tenant.</p><p>The men suspected the eviction notices were a ploy to get them to leave their apartments because they were complaining about the Boyds conditions.</p><p>I think they want to empty the building and start over with brand new people, one said.</p><p>Joseph Woods, an attorney representing the two residents and co-counsel in a habitability lawsuit filed on behalf of tenants in two other Skid Row Housing Trust buildings, said he has seen some small but important steps taken by the receiver.</p><p>We are pleased to see that elevators are being kept in good repair and functional order, which was not true in the past, Woods said.</p><p>Woods said that the receivership has added security, but it remains inadequate.</p><p>Feldstein Soto, Mayor Karen Bass and other city leaders have said their primary goal has been to prevent mass evictions of the trusts tenants, a potential<b> </b>catastrophe that could add hundreds to Skid Rows already overwhelming homeless population.</p><p>"This was an absolutely egregious mistake," Bass said of the eviction notices in a statement. "I support the city attorneys investigation into this incident and steps she is taking to ensure that the rights of all tenants of Skid Row Housing Trust properties are protected and secured."</p><p>City Councilmember Kevin de Len, who represents Skid Row, said that Feldstein Soto and Adams have cut the council out of decisions about the receivership. The eviction notices, he said, provide another example of the need for the council to exercise greater oversight.</p><p>Its not a good first step to introduce yourself to the city by erroneously or mistakenly issuing out eviction notices, sending a panic into already very vulnerable residents, said De Len, who authored a council motion calling for more regular updates on the receivers activities </p>following  after<p> last months Times story on Adams background. When it comes to the receiver and the city attorney, its on both of them. They gotta own it.</p><p>De Len also said hes deeply concerned about the receiverships effects on the citys finances, especially given prior cases </p>where in which<p> judges have cited Adams for overbilling.</p><p>Normally, receiverships pay for repairs and the receivers fees by tapping properties equity or through proceeds from a property sale. But with the trust on the brink of insolvency and federal and local restrictions preventing tenants rents from ballooning, city housing officials have acknowledged the city treasury likely will be on the hook for at least some of the still-unknown cost</p> s<p>.</p><p>Adams has assigned 18 employees, including himself, to the trust matter with hourly rates </p>ranging <p>from $151 to $465. An accounting filed by Adams in court lists $187,000 in expenses and advances incurred by his firm in April. Additionally, Adams has received authority from the court to borrow up to $5.3 million to finance repairs.</p><p>I dont think the majority of the council </p> m<p>embers are aware that the citys budget is an ATM machine that will be strictly controlled by a judge and a receiver, De Len said.</p><p>Feldstein Soto said that her office was leading an investigation into Adams performance and expects to reveal its results </p> before prior to <p>the next court hearing in the case scheduled for June 15. She declined to describe what the investigation entailed but didnt rule out that she might recommend Adams be replaced.</p><p>We, at this point, have to consider all kinds of possibilities, Feldstein Soto said.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to the L.A. Troll Apartment. You can live under a bridge for only $250,000</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-06/welcome-to-the-l-a-troll-apartment-you-can-live-under-a-bridge-for-only-250-000</link>
      <description>Housing in Los Angeles does not come cheap. But one Alhambra apartment lets you live more like a troll under a bridge for only $250,000.</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 18:22:06 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Noah Goldberg</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-06/welcome-to-the-l-a-troll-apartment-you-can-live-under-a-bridge-for-only-250-000</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-06/welcome-to-the-l-a-troll-apartment-you-can-live-under-a-bridge-for-only-250-000">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1b5dab4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/750x938+0+0/resize/320x400!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F9d%2Fd1870d5043ce828f2281523dfee0%2F1340-east-main-street-01.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8f9a01c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/750x938+0+0/resize/568x710!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F9d%2Fd1870d5043ce828f2281523dfee0%2F1340-east-main-street-01.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/dc11d43/2147483647/strip/true/crop/750x938+0+0/resize/768x961!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F9d%2Fd1870d5043ce828f2281523dfee0%2F1340-east-main-street-01.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/abe3143/2147483647/strip/true/crop/750x938+0+0/resize/1024x1281!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F9d%2Fd1870d5043ce828f2281523dfee0%2F1340-east-main-street-01.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/716dd44/2147483647/strip/true/crop/750x938+0+0/resize/1200x1501!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F9d%2Fd1870d5043ce828f2281523dfee0%2F1340-east-main-street-01.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="1340 Main St, Alhambra, California is on the market for $250,000"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9c87eb1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/750x938+0+0/resize/320x400!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F9d%2Fd1870d5043ce828f2281523dfee0%2F1340-east-main-street-01.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/37b93c5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/750x938+0+0/resize/568x710!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F9d%2Fd1870d5043ce828f2281523dfee0%2F1340-east-main-street-01.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a2517dd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/750x938+0+0/resize/768x961!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F9d%2Fd1870d5043ce828f2281523dfee0%2F1340-east-main-street-01.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c56b716/2147483647/strip/true/crop/750x938+0+0/resize/1024x1281!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F9d%2Fd1870d5043ce828f2281523dfee0%2F1340-east-main-street-01.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d84b6ae/2147483647/strip/true/crop/750x938+0+0/resize/1200x1501!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F9d%2Fd1870d5043ce828f2281523dfee0%2F1340-east-main-street-01.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="1501"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d84b6ae/2147483647/strip/true/crop/750x938+0+0/resize/1200x1501!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F9d%2Fd1870d5043ce828f2281523dfee0%2F1340-east-main-street-01.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">1340 Main St, Alhambra, California is on the market for $250,000</div><div class="figure-credit">(Douglas Lee/Courtesy of Douglas Lee / Compas)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Welcome to the L.A. Troll Apartment. You can live under a bridge for only $250,000</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/noah-goldberg">        Noah Goldberg    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 6, 2023">June 6, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Housing does not come cheap in Los Angeles. But if you are willing to live somewhat like a troll, there might be something available for you in Alhambra. </p><p>Compass Real Estate recently put on the market a one-bedroom fixer-upper </p> onat 1340 <p>East Main Street that sits under a bridge, within walking distance of a Vietnamese restaurant and a hair salon. </p><p>Southern California's pricey housing market has forced many potential buyers to either settle into comfortable homes in far-flung suburbs or purchase postage stamp-size properties closer to the region's job centers. The recent <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-04-01/as-spring-buying-season-kicks-off-homes-for-sale-are-scarce">hikes in mortgage interest rates</a> have only aggravated the problem.</p><p>Another extreme option for potential buyers: Consider a quirky, one-of-a-kind property like Alhambra's bridge house. </p><p>The 450-square-foot apartment built in 1949 has a terrace that looks over a stream and a rooftop patio that sits next to a road bridge, separated only by a fence. It is priced at $250,000  a steal considering the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-25/southern-california-home-prices-have-been-falling-but-are-the-drops-over">median sale price</a> for an existing single-family house in Southern California is about $785,000.</p><p>"We had no comparables  no similar properties," said Doug Lee, the Compass agent who listed the home, which he said once belonged to a high school friend's parents. "This is a very, very unique property."</p><p>Lee said his friend's parents purchased the home in 2005 for about $72,000.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/cf/71/907a88374fd5b985c8d287115695/1340-east-main-street-02.jpg"></figure><p>Already, Lee has seen a flurry of interest in the home, which has been on the market for a few weeks. </p><p>He held open houses and showed the place to 40 or 50 groups each day, he said. </p><p>"This weekend we had it open and it was a zoo," he said. </p><p>The average one-bedroom home in the Alhambra neighborhood </p>will<p> costs </p>you<p> about $350,000, so </p>he <p>Lee decided to strategically price the </p>this <p>apartment at </p> just under <p>$250,000 to generate interest  and because there's no dedicated parking spot, Lee said. </p><p>"</p>Theres no dedicated parking. <p>It's a fixer-upper. We didn't know how responsive the market would be," he said. </p><p>The </p>apartment's <p>low price makes it one of only 11 properties in the county listed for under $250,000, Lee said. </p><p>There is one potential hiccup. While most homeowners own the land under their house, the bridge is presumably public land, Lee said. The real estate agents are working to clear up such property issues with the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers. </p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Celebs dodged millions in L.A.’s ‘mansion tax.’ Meet the industry guarding their wealth</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-02/celebrities-la-mansion-tax-homelessness-affordable-housing</link>
      <description>The 'wealth defense industry' — a network of accountants and consultants tasked with helping the rich stay rich — is responsible for homeowners avoiding L.A.'s 'mansion tax.'</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2023 12:00:58 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-02/celebrities-la-mansion-tax-homelessness-affordable-housing</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In downtown L.A., Bass' plan to clear encampments faces crime, addiction and resistance</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-30/la-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance</link>
      <description>Weeks after the Inside Safe program focused on the streets around El Pueblo, the area still has at least three dozen tents. Other areas face similar issues.</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2023 12:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>David Zahniser</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-30/la-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-30/la-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2988865/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3900x2935+0+0/resize/320x241!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fae%2F87139deb4e129d9802aa6d00df10%2F1300842-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance-21-ajs.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/49c96e4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3900x2935+0+0/resize/568x427!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fae%2F87139deb4e129d9802aa6d00df10%2F1300842-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance-21-ajs.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/429614e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3900x2935+0+0/resize/768x578!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fae%2F87139deb4e129d9802aa6d00df10%2F1300842-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance-21-ajs.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b72ba6e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3900x2935+0+0/resize/1024x771!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fae%2F87139deb4e129d9802aa6d00df10%2F1300842-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance-21-ajs.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d16888f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3900x2935+0+0/resize/1200x903!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fae%2F87139deb4e129d9802aa6d00df10%2F1300842-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance-21-ajs.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Los Angeles, CA - May 24: David Ruther, who says he&#x27;s been homeless more than a decade, turned down Mayor Bass&#x27; Safe Inside program as he stands outside his tent, part of a homeless encampment on Broadway next to the public staircase in downtown Los Angeles Wednesday, May 24, 2023. Since taking office, Mayor Karen Bass has told audiences that she has found that L.A.&#x27;s unhoused will say yes when offered the chance to move inside. But in some locations, the mayor is hitting a wall - sending her Inside Safe team to encampments where not everyone has been willing to leave. On the sidewalks around the El Pueblo Historic Monument in downtown Los Angeles, some have decided to stay put. There and in other locations, new homeless people have quickly arrived, putting up new tents. (Allen J. Schaben / Los Angeles Times)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/65cb90d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3900x2935+0+0/resize/320x241!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fae%2F87139deb4e129d9802aa6d00df10%2F1300842-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance-21-ajs.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/243cfff/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3900x2935+0+0/resize/568x427!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fae%2F87139deb4e129d9802aa6d00df10%2F1300842-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance-21-ajs.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e466b31/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3900x2935+0+0/resize/768x578!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fae%2F87139deb4e129d9802aa6d00df10%2F1300842-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance-21-ajs.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/eddade3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3900x2935+0+0/resize/1024x771!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fae%2F87139deb4e129d9802aa6d00df10%2F1300842-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance-21-ajs.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d9aa666/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3900x2935+0+0/resize/1200x903!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fae%2F87139deb4e129d9802aa6d00df10%2F1300842-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance-21-ajs.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="903"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d9aa666/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3900x2935+0+0/resize/1200x903!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fae%2F87139deb4e129d9802aa6d00df10%2F1300842-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance-21-ajs.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Los Angeles, CA - May 24: David Ruther, who says hes been homeless more than a decade, turned down Mayor Bass Safe Inside program as he stands outside his tent, part of a homeless encampment on Broadway next to the public staircase in downtown Los Angeles Wednesday, May 24, 2023. Since taking office, Mayor Karen Bass has told audiences that she has found that L.A.s unhoused will say yes when offered the chance to move inside. But in some locations, the mayor is hitting a wall - sending her Inside Safe team to encampments where not everyone has been willing to leave. On the sidewalks around the El Pueblo Historic Monument in downtown Los Angeles, some have decided to stay put. There and in other locations, new homeless people have quickly arrived, putting up new tents. (Allen J. Schaben / Los Angeles Times)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Allen J. Schaben/Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>In downtown L.A., Bass&#x27; plan to clear encampments faces crime, addiction and resistance</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">L.A. Politics </h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/david-zahniser">        David Zahniser    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="May 30, 2023">May 30, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Homeless outreach workers went to the streets of downtown Los Angeles last month and delivered what is now a seasoned sales pitch: Give up your spot on the sidewalk, and try living in a nearby hotel room instead.</p><p>David Ruther, who has a tent on Broadway near the 101 Freeway, had an emphatic response: No way.</p><p>Ruther denounced the rules that are in place at the L.A. Grand, one of the hotels being used by the city as homeless housing. He said it's not right that unhoused residents have had their bags inspected when they walk into that hotel.</p><p>"I told them I wasn't going to give up my constitutional rights, and have them search me every time I go to the store to buy a soda pop or a pack of beer," said Ruther, sitting in an office chair, clutching a Starbucks cup of coffee and a Newport cigarette.</p><p>Since </p> she tooktaking <p>office, Mayor Karen Bass' Inside Safe initiative has moved more than 1,200 homeless people off the street in <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-01-11/mayor-karen-bass-inside-safe-venice-homeless-encampment">Venice</a>, North Hollywood, Del Rey, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-13/homeless-encampment-beverly-grove-karen-bass-inside-safe">Beverly Grove</a> and about a dozen other L.A. neighborhoods. In many cases, encampment residents went into the same motel or group of motels, leaving an area free of tents.</p><p>Yet Bass' initiative recently stalled in one part of downtown Los Angeles: the streets that surround the <a href="https://elpueblo.lacity.gov/about-us" target="_blank">El Pueblo de Los Angeles Historic Monument</a>, the city's birthplace and home to Olvera Street and other attractions.</p><p>In April, outreach workers with the Inside Safe program went to that neighborhood and persuaded an estimated 78 people to go indoors, according to figures provided by the mayor's team.</p><p>Yet a month later, </p> at least three dozenabout two dozen<p> tents still populate the streets around El Pueblo, including Main, Spring, Cesar Chavez and Broadway, where Ruther keeps his tent.</p><p>In some locations, new arrivals have taken the place of those who accepted hotel rooms. In others, longtime encampment residents have made clear to outreach workers that they're not going anywhere.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/d3/ad/d90dca994af5b9ce7398e8e42473/1300842-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance-18-ajs.jpg"></figure><p>Bass' team acknowledged the challenges in a <a href="https://ens.lacity.org/cao/cao_budget_memo/caocao_budget_memo2925171363_05042023.pdf" target="_blank">May 3 memo</a>, telling </p> City Council<p> members the Inside Safe program had encountered drug addiction, serious mental health issues, criminal activity and "housing-resistant individuals" in that part of the city.</p><p>Despite the involvement of two county agencies and several nonprofit groups, "the array of needs did not allow us to get everyone into housing," wrote Mercedes Marquez, the mayor's homelessness czar. </p><p>The Inside Safe program, which just received $250 million in next year's city budget, has targeted 17 locations since December. Bass, early in her tenure as mayor, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-01-11/mayor-karen-bass-inside-safe-venice-homeless-encampment">said</a> Angelenos will not view that initiative as a success until their communities are free of encampments. They want the tents to go, she said at the time.</p><p>Still, Bass says she's not discouraged by the pace of progress at El Pueblo, pointing out that the vast majority of homeless people being contacted by her program are still saying yes.</p><p>In an interview last week, Bass said the Inside Safe program has faced an "intense" set of problems, particularly drug addiction, both at El Pueblo and on the streets that abut the 110 Freeway in South Los Angeles. Those locations have made up three of the last four Inside Safe operations.</p><p>"There were literally people that overdosed during the operation" at El Pueblo, she said. "And the only thing that saved them was the fact that we were with USC's street medicine [teams], and they had to administer Narcan."</p><p>Bass said her homelessness team will carry out a "deep dive" on Inside Safe in the coming days, examining the program's weakness and identifying strategies for improving it.</p><p>"We know we're going to encounter some encampments where there's resistance. I mean, I don't think anybody's been naive about that," she said. "But then we're gonna have to figure out  what do you do when people are resistant."</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/79/fc/1cc3950944049e4b6b5490609ad4/1301751-me-0526-bass-budget-signing-cmh-04.jpg"></figure><p>Bass is not the first politician to try to get their arms around the encampments near El Pueblo. Then-Mayor Eric</p> <p>Garcetti <a href="https://www.latimes.com/local/lanow/la-me-ln-bridge-home-homeless-20180905-story.html">opened the city's first A Bridge Home shelter</a> in 2018</p> <p>on the neighborhood's eastern edge, not far from Union Station. But that facility was not enough to meet the need.</p><p>After the outbreak of COVID-19, the number of people living near El Pueblo grew dramatically, occupying at least six streets in the area. As pandemic restrictions were scaled back, Councilmember Kevin de Len, who represents much of downtown, took a two-pronged approach to the area.</p><p>De Len's office, working with outreach teams, offered the area's unhoused residents beds inside two Bridge Home shelters, the L.A. Grand and Hilda L. Solis Care First Village, an interim housing facility. In December 2021, his office reported that 84 households there had moved indoors.</p><p>At the same time, De Len designated some stretches of sidewalk near El Pueblo as "41.18 zones," named for the section of the Municipal Code that prohibits camping in locations chosen by the City Council. Homeless advocates <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-01-17/kevin-de-leon-homelessness-activists-el-pueblo-encampment">assailed</a> the new 41.18 zones, saying they criminalized poverty. Some branded the L.A. Grand and Solis Village, which require their inhabitants to follow certain rules, as "carceral," or prison-like.</p><p>Over the following year, the streets around El Pueblo slowly repopulated. Some of the holdouts moved their tents to locations just outside the 41.18 zones.</p><p>Among them was Philip, who frequently relies on a manual wheelchair and is now living on Cesar Chavez Avenue. </p><p>Philip, who is in his 70s and declined to give his last name, told The Times last year that he considered the L.A. Grand to be a "concentration camp." He said </p> he<p> would rather be arrested than be forced into that facility, which had a curfew and regular room searches.</p><p>A year and a half later, the Inside Safe team has not changed his mind. Even though the L.A. Grand no longer has a curfew, Philip said he still has no interest in going there.</p><p>"Once they get in there, there are certain orders they give  you can't do this, you can't do that," he said last week. "That's not democracy. That's a concentration camp."</p><p>That type of hostility is at odds with the message the mayor has delivered since launching Inside Safe. During her State of the City address, Bass said the program had "finally dispelled the myth that people do not want to come inside."</p><p>Bass, during her interview last week, said she always expected there would be some unhoused residents who refuse to move indoors. And she acknowledged the rules at the L.A. Grand are "very strict." </p><p>The mayor said her team will be looking at the rules at Inside Safe's hotels and motels, developing "consistent standards" for each location.</p><p>"When we encounter people who are resistant, we're going to have to use different strategies, different services," she said. "And </p>and<p> we are trying to build those services out now."</p><p>De Len, who took office in 2020, said some of the challenges at El Pueblo can be attributed to its location. Unhoused people have settled in the area, he said, after being released from nearby jail facilities or arriving from the buses and trains that converge at Union Station.</p><p>De Len also thinks the area has not received enough drug addiction and mental health services, which are the responsibility of Los Angeles County.</p><p>"We can house the homeless and clean up the area incessantly, but if L.A. County does not step up and provide the mental health and addiction services that are so urgently needed, it will be a never-ending story," he said.</p><p>Cheri Todoroff, the county's homeless initiative executive director, pushed back on that assertion, saying the county has been working closely with the city at El Pueblo, sending mental health clinicians, substance use disorder counselors and healthcare professionals.</p><p>"To this day, they are continuing to engage clients at the site, she said.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/d0/f2/7216de8c4bf2b75e98bfa78723ad/1300842-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance-4-ajs.jpg"></figure><p>El Pueblo is not the only location where the mayor's program has seen slower progress than at its earlier operations.</p><p>In late April, the mayor's team took Inside Safe to a section of South Los Angeles that hugs the 110 Freeway, targeting encampments from 42nd Street south to Vernon Avenue.</p><p>Bass' team has estimated that about 50 people went indoors during that operation. On </p> Monday,Friday,<p> those streets still had 15 tents or tent-like structures, many near an elementary school</p> Vernon Avenue Elementary School<p>.</p><p>Inside Safe went to another South L.A. location last week, focusing on streets along the 110 between 47th and 51st. During that operation, DASH buses whisked more than 50 homeless people to motels.</p><p>Still, not everyone got on the bus.</p><p>Willie Gutierrez, who has a tent on 51st, was initially interested, chatting up the outreach workers who set up folding chairs on a nearby overpass. But when it came time to move, he hadn't found a home for his ladder and his buckets of paint.</p><p>"If I'm not ready, I'm not ready," the 53-year-old said.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/01/4c/9fa1bc634db581a7a64a98ea99e0/1300842-me-mayor-bass-homeless-encampment-resistance-1-ajs.jpg"></figure><p>Days later, Gutierrez told The Times he had dealt with his supplies and was pursuing a new plan: moving to San Bernardino County to live with his sister. Meanwhile, one of his unhoused neighbors now sounds like something of a booster for Inside Safe.</p><p>Beyanira Lopez, 58, said she recently moved into a "beautiful" motel room on Central Avenue. Lopez, who rode back to 51st Street on her bicycle, said she has been trying to persuade two of the holdouts to come indoors as well.</p><p>"I get to shower every day. I get to cook inside with my little stove. I get to sleep when I want," she said. "I'm very happy."</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>After 40 years, Boyle Heights priest still irks politicians and fights for his flock</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-28/boyle-heights-priest-irks-politicians-fights-for-flock</link>
      <description>From a proposed prison near Boyle Heights to lead contamination from an Exide battery plant, Monsignor John Moretta has fought against threats to his mostly Latino, low-income parishioners.</description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2023 12:00:04 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Andrew J. Campa</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-28/boyle-heights-priest-irks-politicians-fights-for-flock</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-28/boyle-heights-priest-irks-politicians-fights-for-flock">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d9298a8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5472x3648+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F1d%2F774bf0304fa4a41d8e0f10697fa9%2F1253592-me-moretta-eastside-pillar-1-gmf.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4be152f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5472x3648+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F1d%2F774bf0304fa4a41d8e0f10697fa9%2F1253592-me-moretta-eastside-pillar-1-gmf.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1fb1980/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5472x3648+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F1d%2F774bf0304fa4a41d8e0f10697fa9%2F1253592-me-moretta-eastside-pillar-1-gmf.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/367ef43/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5472x3648+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F1d%2F774bf0304fa4a41d8e0f10697fa9%2F1253592-me-moretta-eastside-pillar-1-gmf.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e6250eb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5472x3648+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F1d%2F774bf0304fa4a41d8e0f10697fa9%2F1253592-me-moretta-eastside-pillar-1-gmf.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="LOS ANGELES, CA - FEBRUARY 10, 2023: Monsignor John Moretta, pastor of Resurrection Church in Boyle Heights will be completing his 40th year at Resurrection this spring and 55 year overall as a Roman Catholic priest on February 10, 2023 in Los Angeles, California. Moretta has played a vital and historic role in many of the challenges facing residents of Boyle Heights dating back to the mid-80s. (Gina Ferazzi / Los Angeles Times)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b7581a3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5472x3648+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F1d%2F774bf0304fa4a41d8e0f10697fa9%2F1253592-me-moretta-eastside-pillar-1-gmf.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0b5a0d9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5472x3648+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F1d%2F774bf0304fa4a41d8e0f10697fa9%2F1253592-me-moretta-eastside-pillar-1-gmf.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c8def0f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5472x3648+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F1d%2F774bf0304fa4a41d8e0f10697fa9%2F1253592-me-moretta-eastside-pillar-1-gmf.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f47addd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5472x3648+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F1d%2F774bf0304fa4a41d8e0f10697fa9%2F1253592-me-moretta-eastside-pillar-1-gmf.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/192029c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5472x3648+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F1d%2F774bf0304fa4a41d8e0f10697fa9%2F1253592-me-moretta-eastside-pillar-1-gmf.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/192029c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5472x3648+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fcd%2F1d%2F774bf0304fa4a41d8e0f10697fa9%2F1253592-me-moretta-eastside-pillar-1-gmf.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">LOS ANGELES, CA - FEBRUARY 10, 2023: Monsignor John Moretta, pastor of Resurrection Church in Boyle Heights will be completing his 40th year at Resurrection this spring and 55 year overall as a Roman Catholic priest on February 10, 2023 in Los Angeles, California. Moretta has played a vital and historic role in many of the challenges facing residents of Boyle Heights dating back to the mid-80s. (Gina Ferazzi / Los Angeles Times)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Gina Ferazzi/Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>After 40 years, Boyle Heights priest still irks politicians and fights for his flock</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">L.A. Politics </h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/andrew-j-campa">        Andrew J. Campa    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="May 28, 2023">May 28, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    Monsignor Msgr.<p> John Moretta began the meeting with a prayer of thanks that the community would be able to express its opinions.</p><p>He then segued into a message that was not so kumbaya, warning that Boyle Heights was famous for its social justice movements and would not stand for any </p>cochinadas, <p>or garbage.</p><p>At Resurrection Catholic Church that evening last June, the temperature of the overflow crowd quickly rose, with <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-07-18/thousands-homeless-sears-boyle-heights-opposition">many speakers bashing a plan</a> from the owner of the old Sears building to <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-02-19/life-rebuilding-center-boyle-heights-sears-building">house thousands of homeless people</a>.</p><p>Chants of </p>Fuera!&nbsp; <p>Get out!</p>  <p>rang through the auditorium.</p><p>After three hours of relentless anger from the crowd, project manager Bill Taormina declared the plan dead and agreed to consider community input in future proposals.</p><p>But fallout from the rancorous meeting soon followed, with much of it landing squarely on Moretta, the host.</p><p>The archdiocese received a complaint alleging that the priest had fomented a lynch mob mentality.</p><p>Los Angeles City Councilmember Kevin de Len, who was singled out by many speakers even though he was not at the meeting, called the hostility disgraceful. A De Len staffer who fielded much of the ire said he was disappointed at not receiving a personal apology from Moretta.</p><p>Moretta eventually did apologize, saying he had allowed the meeting to get out of hand.</p><p>In four decades as Resurrections pastor, Moretta has been a respected leader on high-stakes community issues, which has sometimes made him a lightning rod for criticism, including from elected officials.</p><p>From a proposed prison near Boyle Heights to lead contamination from an Exide battery plant, the Italian American native of South L.A., who jumpstarted his fluent Spanish in a Mexican town in the 1960s, has fought against threats to his mostly Latino, low-income parishioners, all while marking the milestones of their lives at baptisms, quinceaeras, weddings and funerals.</p><p>I know some priests want to be neutral, but I cant, said Moretta, 81, whose old-fashioned diction evokes Warner Bros. films of the 1940s. If people need help, Im going to help. Thats the way Ive always seen it.</p><p>Six feet one and heavyset, with a slight stoop and closely cropped white hair, Moretta favors black button-down shirts or white guayaberas when not in his priestly cassock. </p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/94/e8/3ab7a47c4cc482ba82b2b079bca0/1253592-me-moretta-eastside-pillar-4-gmf.jpg"></figure><p>He grew up attending Catholic schools, graduating from St. Pius X High School in Downey. There wasn't a single moment </p>where in which<p> he suddenly found his calling, like in the movies, he said. Rather, his decision to become a priest was gradual and fostered by the love shown to him by the priests and nuns" at school.</p><p>After seminary school in Camarillo, he worked as a young priest in Southern California, including at St. Boniface in Anaheim, St. Augustine in Culver City and St. Hilary in Pico Rivera, before landing in Boyle Heights in 1983.</p><p>As Moretta settled into his new parish, community activists were ramping up their efforts against a proposed <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1989-12-08-me-116-story.html">1,450-inmate prison</a> across the L.A. River from the neighborhood. </p><p>In the summer of 1986, Moretta and landscape architect Frank Villalobos invited dozens of Neighborhood Watch leaders  mostly women  to Resurrection to organize an anti-prison march, along with a group of 47 civic organizations called the Coalition Against the Prison in East Los Angeles. </p><p>Moretta christened the female leaders<a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1989-08-13-me-816-story.html"> the Mothers of East Los Angeles, or MELA</a></p>, <p>and became their media spokesperson, joining them on weekly protest marches.</p><p>With Villalobos and business owner Steve Kasten, Moretta donated tens of thousands of dollars for the women to travel to Sacramento and lobby lawmakers.</p><p>He very much loved his people and would do anything, said Teresa Marquez, now 75, president of the Mothers </p>for of<p> East Los Angeles and a founding member. He stood up for us when so many others didnt."</p><p>As a leader of the movement, Moretta found himself at odds with a powerful politician.</p><p>Soon after being elected to represent the area, Assemblymember Richard Polanco had cast a key committee vote that revived the prison project, prompting some to label him a "sellout."</p> <p>Moretta and the activists stalled the project for years with lawsuits and calls for environmental impact reports. They eventually won converts in the state Legislature, including Polanco. Some couldn't forgive Polanco, but Moretta urged unity against a common foe.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/26/f6/c3ed3e054d1a98d511fe50d5a794/la-photos-1staff-627346-la-me-exide-settlement-5-als.jpg"></figure><p>In September 1992, the mothers group and other activists gathered at Resurrection to celebrate Gov. Pete Wilson's decision to scrap the prison. "We won the war!" they shouted.</p><p>Also at the church were some of the politicians who had ultimately responded to the activists' persistence. Polanco, who helped negotiate the measure that Wilson signed, was there.</p><p>Father has always been a very courageous leader and a pillar in the Boyle Heights community, Polanco said recently. Hes a minister who not only talks about his faith but also about social justice and environmental issues. Hes a throwback to the civil rights movement.</p> "<p>Moretta and the mothers group have also been at the forefront of successful campaigns to stop the construction of an oil pipeline through Boyle Heights and a hazardous trash incinerator in Vernon. In 2017, <a href="https://abc7.com/south-coast-air-quality-management-district-rancid-smell-vernon-boyle-heights-maywood/2611048/" target="_blank">Moretta brought Resurrection Catholic School students</a> to speak about the rancid smells emanating from nearby meat rendering plants before the South Coast Air Quality Management District voted unanimously to take steps to address the problem.</p><p>"Everybody talks about environmental justice, and it's real trendy now," Villalobos said. "Father was leading the push back in the '80s, when nobody was talking about the concept. </p><p>But Moretta has not been able to declare victory against the lead contamination spread by a now-shuttered Exide battery plant.</p><p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-02-10/exide-lead-cleanup-leaves-fear-and-frustration-in-its-wake">A recent Times investigation</a> noted that many Eastside homes and gardens are still polluted despite a massive effort to detoxify the area.</p><p>Moretta has spent countless hours knocking on doors to educate residents about the lead and its potential effects on their health.</p><p>He has begged those living in contamination zones to avoid being outside too long, to remove their shoes before entering the house and to follow other</p> <p><a href="http://www.publichealth.lacounty.gov/eh/exide/" target="_blank">public health guidelines such as keeping children from touching dirt and washing their toys often.</a></p><p>"I remember stopping by a house a few years ago where there was a mother and a daughter making tamales in their backyard and completely unaware anything was wrong or dangerous," he said. "It would have been bucolic if it wasn't so devastating."</p><p>Moretta's hero is Pope John XXIII, perhaps best known for helping incorporate the local vernacular, instead of Latin, into </p>masses Masses<p> in 1964.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/26/87/618da8654472b22cf70a4c92bfe2/1253592-me-moretta-eastside-pillar-5-gmf.jpg"></figure><p>Moretta, whose Spanish is modestly accented but understandable, started Spanish-language services at his two previous parishes, St. Augustine and St. Hilary.</p><p>Even though hes not Latino, we feel like hes one of us, said Resurrection parishioner Ana Maria De Anda, 70, who credited Morettas church fundraisers and activities for keeping her eight children busy and away from gangs and drugs.</p><p>Rick Caruso, the billionaire developer who recently ran unsuccessfully for L.A. mayor, recalls a time in the early 1990s when homicides and gang violence were at all-time highs. </p><p>Caruso was then a member of the Los Angeles Board of Police Commissioners, and Moretta pleaded for<a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1991-03-24-op-1228-story.html"> more patrols</a> and other help.</p><p>"I didn't know who Father John was, and he reached me out of the blue with a no-nonsense call," said Caruso, who occasionally attends </p>mass Mass<p> at Resurrection. "He said, 'Rick, we've got kids dying in the streets,' and within a matter of days, we made changes."</p><p>His work steering kids in a positive direction has continued through the years. In the mid-2000s, <a href="https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/CRECB-2008-pt11/html/CRECB-2008-pt11-Pg15131.htm" target="_blank">Moretta secured funding</a> for a federal gang reduction program, known as <a href="https://bja.ojp.gov/funding/awards/2008-dd-bx-0239" target="_blank">project CLEAR</a></p>,<p> <a href="https://bja.ojp.gov/funding/awards/2008-dd-bx-0239" target="_blank">Community Law Enforcement and Recovery, or CLEAR,</a> </p>that which<p> provided for more officers on the streets as well as counseling, tutors and job placement for local youths.</p><p>Most Monday evenings, as he has for decades, Moretta hosts a community watch forum at Resurrection.</p><p>At one forum in early March, he gleefully scarfed down two jelly </p>donuts doughnuts<p> from the boxes he had brought.</p><p>Dressed all in black  a puffy rain jacket, slacks and tennis shoes  Moretta listened as Villalobos, his longtime ally, spoke about Exide.</p><p>You dont hear politicians talking about it anymore, and, maybe most troubling, our youth arent interested, Villalobos said. The whole discussion about social justice has shifted to affordable housing and homelessness, and Exide has been let off the hook.</p><p>Marquez of Mothers of East Los Angeles said her work has gotten more difficult since Exide <a href="https://www.latimes.com/environment/story/2020-10-12/exide-battery-recycler-bankruptcy-vernon-cleanup">declared bankruptcy in 2020</a>.</p><p>Weve questioned their contractors in charge of cleanup, but Exide keeps changing them, and its difficult to know who to contact, Marquez said. Its frustrating, but the work continues.</p><p>Moretta is focused on testing residents for lead poisoning and studying long-term consequences, such as cancer and <a href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/lead-poisoning-and-health#:~:text=Lead%20exposure%20can%20have%20serious,intellectual%20disability%20and%20behavioural%20disorders.">long-term learning disabilities</a>.</p><p>Moretta told the dozen or so people at the meeting that blood testing can only detect lead for 36 days after it <a href="https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/csem/leadtoxicity/biologic_fate.html#:~:text=The%20half%2Dlife%20of%20lead%20in%20adult%20human%20blood%20has,36%20days%20%5BRabinowitz%20et%20al.">has entered the body</a>. He has been advocating for non-invasive bone testing that can detect trace amounts introduced years or even decades ago. </p><p>Seven years ago, as he neared the mandatory retirement age of 75, Moretta asked the Archdiocese of Los Angeles to let him continue indefinitely. He said he views his job as "an assignment for life" and wants to keep going as long as he can "still move and still serve."</p><p>"It's easy to recognize that we have so many things working against us as a community," Moretta said. "What matters, though, is how we proceed and how we lift the burdens of others."</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>L.A. asked Congress for millions to address homelessness. But getting the cash isn’t certain</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-05/earmarks-california-senate-candidates-karen-bass-los-angeles-homeless</link>
      <description>The return of earmarks has also rekindled a debate among the three California Democrats vying for a seat in the U.S. Senate. It's a rare area of policy disagreement.</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2023 12:00:46 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-05/earmarks-california-senate-candidates-karen-bass-los-angeles-homeless</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wells Fargo denied well-off borrowers low-interest loans. Is it because they're Black?</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-25/wells-fargo-denied-well-off-borrowers-loans-is-it-because-they-are-black</link>
      <description>A group of Black customers is suing Wells Fargo, claiming the bank slow-rolled or denied them loans based on race.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 12:00:06 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Anita Chabria</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-25/wells-fargo-denied-well-off-borrowers-loans-is-it-because-they-are-black</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-25/wells-fargo-denied-well-off-borrowers-loans-is-it-because-they-are-black">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6657cc1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4650x2664+0+0/resize/320x183!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F58%2Faa%2F5855f78c49f8882f3f664a1048bc%2Fap120117123436.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b527e8e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4650x2664+0+0/resize/568x325!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F58%2Faa%2F5855f78c49f8882f3f664a1048bc%2Fap120117123436.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1d35064/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4650x2664+0+0/resize/768x440!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F58%2Faa%2F5855f78c49f8882f3f664a1048bc%2Fap120117123436.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a034060/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4650x2664+0+0/resize/1024x586!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F58%2Faa%2F5855f78c49f8882f3f664a1048bc%2Fap120117123436.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a072fc7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4650x2664+0+0/resize/1200x687!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F58%2Faa%2F5855f78c49f8882f3f664a1048bc%2Fap120117123436.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="A customer uses an ATM outside a Wells Fargo branch in Charlotte, N.C. in 2012."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/86547ab/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4650x2664+0+0/resize/320x183!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F58%2Faa%2F5855f78c49f8882f3f664a1048bc%2Fap120117123436.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/45e7eea/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4650x2664+0+0/resize/568x325!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F58%2Faa%2F5855f78c49f8882f3f664a1048bc%2Fap120117123436.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9a6a6c8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4650x2664+0+0/resize/768x440!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F58%2Faa%2F5855f78c49f8882f3f664a1048bc%2Fap120117123436.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9eef4b2/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4650x2664+0+0/resize/1024x586!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F58%2Faa%2F5855f78c49f8882f3f664a1048bc%2Fap120117123436.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/55b6fb7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4650x2664+0+0/resize/1200x687!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F58%2Faa%2F5855f78c49f8882f3f664a1048bc%2Fap120117123436.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="687"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/55b6fb7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4650x2664+0+0/resize/1200x687!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F58%2Faa%2F5855f78c49f8882f3f664a1048bc%2Fap120117123436.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">A customer uses an ATM outside a Wells Fargo branch in Charlotte, N.C., Tuesday, Jan. 17, 2012. Wells Fargo &amp; Co. said Tuesday, Jan. 17, 2012, its fourth-quarter profit rose 20 percent, helped by better performance of its loans, growth in deposits and a steadying mortgage business. (AP Photo/Chuck Burton)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Chuck Burton/AP)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Wells Fargo denied well-off borrowers low-interest loans. Is it because they&#x27;re Black?</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/anita-chabria">        Anita Chabria    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="May 25, 2023">May 25, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Gia Gray seems like a dream client for any bank: a well-off family doctor living in an exclusive Bay Area town, in a 5,000-square-foot mansion with a master bath bigger than my office. </p><p>With a credit score topping 800, she expected little drama when she and her husband decided to refinance their Danville home and two other investment properties in 2020 to capture some of the lowest interest rates in recent history  remember when 3% loans were a thing? </p><p>But after endless excuses and delays in her applications, "I started feeling Black," </p>she  Gray <p>told me. Her bank, Wells Fargo, </p>she said,<p> flat </p>-<p>out turned her down on the investment properties, </p> she said, <p>and slow-rolled the application on her residence, coming up with new requirements as the process dragged on. </p><p>"At the visceral level, I felt that something was not right," she said. </p><p>Across the country, other borrowers have had similar experiences. Earlier this year, a federal court in Northern California, where Wells Fargo is headquartered, consolidated the claims of Gray and seven other Black plaintiffs into one case that may be certified as a class-action suit in coming months. </p><p>The lead attorney in the case, Los Angeles-based Dennis S. Ellis, says up to 750,000 minority customers nationwide  Black, Asian and Latino  could have been affected by what he sees as a pattern of discriminatory lending that left qualified borrowers denied or pushed into higher interest rates and more expensive loans. </p><p>It's a form of modern-day economic redlining, he told me, that if proven true inflicted pain that resonated beyond the borrowers, many of whom lost out on a chance to save hundreds or thousands off their loans each month</p> . <p>It also hurt Black and minority communities as a whole, because it took away an exceptional chance to build generational wealth through affordable home</p> <p>ownership. </p><p>"Realizing the American dream of owning your own home is not just about having a safe place to live," Ellis pointed out. "It's about securing the future of generations that follow because of the incredible financial stability that home</p> <p>ownership provides."</p><p>Ellis contends that the problem developed in part because Wells Fargo was short-staffed during the pandemic and relied on flawed algorithms and an automated system that may have had discrimination baked into it. </p><p>But it wouldn't be the first time Wells Fargo was found to have discriminated. In 2012, the U.S. Department of Justice won a $175</p> -<p>million settlement against the bank, the second-largest fair</p> -<p>lending settlement in the </p> department's DOJ's<p> history, over allegations that Wells Fargo engaged in a pattern or practice of "discrimination against qualified African-American and Hispanic borrowers in its mortgage lending from 2004 through 2009." </p><p>The cities of Oakland and Philadelphia have also sued Wells Fargo for discriminatory lending practices; Philly settled its case for <a href="https://whyy.org/articles/wells-fargo-will-pay-philadelphia-10m-to-settle-citys-discriminatory-lending-lawsuit/" target="_blank">$10 million</a> in 2019. </p><p>Wells Fargo has been accused of holding <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/05/19/business/wells-fargo-fake-interviews.html" target="_blank">fake job interviews</a> with minority candidates for posts that had already been promised to other applicants, <a href="https://news.bloomberglaw.com/banking-law/wells-fargo-must-face-black-homeowners-bias-suit-over-appraisal" target="_blank">low-balling home appraisals</a> and <a href="https://news.bloomberglaw.com/esg/wells-fargo-ignored-diversity-problems-shareholders-say-in-suit" target="_blank">ignoring issues</a> of discrimination that, as they come to light, may be harming the bank's bottom line. </p><p>Wells Fargo has denied all of the allegations, including those made</p> <p>in this lawsuit. In a statement, the company said it was confident it was following all required guidelines and that its underwriting practices are consistently applied regardless of a customers race or ethnicity. </p><p>"These allegations against Wells Fargo stand in stark contrast to the companys significant and long-term commitment to closing the minority home ownership gap," the statement read. </p><p>It's not just owning a home, though. It's owning it on good terms. </p><p>Google tells me that a $500,000 30-year loan at 3% interest costs about $900 less a month than a loan at 6% interest</p> <p> about $324,000 over its lifetime. For the folks who weren't able to refinance, that's money lining corporate pockets instead of paying for college or retirement or funding other investments. </p><p>The lawsuit alleges that in 2020, "at a time when millions of white Americans were able to take advantage of historically low-interest rates for home loans,</p> "<p> Wells Fargo approved 47% of refinancing applications from Black homeowners, 53% from Hispanic and/or Latino homeowners, and 67% from Asian</p>-<p> American applicants. That compares with 71%, 79%</p>,<p> and 85%, respectively, for these same </p>ethnic<p> groups across all other lenders, according to the lawsuit.</p><p>That same year, Wells Fargo approved 71% of residential refinancing applications from white borrowers.</p><p>Ouch, Wells Fargo. Those are some dismal numbers. </p><p>The lawsuit also alleges that federal data show</p>s<p> Wells Fargo was more likely to approve refinancing applications from low-earning white borrowers than high-earning Black borrowers. Analyzing</p> <p>data from </p>eight  8<p> million refinancing applications filed in 2020, Ellis and his team found white applicants earning less than $63,000 a year were "more likely to have their refinancing application approved by Wells Fargo than Black refinancing applicants earning between $120,000 and $168,000 a year," according to the lawsuit. </p><p>The insidiousness of financial discrimination lies in</p> <p>how hard it is to prove on an individual basis  and in</p> <p>how hard it is to even believe it's happening. The loan process can be so remote and impersonal  even more so during the isolation of</p> <p>the pandemic  that Gray and her co-plaintiffs were at first unsure</p> <p>if what they felt was really taking place. </p><p>Last week, Gray met two of those other borrowers in person at a news conference in San Francisco. I spoke with the three of them in a coffee shop afterward</p>s<p>, but mostly I just listened, because there was a tremendous sense of relief and camaraderie as they shared how similar their experiences had been. </p><p>Until the lawsuit, Aaron Braxton, a Los Angeles homeowner, had been left wondering, "Are they doing this to everybody, or are they only doing this to Black folks?" he said. </p><p>Braxton was one of the first to file a complaint in 2020. <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/blogs/culture-monster-blog/story/2012-01-18/teacher-actor-aaron-braxton-takes-his-classroom-to-the-stage">A noted screenwriter, playwright and teacher</a>, Braxton had owned his home in a historically Black neighborhood near USC for about 18 years and owed a fraction of what it was worth when he went to refinance his Wells Fargo mortgage. Like Gray, it was one thing after another, despite never missing a payment and having good credit. By the time Wells Fargo approved his loan, the interest rate had climbed and so had his frustration. </p><p>"I told them, 'I am going to sue you. I don't know how I'm going to sue you, but I am going to sue you, because I know I am not the only one,'" he said. </p><p>Gray was scrolling through her phone during the pandemic lockdown and came across a story about Braxton. "It was like a bright bulb," she recalled, "and I said, 'Oh</p> ,<p> my God, this happened to someone else.'"</p><p>Christopher Williams flew in from Georgia, where he owns a home and rental properties. He worked in the financial industry for decades, so when Wells Fargo offered him a loan at 3 points higher than he expected, he asked why. Williams said the bank couldn't give him clear answers, and he</p>,<p> too</p>,<p> began to suspect it was about the color of his skin. </p><p>Now, Williams said he wonders how many people there are who accepted loans at higher rates or with higher costs without knowing it. "How many of those loans and lines of credit are on the books of Wells Fargo right now</p>,<p>?" he asked. </p><p>Ellis will be in federal court in San Francisco for the lawsuit on Thursday, the anniversary of the death of George Floyd. He says like the movement Floyd's death set off to address issues of social justice, he hopes this case can raise awareness of financial injustice and its toll  which he considers the "21st</p>-<p> century battleground of civil rights." </p><p>Just as weve cried out against policing practices that kill Black lives, so we denounce Wells Fargos racially motivated banking practices that kill Black opportunity," said civil rights attorney Ben Crump, who is also involved in the case. </p><p>Interest rates are not as compelling as the tragedy we witnessed with Floyd, but Crump and Ellis make an important point. </p><p>This is a capitalist joint. </p><p>Until we all have the same opportunities to create wealth, we're left with the oppressed and the oppressors, who too often get away with strangling equity under the cover of paperwork and algorithms. </p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Killed for shoplifting snacks and a Sprite: San Francisco, Walgreens and an ugly legacy</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-24/security-guard-shot-black-man-for-shoplifting-exposing-san-francisco-intolerance-of-poverty</link>
      <description>A security guard in San Francisco shot Banko Brown, a transgender Black man, exposing how the city's Black community suffers under the pressures of poverty and racism.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2023 12:00:10 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Anita Chabria</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-24/security-guard-shot-black-man-for-shoplifting-exposing-san-francisco-intolerance-of-poverty</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-24/security-guard-shot-black-man-for-shoplifting-exposing-san-francisco-intolerance-of-poverty">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6f5788b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2488x1659+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F0b%2Fe7%2F2b424cef4d8eb3ae0c4935dfe0c5%2F837890f8b55c4c0db851a31fae802907-crop.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b05c6db/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2488x1659+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F0b%2Fe7%2F2b424cef4d8eb3ae0c4935dfe0c5%2F837890f8b55c4c0db851a31fae802907-crop.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7ffc263/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2488x1659+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F0b%2Fe7%2F2b424cef4d8eb3ae0c4935dfe0c5%2F837890f8b55c4c0db851a31fae802907-crop.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9f59bb8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2488x1659+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F0b%2Fe7%2F2b424cef4d8eb3ae0c4935dfe0c5%2F837890f8b55c4c0db851a31fae802907-crop.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1bced93/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2488x1659+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F0b%2Fe7%2F2b424cef4d8eb3ae0c4935dfe0c5%2F837890f8b55c4c0db851a31fae802907-crop.JPG 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Asia Hubbard, ex-girlfriend of Banko Brown, speaks outside City Hall, Monday, May 15, 2023, after a march from the Market Street Walgreens in San Francisco, following District Attorney Brooke Jenkins&#x27; decision not to prosecute security guard, Michael Earl-Wayne Anthony, for confronting and killing Brown, who was suspected of shoplifting inside the store. (Scott Strazzante/San Francisco Chronicle via AP)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3c53d95/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2488x1659+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F0b%2Fe7%2F2b424cef4d8eb3ae0c4935dfe0c5%2F837890f8b55c4c0db851a31fae802907-crop.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/062092f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2488x1659+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F0b%2Fe7%2F2b424cef4d8eb3ae0c4935dfe0c5%2F837890f8b55c4c0db851a31fae802907-crop.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/358914b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2488x1659+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F0b%2Fe7%2F2b424cef4d8eb3ae0c4935dfe0c5%2F837890f8b55c4c0db851a31fae802907-crop.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a8db714/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2488x1659+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F0b%2Fe7%2F2b424cef4d8eb3ae0c4935dfe0c5%2F837890f8b55c4c0db851a31fae802907-crop.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6f151f0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2488x1659+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F0b%2Fe7%2F2b424cef4d8eb3ae0c4935dfe0c5%2F837890f8b55c4c0db851a31fae802907-crop.JPG 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6f151f0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2488x1659+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F0b%2Fe7%2F2b424cef4d8eb3ae0c4935dfe0c5%2F837890f8b55c4c0db851a31fae802907-crop.JPG"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">Asia Hubbard, ex-girlfriend of Banko Brown, speaks outside City Hall, Monday, May 15, 2023, after a march from the Market Street Walgreens in San Francisco, following District Attorney Brooke Jenkins decision not to prosecute security guard, Michael Earl-Wayne Anthony, for confronting and killing Brown, who was suspected of shoplifting inside the store. (Scott Strazzante/San Francisco Chronicle via AP)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Scott Strazzante/AP)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Killed for shoplifting snacks and a Sprite: San Francisco, Walgreens and an ugly legacy</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">California Politics </h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/anita-chabria">        Anita Chabria    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="May 24, 2023">May 24, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Last month, a Black man raised in chaos and scarcity shot and killed a Black man living in chaos and scarcity on the sidewalk in front of a downtown Walgreens. </p><p>It was a dispute over the alleged shoplifting of $14 worth of snacks and a Sprite.</p><p>Since then, the killing of<a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-16/san-francisco-video-walgreens-shooting-alleged-shoplifter"> Banko Brown,</a> 24, by security guard </p> Michael Earl-Wayne Anthony<p>, 33, has incited</p> <p>protests, blame and frustration in this troubled city, where chaos and scarcity are as common as the political divisions they breed. </p> On <p>Thursday, one of San Francisco's great civil rights leaders, <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/lift-every-voice/article/Amos-Brown-16219697.php" target="_blank">the Rev. Amos Brown</a> (no relation to Banko Brown), will preside over the funeral, expected to draw hundreds, at the church where </p> the slain man<p> once attended Sunday school. </p><p>For the </p> pastor<p>, the answer to why Banko Brown is dead  the bigger context  is obvious: racism. For all of San Francisco's liberal legacy, for all of the political success of leaders including Willie Brown and Mayor London Breed, he told me, it has long been one of the hardest places in California for Black people to thrive  a reality </p> that<p> <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/16/us/san-francisco-reparations.html" target="_blank">the city has confronted</a> in recent years, but </p> that <p>persists. A reality that left Banko Brown and Anthony struggling in a city that has never been fair.</p><p>"It's been so subtle, so hidden, so sneaky," </p> pastor Brown<p> said. "But Black folks are on an island of poverty."</p><p>That ugly truth has been lost in the politics of the moment. Banko Brown's killing has become another fraught crisis in a city that is in political upheaval over homelessness, mental illness and drug use  as is much of California and the nation. </p><p>Some folks are angry that Anthony is not being criminally charged, Brown's life seemingly written off as unworthy of justice. Others, already irate over conditions in the nearby</p> <p>Tenderloin, are using the death to push for the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-04-23/column-for-25-years-this-transgender-club-has-celebrated-the-soul-of-san-francisco">kind of policies</a> that would have further marginalized Brown, a transgender Black man living an unstable existence: more policing, more incarceration and potentially even forced treatment for addictions. But there is little acknowledgment of the role race and history played in bringing Anthony and Brown together. </p><p><a href="https://sf.gov/sites/default/files/2022-04/Reallocation-of-SFPD-Funding-Report-09-2020.pdf" target="_blank">Thirty-seven percent </a>of San Francisco's homeless population is Black, despite Black people making up only 6% of the city as a whole. Black households had an average income of $31,000 compared </p> with<p> $116,000 for white families in 2019. Los Angeles, with its many disparities, has a <a href="https://storymaps.arcgis.com/collections/cc7914ce627845448d235549b353f411?item=4" target="_blank">median Black household income </a>of $51,000, about $40,000 less than white households. </p><p>Nowhere are San Francisco's divisions more apparent than in the area where Brown and Anthony met: a stretch of Market Street popular with tourists shopping at places such as the Levi's store one door over from Walgreens, or catching the cable car at its nearby turnaround. </p><p>But it's an area also filled with homeless people  some clearly suffering from mental health issues, drug use or both. It's not far from United Nations Plaza, a hub of drug dealing and homelessness, where right-wing media (including now, <a href="https://www.cnn.com/videos/us/2023/05/12/san-francisco-sara-sidner-pkg-actws-vpx.cnn" target="_blank">apparently, CNN)</a> loves to film their doom-loop narratives about a "failed city" of progressive policies. Shoplifting  both by organized retail gangs and amateurs  is common. </p><p>"That whole area down there is a place where people have been forced to congregate because they have no other place," said </p> pastor <p>Brown. </p><p>In those volatile surroundings, Anthony was expected to provide security for shoppers and staff inside the drugstore, while maybe also preventing robberies, though what that means was unclear even to him. His instructions from supervisors, according to what he told police, flip-flopped from taking a hands-off approach to physically stopping thieves from leaving with goods. </p><p>"They kept changing it back and forth," he told an officer after the shooting, calling Walgreens' policies "confusing." </p><p>He wasn't particularly well-trained in either approach, left largely to his own devices to figure out how to do his job well enough to keep it. "Damned if we do, damned if we don't," he said. </p><p>Like Banko Brown, Anthony came from a hard life. In an interview recorded on body camera video after the shooting, he told an officer he had been </p> on his own since he was young.<p> His parents, he said, rarely worked. His stepfather belittled him for having a job. Still, Anthony became a security guard at 18 and an armed guard at 19. </p><p>"It's the first job I had that paid a decent amount," he said. </p><p>But it wasn't easy. He dislocated his shoulder in a "tussle" at another job location, and has been worried about the joint popping out again. His life has been falling apart in recent months. He separated from his wife after a year of marriage. He got stuck with bills  his ex took even his piggy bank, he </p> said<p>. His car was stolen, with some of his security gear inside. His brother was shot seven times, but survived. His guns, which he was required to have for work, were confiscated by police though he hadn't broken any laws  they were returned days before the shooting. He'd been passing off a BB gun as the real thing. </p><p>"My whole </p> ...fg<p> life has been </p>shitty  [lousy]<p>," he told police. </p><p>Brown had his own struggles as a Black transgender man, marginalized in so many ways. Friends said </p> he <p>had lacked stable housing for years and was sleeping on public transit, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2023/may/10/banko-brown-death-san-francisco-walgreens" target="_blank">according to media reports.</a> He had been convicted of second-degree robbery in the past, giving him the stigma and challenges of a criminal record. In recent days, he was distraught at being unable to find help. </p><p>He was also loved, and is missed. </p><p>Banko Brown's father, Terry Brown, described his son as genuine and kind, an activist who helped others. </p><p>"I'm so hurt," he said in a TV interview</p> ,<p> "</p> j<p>ust to even know my baby is gone."</p><p>San Francisco Dist</p> .<p> Atty. Brooke Jenkins has declined to press charges against Anthony based on his claims of self-defense, but released <a href="https://sfdistrictattorney.org/criminal-case-investigation/brown-declination-investigation/" target="_blank">surveillance footage</a> and police investigation </p> findings<p> in an attempt to quell outrage. The video, however, is deeply disturbing and has led to calls for an outside investigation. </p><p>Civil rights attorney John Burris, who expects to file a civil lawsuit Friday on behalf of the family, sent a letter to the state attorney general asking him to review Jenkins' decision. </p> On <p>Tuesday, Attn. Gen. Rob Bonta said he would examine whether Jenkins</p> '<p> failure to file charges was an "abuse of discretion." </p><p>Burris said he is "not particularly empathetic" to Anthony and believes he should have been charged with manslaughter at a minimum, because "at the time he shot [Brown], the officer's life was not in danger." </p><p><a href="https://sfdistrictattorney.org/criminal-case-investigation/brown-declination-investigation/" target="_blank">The video</a> shows Anthony tried to stop Brown from leaving the store with a bag that may have contained stolen items. Brown refused to give it up, and the two fought. Anthony wrestled Brown to the floor. Anthony told police Brown threatened to stab him, though ultimately no weapon was found on Brown. </p><p>After Anthony released </p> him<p>, Brown walked outside, only to turn back and allegedly spit on Anthony. It was in that second, when Brown spun around to face Anthony then backed away, that </p> the guard<p> fired a hollow-point bullet from one of two modified Glocks he carried. </p><p>Beyond the debates about</p> <p>Anthony's criminal culpability, the situation  a guard attempting to stop a shoplifter in a neighborhood overrun with petty crime and homelessness  is fodder for San Francisco's ongoing battle between progressive harm reductionists who believe housing, services and compassion are the solution to the problems plaguing streets, and the don't-call-them-conservatives (they really hate it) conservatives who want an old-school crackdown because things are out of control. </p> On <p>Wednesday, Breed, who grew up in public housing and lost a sister to an overdose, declared </p> that <p>"compassion is killing people</p> ,<p>" and promised to impose order through force if necessary</p> ,<p> while speaking about conditions in the Tenderloin. </p><p>"When you know what it feels like to grow up in chaos, you want nothing more than change," she said at a public meeting in U.N. Plaza, which lasted about 10 minutes before heckling shut it down. "You want nothing more than something better for the kids and the next generation." </p><p>To be fair, things are out of control. </p><p>When I visited that Walgreens on a recent Thursday, a memorial to Brown that </p> had<p> hung on the chain</p> -<p>link fence outside was gone, except for a few shiny ribbons dangling limply. </p><p>Inside, shoplifting was rampant. A man with what looked and smelled like vomit on his sweatshirt barreled past a security guard  from a new subcontractor whose employees do not carry any weapons  and through the checkout line in search of candy bars. He grabbed a few handfuls, stuffing them in his pockets, along with a Mountain Dew. Then he walked out, despite the guard's feeble pleas that he have some self-respect. </p><p>"Oh, Jesus, help me," yelled the woman in front of me, offended by the scent, not the stealing. She was an off-duty security guard who worked at the French </p> Consulate<p>, preferring </p> its<p> lower pay to the pandemonium of retail jobs.</p><p>"The thing is, we're walking on eggshells," another guard at the store, Christoper Rivers, told me later  unknowingly using the exact same phrase Anthony had with police. </p><p>It was at least the third incident in that Walgreens that day, Rivers said  and it was just past lunch. Rivers is also Black, as was nearly every security guard I came across in the neighborhood</p> . He was <p>born and raised in Bayview-Hunters Point, historically a poor neighborhood. He isn't particularly enjoying this posting, but he needs the job, he said. </p><p>"I'm always looking over my shoulder while I work here because you never know who [has] a gun or knife or anything," he said. "Corporate is telling us not to do anything about nothing."</p><p>Like Anthony, he worries about doing too little and is scared to do too much. Which </p> raises begs<p> the question, what is Walgreens' responsibility in all this, putting ill-trained, often minority security guards</p> <p>on the front lines of this crisis that it helped to create? </p><p>A few days ago, Walgreens settled a lawsuit with San Francisco and agreed to pay the city $230 million for its role in the opioid epidemic (though the company claims no wrongdoing). A federal judge called the results of Walgreens</p> '<p> actions in filling prescriptions without due diligence part of a <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2023/may/17/walgreens-reaches-230m-settlement-san-francisco-opioids-crisis" target="_blank">"catastrophic"</a> outcome for the city, overwhelming hospitals and neighborhoods such as the Tenderloin with people</p> <p>who were introduced to their addictions through prescription medication. </p><p>Walgreens, for the record, told me via email</p> :<p> "</p> W<p>e do not discuss our security procedures," but the "safety of our patients, customers and team members is our top priority." </p><p>I asked </p> pastor <p>Brown what he thought of Walgreens</p> ,<p> and he told me he believes there "is corporate guilt for what happened to Banko Brown." </p><p>It reminded him of something he learned from his teacher, the Rev. Martin Luther King Jr., about the </p> "<p>thingification</p> "<p> of Black people, first through enslavement, now through systemic oppression: the guards as less-than-human things to be used by corporations to handle the people seen by many of us as less-than-human things</p>  due to<p> their poverty and addictions. </p><p>"I just threw my whole fg life</p>sk approved <p> away," Anthony wailed when police told him Banko Brown had died at the hospital. "Who ever thought life would be like this?"</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The real and complicated reasons why Los Angeles still has so many RV encampments</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-03-05/reasons-los-angeles-homeless-unhoused-rv-encampments</link>
      <description>There aren't enough trucks to tow or space to park large vehicles. But those issues pale in comparison to changing the mindset of many who live in RVs.</description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 14:00:50 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Erika D. Smith</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-03-05/reasons-los-angeles-homeless-unhoused-rv-encampments</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-03-05/reasons-los-angeles-homeless-unhoused-rv-encampments">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/06fc629/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4000x2272+0+0/resize/320x182!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7e%2F9f%2F3453bd0a48b9bda5fa865b382930%2Fla-photos-1staff-790720-la-me-homeless-encampments-ballona-wetlands-19-als.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/bbd67de/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4000x2272+0+0/resize/568x323!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7e%2F9f%2F3453bd0a48b9bda5fa865b382930%2Fla-photos-1staff-790720-la-me-homeless-encampments-ballona-wetlands-19-als.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/03be21c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4000x2272+0+0/resize/768x436!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7e%2F9f%2F3453bd0a48b9bda5fa865b382930%2Fla-photos-1staff-790720-la-me-homeless-encampments-ballona-wetlands-19-als.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9dee5f0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4000x2272+0+0/resize/1024x582!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7e%2F9f%2F3453bd0a48b9bda5fa865b382930%2Fla-photos-1staff-790720-la-me-homeless-encampments-ballona-wetlands-19-als.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6c0f554/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4000x2272+0+0/resize/1200x682!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7e%2F9f%2F3453bd0a48b9bda5fa865b382930%2Fla-photos-1staff-790720-la-me-homeless-encampments-ballona-wetlands-19-als.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="LOS ANGELES, CA - JUNE 11: Campers are parked along West Jefferson Blvd as Scott Culbertson, executive director of Friends of the Ballona Wetlands gives a tour of some of the destruction caused by homeless encampments that are encroaching on the Freshwater Marsh in Ballona Wetlands. Play Del Rey on Friday, June 11, 2021 in Los Angeles, CA. (Al Seib / Los Angeles Times)."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0bab829/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4000x2272+0+0/resize/320x182!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7e%2F9f%2F3453bd0a48b9bda5fa865b382930%2Fla-photos-1staff-790720-la-me-homeless-encampments-ballona-wetlands-19-als.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ba2d21e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4000x2272+0+0/resize/568x323!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7e%2F9f%2F3453bd0a48b9bda5fa865b382930%2Fla-photos-1staff-790720-la-me-homeless-encampments-ballona-wetlands-19-als.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/62725d5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4000x2272+0+0/resize/768x436!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7e%2F9f%2F3453bd0a48b9bda5fa865b382930%2Fla-photos-1staff-790720-la-me-homeless-encampments-ballona-wetlands-19-als.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2f1796c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4000x2272+0+0/resize/1024x582!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7e%2F9f%2F3453bd0a48b9bda5fa865b382930%2Fla-photos-1staff-790720-la-me-homeless-encampments-ballona-wetlands-19-als.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9480a14/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4000x2272+0+0/resize/1200x682!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7e%2F9f%2F3453bd0a48b9bda5fa865b382930%2Fla-photos-1staff-790720-la-me-homeless-encampments-ballona-wetlands-19-als.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="682"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9480a14/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4000x2272+0+0/resize/1200x682!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7e%2F9f%2F3453bd0a48b9bda5fa865b382930%2Fla-photos-1staff-790720-la-me-homeless-encampments-ballona-wetlands-19-als.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">LOS ANGELES, CA - JUNE 11: Campers are parked along West Jefferson Blvd as Scott Culbertson, executive director of Friends of the Ballona Wetlands gives a tour of some of the destruction caused by homeless encampments that are encroaching on the Freshwater Marsh in Ballona Wetlands. Play Del Rey on Friday, June 11, 2021 in Los Angeles, CA. (Al Seib / Los Angeles Times).</div><div class="figure-credit">(Al Seib/Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>The real and complicated reasons why Los Angeles still has so many RV encampments</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">L.A. Politics </h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/erika-d-smith">        Erika D. Smith    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="March 5, 2023">March 5, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>For five nights, Melissa Grady refused to sleep. </p><p>She told me this on a recent afternoon, rubbing her eyes with blackened hands, while trying to ignore the burned </p>out <p>husk of twisted metal that barely resembled the RV she had been sharing with her boyfriend, Woody Akiedis.</p><p>No one knows for sure how it started, but over President</p>'<p>s Day weekend, a fire engulfed their metal home, melting its tires to the pavement and sending a <a href="https://citizen.com/-NO_zay1JbkXsRu45NN5" target="_blank">plume of dark smoke</a> billowing over the Ballona Wetlands, Playa Vista and Playa del Rey. </p><p>Grady, who had been asleep, saw the flames and dashed outside in panic. Akiedis did</p>,<p> too. But then, for some reason, he went back in. Grady tried to chase him down, getting close enough to spot his ankle. But the heat was too much. Others who had run over from their own RVs couldn't get to him either. </p><p>Eventually, firefighters found the body of Akiedis, charred and lifeless next to his prized, if now destroyed, collection of Hot Wheels toy cars. His friends said he was 60.</p><p>"I just had cinnamon rolls with him," Grady told me in disbelief, taking a break from digging through the wreckage as a line of storm clouds moved in. "Cuddled in bed with him." </p><p>What happened to Akiedis is just one of many truly terrible incidents to befall this encampment on Jefferson Boulevard. It's not far from my apartment, </p>so<p> and since the start of the pandemic, I've watched the number of RVs  and the number of desperate people living in them  grow and shrink, and grow and shrink again. </p><p>There have been fires and overdoses, and at least one deadly shooting. </p><p>Meanwhile, the Ballona Wetlands and adjacent </p> Freshwater Marsh<p>, once prized destinations for bird </p>-<p>watching, have taken a beating environmentally, with mature trees cut down, storm drains used as trash receptacles and the entire area doubling as a toilet.</p><p>"Its so messy and so bad now," lamented Scott Culbertson, executive director of Friends of the Ballona Wetlands.</p><p>That this encampment remains while so many tents have vanished from the Westside of Los Angeles under <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-01-12/karen-bass-housing-homelessness-q-a">Mayor Karen Bass' new "Inside Safe" initiative</a> has caused confusion and consternation among my housed neighbors and environmentalists alike. </p><p>But there are reasons for </p> the difference,<p> so I've come to understand. Complicated reasons that more Angelenos should understand</p>,<p> too, because what's happening on Jefferson Boulevard is all but certain to be repeated in other parts of </p> Los Angeles the city<p>, as the city scales up its efforts to get unhoused people indoors. </p><p>"We have not resolved the RV issue yet," Bass acknowledged. "But we absolutely will because it's a very serious issue."</p><p>Just don't <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2021-11-27/banning-la-homeless-encampments-could-get-more-support-than-liberals-think">expect it to happen quickly</a>. Nearly a year after the L.A. City Council <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-04-07/los-angeles-lifts-moratorium-on-towing-rvs-pledges-to-move-homeless-camps">voted to lift a pandemic-era moratorium</a> on towing oversize</p>d<p> vehicles used as homes that had been parked for months on city streets, there are all sorts of logistical problems. </p><p>Then as now, there aren't enough trucks capable of removing such large vehicles, not enough space to store them, and not enough money to pay for it all. More recently, finding the owners of RVs has become a challenge because, quite often, the occupants are merely renters, making towing a legally dubious decision. </p><p>But those problems pale in comparison to changing the mindset of many of the people who live in those RVs. </p><p>"They don't necessarily consider themselves as homeless," said Va Lecia Adams Kellum, the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/homeless-housing/story/2023-01-23/va-lecia-adams-kellum-appointed-new-head-of-lahsa">incoming chief executive of the Los Angeles Homeless Services Authority</a>. "This thing they had that kept them from being in a tent was extremely important to how they defined [and] how they saw themselves."</p><p>After the storms that rolled through L.A. in January, for example, outreach workers in Venice were able to motivate people in tents to <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-01-11/mayor-karen-bass-inside-safe-venice-homeless-encampment">trade in their soaked bedding</a> for a hotel room and the promise of future permanent housing. </p><p>That probably won't work as well for those living in RVs on Jefferson Boulevard. They rolled through February's storms with roofs over their heads and dry, if dilapidated, places to sleep.</p><p>"How," Adams Kellum continued, "do you convince someone that they're vulnerable and homeless, and they don't see themselves as homeless?"</p><p>::</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/fe/c7/925fcf084da68c816c60e9adad14/la-photos-1staff-790720-la-me-homeless-encampments-ballona-wetlands-13-als.jpg"></figure><p>When I first met Wendy Lockett, she was the newest resident of the encampment on Jefferson Boulevard.</p><p>It was deep in the pandemic <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2021-06-17/hes-watching-la-homelessness-destroy-ballona-wetlands">in the summer of 2021</a>. I had been trudging along a trail with Culbertson, who seemed as pained about the environmental damage to the Freshwater Marsh as the humanitarian crisis playing out alongside it, when we came upon a hand-painted sign.</p><p>DO NOT THROW TRASH OVER THIS FENCE!! IF I CATCH YOU, I WILL HUNT YOU DOWN AND EAT YOU FOR BREAKFAST.</p><p>Lockett, a slight woman with dark hair and piercing eyes, emerged from a white van, smiling proudly at her handiwork. She told us she had been living there for about six months. </p><p>Nearly two years later, and she's still out there. Well, I should say she's </p>back<p> out there. For a time, she had moved into a hotel room near LAX, but told me she got "kicked out" for painting on the walls, mural-style. So, she got another RV and returned to the life and the people she knew. </p><p>Now with Akiedis gone, Lockett has been at the encampment the longest and, as such, feels responsible for protecting Grady, even finding her another RV.</p><p>"I'm kind of like the sheriff," Lockett told me. "He was the mayor, for lack of better terminology. He was very diplomatic, and knew how to handle stuff. I literally go after people with bats when I lose my temper." </p><p>As if on cue, she spotted a man stealing something from a pile of belongings outside a neighbor's RV and took off after him yelling, her </p>pitbull  pit bull<p> not far behind. </p><p>"There she goes," Grady said, laughing as another woman handed her a peanut butter and jelly sandwich. </p><p>Like it or not, this RV encampment, like so many others across Los Angeles, has evolved over the </p>p<p>last three years into what can only be called a community. An entrenched one, at that. </p><p>Those who live on Jefferson Boulevard see themselves as residents, the block along the Freshwater Marsh as their neighborhood, and their RVs spread throughout it like houses with addresses and yards. They look out for </p> one anothereach other,<p> too.</p><p>After the firefighters had put out the flames and removed Akiedis' remains, nosy housed residents from nearby neighborhoods started coming by. One man brought a camera and began</p> <p>taking photos. Lockett and other residents from the encampment pulled him aside and told him to leave, to be respectful of what had been Grady's home. </p><p>"I was pretty disgusted by the behavior," Culbertson recounted. "Nobody's fought harder to get these RVs out of here than me, but for crying out loud, somebody just died."</p><p>::</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/0c/d6/d12622a14933a84bab96c019ce49/1237839-me-0105-venice-homeless-gem-015.jpg"></figure><p>So how do you convince someone that they're vulnerable and homeless </p> when<p> they don't see themselves as homeless?</p><p>Adams Kellum has ideas. </p><p>One is to work with other organizations to secure cheap or free places to park RVs for people who have agreed to move indoors. It's hard to believe, but apparently there aren't enough underused, city-owned parking lots for this.</p><p>Bass found that out while exploring whether to make the encampment on Jefferson Boulevard one of the first sites to try "Inside Safe." </p><p>"We thought we had identified a property near the airport. But it turned out that the rent for that parking lot was going to be in the millions," she told me. "And then we had to decide, do we spend money that way? Or do we take the millions leasing motel rooms and getting people out of tents?"</p><p>Her administration chose the latter. </p><p>Another idea, which Bass favors, is to persuade people to give up their RVs for demolition</p> by offering to pay them a lump sum for it and wipe out parking tickets and warrants<p>. </p> That could happen by offering to pay a lump sum for the vehicles or by wiping out parking tickets and warrants. <p>L.A. City Councilmember Monica Rodriguez had some <a href="https://www.dailynews.com/2022/11/04/la-councilwoman-monica-rodriguez-says-her-push-to-get-homeless-out-of-rvs-is-working/?clearUserState=true" target="_blank">success with such incentives</a> during a pilot program last year in her San Fernando Valley district. </p><p>But to do this, city officials must first convince people like Lockett that it's worth the risk. That giving up the only shelter they have in hopes of securing something better won't backfire. After years of bureaucratic failures and broken promises for permanent and even temporary housing, such trust is a tough sell. </p><p>"If people feel like their income is so unstable or their housing has been unstable all these years, it's hard for them, right? Their mindset is, </p> '<p>I'm not in the tent,</p> '<p>" Adams Kellum said. "</p> '<p>What do I do if I fall out of housing? Like, what if I lose my voucher or I lose my job?</p> '<p>" </p><p>What's clear is that offers of hotel rooms probably aren't going to be enough for RV dwellers, who feel as though they already are in a form of temporary housing. Permanent housing will be key, but it's in short supply.</p><p>In the meantime, L.A. City Councilmember Traci Park, whose Westside district takes in the Ballona Wetlands and Freshwater Marsh, said city sanitation workers have visited the RV encampment on Jefferson Boulevard multiple times in the past two months, and have removed tens of thousands of pounds of trash and hazardous waste. </p><p>The number of RVs, by her office's count, has dropped from 50 to about 25, thanks in part to efforts by outreach workers. </p> Many more are <p><a href="https://smdp.com/2022/09/19/county-hopes-to-remove-one-in-six-rv-encampments-by-2026/" target="_blank">parked across the city and unincorporated county</a></p> .<p>"I am extremely concerned about the unsafe conditions that those RVs present for the people who are living in them," Park said. "A lot of folks are using gas-powered generators for electricity and heat, folks are using space heaters and warmers inside those RVs, many of which cannot pass basic fire safety standards."</p><p>I'm extremely concerned</p>,<p> too. But watching Grady sift through lumps of burnt debris just</p> <p>feet from where Akiedis died, looking for anything salvageable enough to move to her new RV, it's clear that she wasn't</p> . <p>"I thank God we had him," Grady said, "even if it wasn't long enough."</p> LA Times Today: The real and complicated reasons why Los Angeles still has so many RV encampments                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jeanette Rowe, who brought homeless services to people in the streets of L.A., dies at 72</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-06/jeanette-rowe-homeless-outreach-pioneer-dies</link>
      <description>Rowe rejected the idea homeless people were 'service-resistant,' feeling they would come indoors if people would only listen to them.</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 18:12:26 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Gale Holland</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-06/jeanette-rowe-homeless-outreach-pioneer-dies</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-06/jeanette-rowe-homeless-outreach-pioneer-dies">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/906d2a9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/784f939/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/71cb368/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/046e6e7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2f22e75/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Jeanette Rowe, left, meets Beverly Walker, who was living on a sidewalk in Los Angeles."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/12508db/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/dc32754/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/887ddba/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/694fe96/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0a09b75/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0a09b75/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption"> Jeanette Rowe, left, meets Beverly Walker, who was living on a sidewalk in Los Angeles. </div><div class="figure-credit">(Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Jeanette Rowe, who brought homeless services to people in the streets of L.A., dies at 72</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/gale-holland">        Gale Holland    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 6, 2023">June 6, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Jeanette Rowe, a pioneer in bringing homeless services into the streets instead of dumping people on Skid Row, or expecting them to scale bureaucratic mountains, has died at 72.</p><p>Mayor Karen Bass' Inside Safe encampment clearances and other modern homeless programs were "built on the shoulders" of Rowe, the agency's current director said. Rowe took the Los Angeles Homeless Services Authority's emergency response team from two to 85 staff members. </p><p>"Not everyone would feel comfortable seeking help because of levels of depression, hopelessness and other challenges," said LAHSA executive director Va Lecia Adams Kellum. "The notion someone goes to the encampment gives inspiration to them."</p><p>Within a year of her 2016 retirement from LAHSA, Rowe took a position as head of programs at the Midnight Mission on Skid Row, where she overcame institutional resistance to build the 110-year-old shelter's first women's program.</p><p>Rowe called herself "an old hippie," but few hippies ever worked her punishing six-day </p>work<p> weeks, helping people at encampments from the San Gabriel riverbed to Union Station, where she spent a two-day Christmas holiday helping relocate hundreds of people swept out of the landmark's ornate lobby. </p><p>Homeless people were not "service resistant," she believed  if only </p>anyone someone <p>would listen to what they needed. Besides, she said, "I dig that these people have a choice." </p><p>Rowe died May 26 at a hospital after a short illness. She is survived by her wife, Karen Jenkins-Galloway; brother Eddie Rowe and sister Marilyn Silver. </p>Midnight Mission president G. Michael Arnold said.  <p>Rowe grew up in Newark, N.J., in a poor household that never felt that way. My mother always said you only need one pair of shoes, she said.</p><p>Her mother kept the back door, and her dinner table, open to people facing hard times.</p><p>I never slept by myself until I left home for college at Cal State Los Angeles and Dominguez Hills, where she studied music, Rowe said. </p><p>She was working as an accountant when the plight of young homeless people in Hollywood drew her into homeless services. At first she worked with homeless families and children, who she found thrived if their bonds to church, school and community were preserved while they got back on their feet.</p><p> Midnight Mission President G. Michael Arnold said what passed for outreach back then was rounding up homeless people to drop off at Skid Row shelters, or handing out appointment slips.</p><p> "Jeanette realized what she learned applies to everyone being traumatized on the street," said Arnold, who also headed LAHSA during Rowe's tenure there. </p><p>The homeless service system had floundered for years in fits and starts, Rowe said. Sobering centers, serviced by Skid Rows boozer cruise, and short-term rent vouchers were cut off for lack of funding. Until 2005, officials had no reliable homeless count, which she likened to trying to cook without knowing whos coming to dinner.</p><p>After the 2016 passage of the city's $1.2-billion homeless housing bond, she felt Los Angeles was heading in the right direction and retired from LAHSA. "Housing is key," she said. </p><p>Her plan was to rescue animals and organize concerts for homeless people with a musician friend from New York. She did rescue street animals, particularly in her longtime neighborhood of Leimert Park, and organize Skid Row concerts  but her retirement was barely a year old when Arnold hired her at the Midnight Mission, where she worked until her death. </p><p> "Her heart just wouldn't keep her out of the streets," Arnold said.</p><p>Doris Starling, the Midnight Mission's director of street services access center, called Rowe her friend and mentor. </p><p>"She taught me how to motivate people," said Starling, adding that they often </p> attendedbought tickets to<p> women's basketball games together.</p>Starlng said she would never ask users to give up drugs. Instead, she'd ask how much they could cut back, pointing out the money they saved could go for rent in housing. "And when they started cooking for themselves and showering and going to the movies and on dates, they'd come to me and say , 'I got to get into a [drug] program,' "she said.<p>Rowe</p>r<p> was a gifted writer, and her program proposals generally won the day  even when they arrived by email at 3 in the morning, Starling said. </p><p>"We'd say, 'Jeanette. Go to bed. Please go to bed,'" Starling said. </p>Memorial plans are pending.                                     </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homeless outreach workers are paid so little they risk losing their own housing</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/opinion/story/2023-06-04/outreach-workers-to-homeless-people-shouldnt-risk-becoming-homeless-themselves</link>
      <description>Front-line workers grapple with money worries as well as the stress of a job working with traumatized people. It's no surprise that burnout and turnover are high.</description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2023 12:00:07 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>The Times Editorial Board</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/opinion/story/2023-06-04/outreach-workers-to-homeless-people-shouldnt-risk-becoming-homeless-themselves</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/opinion/story/2023-06-04/outreach-workers-to-homeless-people-shouldnt-risk-becoming-homeless-themselves">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/783c522/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2Fbb%2F47a9aef140a5869acbc76af50efd%2F929434-me-0315-metro-station-homeless-003-ik.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/970a14f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2Fbb%2F47a9aef140a5869acbc76af50efd%2F929434-me-0315-metro-station-homeless-003-ik.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f5c81f0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2Fbb%2F47a9aef140a5869acbc76af50efd%2F929434-me-0315-metro-station-homeless-003-ik.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/29b3779/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2Fbb%2F47a9aef140a5869acbc76af50efd%2F929434-me-0315-metro-station-homeless-003-ik.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d48fd4a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2Fbb%2F47a9aef140a5869acbc76af50efd%2F929434-me-0315-metro-station-homeless-003-ik.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Los Angeles, CA - March 15: John Hargrave, PATH outreach worker, right, talks to a homeless woman Tracy Hellams, center, resting at the entrance of 7th. Street Metro station on Tuesday, March 15, 2022 in Los Angeles, CA. (Irfan Khan / Los Angeles Times)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/27fcda7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2Fbb%2F47a9aef140a5869acbc76af50efd%2F929434-me-0315-metro-station-homeless-003-ik.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4d0515b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2Fbb%2F47a9aef140a5869acbc76af50efd%2F929434-me-0315-metro-station-homeless-003-ik.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/287a00b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2Fbb%2F47a9aef140a5869acbc76af50efd%2F929434-me-0315-metro-station-homeless-003-ik.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/287effc/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2Fbb%2F47a9aef140a5869acbc76af50efd%2F929434-me-0315-metro-station-homeless-003-ik.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c6fb941/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2Fbb%2F47a9aef140a5869acbc76af50efd%2F929434-me-0315-metro-station-homeless-003-ik.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c6fb941/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Faa%2Fbb%2F47a9aef140a5869acbc76af50efd%2F929434-me-0315-metro-station-homeless-003-ik.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Los Angeles, CA - March 15: John Hargrave, PATH outreach worker, right, talks to a homeless woman Tracy Hellams, center, resting at the entrance of 7th. Street Metro station on Tuesday, March 15, 2022 in Los Angeles, CA. (Irfan Khan / Los Angeles Times)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Irfan Khan/Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Homeless outreach workers are paid so little they risk losing their own housing</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">Editorials</h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/the-times-editorial-board">        The Times Editorial Board    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 4, 2023">June 4, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>In Los Angeles, an outreach worker searches out homeless people, makes contact, earns the trust of people who have learned to trust few and shepherds them into temporary housing and eventually permanent housing. Sometimes, they are first responders for homeless people living on sidewalks, in parks and along beaches. They routinely carry naloxone to administer to homeless people who overdose on opioids, and they use it more and more often.</p><p>Outreach workers, along with social workers and case managers who help get homeless people services, benefits and housing are the people who toil on the front lines of the homelessness crisis that the city and county of Los Angeles have devoted billions to address. Their jobs are grueling. Thousands of them work for the nonprofit organizations that serve homeless people. But these front-line workers are paid so little that they face their own struggles to stay housed in the high-priced L.A. County market, according to a new <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-15/frontline-workers-key-in-l-a-countys-homelessness-struggle-to-afford-ho">study</a> by the Rand Corp. commissioned by the nonprofit Social Justice Partners Los Angeles.</p><p><a href="https://www.rand.org/pubs/research_reports/RRA2266-1.html" target="_blank">According to the study</a>, most are paid between $40,000 and $60,000 a year. (Excluded from the survey were healthcare professionals working for these nonprofits who generally are offered more competitive pay, according to the study.)</p><p>But it takes a salary of $64,000 to afford a one-bedroom apartment in L.A. County without spending more than 30% of annual income in housing costs, according to the study, which uses the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development's calculation of fair market rents. As a result, workers grapple with money worries as well as the stress of a job working with traumatized people. Burnout and turnover are high, the study says, citing a report that found that 53% of people doing this work had spent less than two years at their current employer in part because of worker burnout. According to the study, more than 200 nonprofits are doing homeless services work. </p><p>John Maceri, the chief executive of the homeless services nonprofit the People Concern, says that his younger, newer staff members tend to stay </p> between<p> 12 </p> and<p> 18 months. Longer tenured staff have been there five to seven years, he estimates, but they struggle the most with burnout. Turnover is not only bad for workers, its bad for their homeless clients who, according to the report, have cycled through as many as six or seven case managers in Los Angeles County. And both the majority of front-line workers as well as the people they serve are Black and brown.</p><p>Why the low pay? Nonprofit homeless service organizations that employ the front-line workers work mostly on contracts with government agencies  such as the Los Angeles Homeless Services Authority  to provide homeless services. Those contracts are funded with county, city, state or federal funds </p> that nonprofits say are routinely underfunded.Nonprofits blame the government agencies who hire them for<b> </b>routinely underfunding contracts. <p>The total expenses to provide services at a shelter or housing development, </p> including worker pay,<p> can be $70 to $125 per bed (based on a 2021 estimate)<b> </b>depending on whether the clients have mental illnesses, substance abuse issues, chronic physical ailments or some combination thereof. Maceri says if his organization is providing services in an interim housing location, the bed rates on some contracts range from $50 to $68 a day.<b> </b>The true costs are closer to $108 a night, he said. The expectation is that whatever it costs, youll figure it out. As a result, organizations must fund-raise privately to attempt to make up the difference.</p><p>L.A. city and county agencies must stop exploiting people doing this indispensable humanitarian work by underpaying them. These workers should be paid enough to afford housing. Two years ago the editorial board <a href="https://www.latimes.com/opinion/story/2021-05-10/service-providers-get-homeless-people-off-the-streets-and-into-housing-pay-them-what-they-need">wrote </a>about how little homeless service workers get paid  even when the federal government mandated that pandemic relief dollars going to homelessness programs cover actual costs. As the new Rand study indicates, they are still underpaid. Va Lecia Adams Kellum, the new head of LAHSA, has said her agency is working with federal, state and local entities to develop funding models that will allow for higher pay. </p><p>The Rand study recommends, among other things, that government<b> </b>funders cover the full cost of services that an organization provides. It also suggests that workers get basic cost of living increases in their contracts.</p><p>Those are smart recommendations. Mayor Karen Bass is deeply invested in moving homeless people out of encampments and into housing. Part of that investment must involve fair pay for the workers who connect with homeless individuals and make that move toward housing happen.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My son the vandal — and the untreated, unaddressed epidemic of mental illness</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/opinion/story/2023-06-04/mental-health-psychoaffective-disorder-psych-hold-incarceration</link>
      <description>Our son has schizoaffective disorder with depressive episodes. He was arrested in L.A. for breaking windows, jailed, found competent and released pending a court date. Things did not go well.</description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2023 10:00:47 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Kerry Madden-Lunsford</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/opinion/story/2023-06-04/mental-health-psychoaffective-disorder-psych-hold-incarceration</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/opinion/story/2023-06-04/mental-health-psychoaffective-disorder-psych-hold-incarceration">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7d0692c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F38%2Fc5%2F51d0db244ebb8a4c75150ee9ae2a%2Foe-madden-lunsford-mental-health-illo.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1b27e6a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F38%2Fc5%2F51d0db244ebb8a4c75150ee9ae2a%2Foe-madden-lunsford-mental-health-illo.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/943f154/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F38%2Fc5%2F51d0db244ebb8a4c75150ee9ae2a%2Foe-madden-lunsford-mental-health-illo.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8aafdbc/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F38%2Fc5%2F51d0db244ebb8a4c75150ee9ae2a%2Foe-madden-lunsford-mental-health-illo.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/bc05c66/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F38%2Fc5%2F51d0db244ebb8a4c75150ee9ae2a%2Foe-madden-lunsford-mental-health-illo.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Illustration of a shattered window with reflections of a man and multiple demons seen in the shards. A hole is in the middle."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/38c0930/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F38%2Fc5%2F51d0db244ebb8a4c75150ee9ae2a%2Foe-madden-lunsford-mental-health-illo.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8eb051d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F38%2Fc5%2F51d0db244ebb8a4c75150ee9ae2a%2Foe-madden-lunsford-mental-health-illo.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/80a8232/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F38%2Fc5%2F51d0db244ebb8a4c75150ee9ae2a%2Foe-madden-lunsford-mental-health-illo.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/baec158/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F38%2Fc5%2F51d0db244ebb8a4c75150ee9ae2a%2Foe-madden-lunsford-mental-health-illo.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/38fdff4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F38%2Fc5%2F51d0db244ebb8a4c75150ee9ae2a%2Foe-madden-lunsford-mental-health-illo.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/38fdff4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F38%2Fc5%2F51d0db244ebb8a4c75150ee9ae2a%2Foe-madden-lunsford-mental-health-illo.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">Our son has schizoaffective disorder with depressive episodes. He was arrested in L.A. for breaking windows, jailed, found competent and released pending a court date. Things did not go well. Illustration by Ivan Ehlers / For The Times</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>My son the vandal  and the untreated, unaddressed epidemic of mental illness </h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">Op-Ed,Mental Health</h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" >        Kerry Madden-Lunsford    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 4, 2023">June 4, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>In a courthouse hallway in Los Angeles in early May, I begged my sons public defender to advocate for a mental health program where he could get the treatment he needed.</p><p>She wasnt listening, not to me or my husband or Soma Snakeoil</p>,<p> of the Skid Row non</p>-<p>profit Sidewalk Project, who advocates for our son.</p><p>At age 34, plagued with mental health and addiction issues, our son has lived unhoused for almost a third of his life  beneath trees, on sidewalks, in abandoned buildings and inside the cab of a truck.</p><p>Now he was in court because of an outstanding 2020 bench warrant for felony vandalism. Hed broken windows in a commercial building because he saw something evil reflected there, causing approximately $40,000 in damages.</p><p>When he was late to the hearing, the </p> public defenderPD<p> said, He must be having trouble parking.</p><p>Parking? He hasnt had a car or a drivers license in years, I wanted to say. Shed turned away. He was her client, not us, his parents.</p><p>Our son has schizoaffective disorder with depressive episodes. He had gotten picked up on the bench warrant in October, jailed until a competency hearing in April  which he passed  and then released pending the May court date. After the release, things had not gone well with him. But the competency decision was still in force.</p><p>If only it had still been accurate. During his months of incarceration, his father or I had spoken with him daily, and we visited weekly. We sent care packages, letters and books. So did friends. He read a lot: The Count of Monte Cristo</p>, <p>My ntonia, On Gold Mountain, Anna Karenina and lots of Jackie Collins.</p><p>While inside, he refused meds and regaled us with impersonations of doctors who visited him. But housed and free of drugs, he grew interested in his family again.</p><p>How was his new nephew doing? His siblings? He asked about our rehearsals with the Silverlake Singers and recommended that we drink tea with honey and lemon to keep our voices healthy.</p><p>I told myself, even if he goes out again, at least weve had these months. Our son was back, albeit behind thick glass during visiting hours or calling on prepaid cards from a jail phone.</p><p>The day after the April competency hearing, my son was supposed to answer for the broken windows. But the prosecutors werent ready. We were in the courtroom that day too. When his </p> public defenderPD<p> argued for my son's release, she explained that hed be staying with a girlfriend in Inglewood.</p><p>So the parents are unwilling to accept him into the home? the judge asked. She stared at us.</p><p>We weren't sure how to respond. We knew from long experience we couldnt run a rehab for him or be his jailers. But hes our beloved son. Maybe this time we could figure it out.</p><p>Well accept him, I said.</p><p>Our son smiled at us in his jail clothes from the holding box.</p><p>His release took 24 hours to process. He walked home from Twin Towers to Echo Park in the rain. For several days, we cooked dinners, attended a film festival, made lunches with the Hollywood Food Coalition, reconnected with family, and he played the piano.</p><p>Then it started. I spent 15 hours trying to get him to stop harming himself as he removed nonexistent mites from his face with bug spray, avocados, soup, chocolate, hydrogen peroxide, shaving cream, candle wax and turmeric.</p><p>I sent texts, photos and videos to his public defender to keep her informed of his mental state. With the help of the county Psychiatric Mobile Response Team, our son was placed on an emergency psych hold. A week later, the hospital released him with bus fare to Inglewood. Wed asked for a longer emergency hold, the better to get his meds and his life regulated. </p><p>We got nowhere.</p><p>Our family is by no means unique. Were part of an untreated, unaddressed epidemic.</p><p>When our son is not using, he is still psychotic, and his delusions are poetic and cinematic. He is convinced that Germans invented time travel. He can summon the year 1890 with broken headphones, which allow him to hear the old trolley cars in L.A. Hes fixated on local history, old Hollywood and baseball: Jean Harlow, Mayor Tom Bradley, Bob Gibson. When he was arrested on the bench warrant in October, he carried</p> <p>only a baseball and glove.</p><p>He doesnt want treatment. Hes lived a feral life on the streets. During the pandemic, he stayed in hotels as part of Project Room Key, and wed take him for picnics. But, according to him, the water in the showers weakened his joints and it was back to the streets.</p><p>We try to understand, why him, why us? Our son has been our greatest teacher. As a young mother, I thought if you loved your children and helped them pursue their dreams, it would be enough. Its not enough, and it never will be when youre grappling with the twin monsters of addiction and mental illness.</p><p>My son finally made it to the May hearing. In the courtroom, </p> Soma Snakeoil<p> attempted to explain the odyssey hed been through, what wed been through  would the court hear her out? The judge just said, "I don't allow questions in my courtroom."</p><p>His jail time was taken into account. He was put on probation and assigned community service.</p><p>When we walked out of the courthouse, </p> Soma<p> asked him what he needed. "Trust and communication," he said. He would be open to the Sidewalk Projects offer of housing and medication. He sounded rational, if you didnt know better.</p><p>His father hugged him goodbye and went to work.</p><p>Then my son and I sat on a bench in Grand Park by City Hall. He rolled up his sleeves and showed me his arms, skin raw from scraping.</p><p>He said, Why are you crying? I didnt do it! It was zappers. They got me.</p><p>We talked in circles. He wanted my coat because the zappers had also ripped a hole in his pants.</p><p>No, I told him. Sorry, I love this coat.</p><p>Then buy me new pants, come on, Virginia Woolf. Dont look so doom and gloom. You dont know my life. Im fine. Im great.</p><p>When we hugged goodbye, I left him standing on Grand Avenue by the Music Center afraid he would follow me, afraid he wouldn't. He didn't.</p><p>I headed for the bus stop, and Echo Park, walking home through the hills, listening to wind chimes and leaf blowers, the sounds of an ordinary Monday in the city.&nbsp;</p>Kerry Madden-Lunsford lives in Los Angeles and Alabama, where she is a professor of creative writing at the University of Alabama at Birmingham. Her forthcoming children's novel is "Werewolf Hamlet."                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What's the cost to cool Los Angeles? City explores a cooling mandate for all rental units</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-03/los-angeles-explores-a-cooling-mandate-for-all-rental-units</link>
      <description>Los Angeles city leaders also directed staff to explore programs to potentially assist low- and middle-income families in paying to install and operate an AC unit.</description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jun 2023 13:00:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Nathan Solis</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-03/los-angeles-explores-a-cooling-mandate-for-all-rental-units</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-03/los-angeles-explores-a-cooling-mandate-for-all-rental-units">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d7702d4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5516x3599+0+0/resize/320x209!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc6%2Fc0%2F2fc94f2f4edebe3d8e40ebfe0003%2Fap100928157211.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8729206/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5516x3599+0+0/resize/568x371!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc6%2Fc0%2F2fc94f2f4edebe3d8e40ebfe0003%2Fap100928157211.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f1f14e1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5516x3599+0+0/resize/768x501!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc6%2Fc0%2F2fc94f2f4edebe3d8e40ebfe0003%2Fap100928157211.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/bdc8506/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5516x3599+0+0/resize/1024x668!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc6%2Fc0%2F2fc94f2f4edebe3d8e40ebfe0003%2Fap100928157211.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f0f1711/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5516x3599+0+0/resize/1200x783!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc6%2Fc0%2F2fc94f2f4edebe3d8e40ebfe0003%2Fap100928157211.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Even though the air coming out is pretty warm, Al Manzano, founder of A&amp;M Refrigeration Co., cools his hand on the vent fan outlet on an air conditioning unit on the roof of an apartment building in the North Hollywood district of Los Angeles Tuesday, Sept. 28, 2010. Tuesday temperatures, while not as high as the previous day, continued near the triple-digit mark, with elevated humidity for overall muggy weather, in many parts of Southern California. (AP Photo/Reed Saxon)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b43e0f0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5516x3599+0+0/resize/320x209!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc6%2Fc0%2F2fc94f2f4edebe3d8e40ebfe0003%2Fap100928157211.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d5b6f68/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5516x3599+0+0/resize/568x371!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc6%2Fc0%2F2fc94f2f4edebe3d8e40ebfe0003%2Fap100928157211.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a1251d6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5516x3599+0+0/resize/768x501!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc6%2Fc0%2F2fc94f2f4edebe3d8e40ebfe0003%2Fap100928157211.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/68052b0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5516x3599+0+0/resize/1024x668!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc6%2Fc0%2F2fc94f2f4edebe3d8e40ebfe0003%2Fap100928157211.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b437598/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5516x3599+0+0/resize/1200x783!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc6%2Fc0%2F2fc94f2f4edebe3d8e40ebfe0003%2Fap100928157211.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="783"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b437598/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5516x3599+0+0/resize/1200x783!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc6%2Fc0%2F2fc94f2f4edebe3d8e40ebfe0003%2Fap100928157211.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Even though the air coming out is pretty warm, Al Manzano, founder of A&amp;M Refrigeration Co., cools his hand on the vent fan outlet on an air conditioning unit on the roof of an apartment building in the North Hollywood district of Los Angeles Tuesday, Sept. 28, 2010. Tuesday temperatures, while not as high as the previous day, continued near the triple-digit mark, with elevated humidity for overall muggy weather, in many parts of Southern California. (AP Photo/Reed Saxon)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Reed Saxon/AP)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>What&#x27;s the cost to cool Los Angeles? City explores a cooling mandate for all rental units</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/nathan-solis">        Nathan Solis    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 3, 2023">June 3, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Heading into the peak of summer, Los Angeles officials want to know what it would take to require every rental unit in the city to have an air conditioner or central air.</p><p>Just last year, Southern California was gripped by a 10-day heat wave that <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-09-07/extreme-heat-across-california-lingers-threat-of-blackouts-grows">rippled through the region and smashed temperature records.</a> By the time </p> it <p>subsided, Los Angeles County emergency crews had responded to 146 calls classified as heat  defined by the agency as environmental hyperthermia. </p>So <p>Now, city staff are studying the costs and feasibility of cooling off all rental units citywide. </p><p>"At this point in the climate emergency, the ability to cool one's home cannot be considered a luxury and rather must be treated as a necessity," Los Angeles City Councilmember Eunisses Hernandez said in her motion proposing the feasibility study, which would include a cost estimate for updating the city's building code. </p><p>"Requiring cooling apparati for all residential units could be a life</p>-<p>saving measure for countless Angelenos during extreme heat events."</p><p>The council approved the motion Wednesday, and it is expected to come back for public input. </p><p>A 2021 <a href="https://www.latimes.com/projects/california-extreme-heat-deaths-show-climate-change-risks/#nt=0000017c-3247-d42d-adfd-32ef494d0000-showMedia-title-promoSuperLeadSmall-1col-enhancement" target="_blank">Times investigation found that 3,900 deaths</a> were caused by extreme heat in California from 2010 to 2019. But access to life</p>-<p>saving cooling devices and the ability to cover the costs of electricity during a heat wave are often out of reach for low</p> -<p>income and elderly residents on a fixed income.</p><p>As part of the proposed study, the council asked staff to determine which buildings lack submeters, </p>a<p> device</p> s <p>that allow</p>s<p> utility companies to track power consumption on a unit-by-unit basis, and also the difference in costs between installing wall </p>AC  air conditioning<p> units </p>or <p>versus a central air system for an entire building.</p><p>Currently, air conditioners or central air are not required to ensure a rental unit is habitable in California, according to the state building standards code.</p> The lack of an air conditioner didn't bother Juliana Wingate when she and her husband moved into their apartment last year near MacArthur Park. Then in late August a record-breaking heat wave hit and Wingate felt miserable. "Our cat spent most of his time in our bathtub,  because it was so much cooler,"  Wingate said Wingate, who recalls feeling lightheaded and nauseated during the 10-day heat wave, when temperatures    topped   hit over 100 degrees. She 's hasn't thought about the lack of a cooling device this year, but now that it's getting warm again she's wondering if it would be better to just leave their second-story apartment. "Clearly, if that's not possible, I will bring it up with our landlord," Wingate said. It's unclear if that would mean her rent would go up, but she's not sure she could stick it out for another summer. "I love that every year just keeps getting hotter," Wingate said sarcastically.The state California <p>laid the ground</p> <p>work for an extreme heat action plan last year and earmarked $800 million to address the issue, but also saw a proposal to establish a chief heat officer fail in the state Assembly. A statewide <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-09-09/newsom-signs-bills-california-extreme-heat-warning-system">warning and ranking system</a> for extreme heat events is expected to launch by 2025, providing </p>some <p>general information to the public, much like the way other states respond to hurricanes. </p><p>But to advocates </p>on the ground<p>  </p>like  such as<p> housing policy coordinator Jovana Morales with </p>the <p>Leadership Counsel for Justice and Accountability, a Central Valley</p>-based<p> advocacy group  it feels like the emphasis on addressing climate change and strengthening heat waves is often ignored until summer </p>time <p>rolls around and reminds everyone of the danger.</p><p>"I just don't feel like there is urgency in the Legislature," Morales said. "You know</p>,<p> ... we've been working on this, and people have been advocating for solutions, especially </p>like  ... <p>in the home, but it's just not happening fast enough."</p><p>Morales' group last year supported </p>proposed legislation,<p> <a href="https://leginfo.legislature.ca.gov/faces/billNavClient.xhtml?bill_id=202120220AB2597">Assembly Bill 2597,</a> which sought to update the state's building code to set a safe maximum indoor temperature in new and existing dwelling units. Units found without cooling options would be deemed substandard, according to the bill, which failed to become law.</p><p>The proposed code update was meant to address workers who live in substandard housing conditions, where temperatures often become so hot that </p>rental <p>units are unsafe to live in, Morales said.</p><p>But </p>the <p>Leadership Counsel was not focused solely on air conditioners. </p>They  It <p>pushed for improved insulation, increased shade through landscaping, heat pumps and roofs designed to reflect sunlight. AC units were not an emphasis</p>,<p> because they generate greenhouse gas emissions.</p><p>"Many of the older buildings just don't have that cooling mechanism, and so our bill would have required to set an indoor maximum air temperature," Morales said.</p><p>Older buildings are often the only units low</p> -<p>income families can afford, Morales said, and they would benefit the most from updates to the </p>existing <p>housing code to require cooling standards.</p><p>City leaders directed staff to study an update to the </p>existing <p>housing code</p>,<p> and </p>also <p>explore potential programs to </p>assist  help<p> low- and middle-income families </p>in <p>pay</p>ing<p> for the installation and operation of an AC unit.</p><p>Fred Sutton, senior vice president of local public affairs </p>with  for<p> the California Apartment Assn., said tenants are aware of the amenities available when they sign a lease. Those tenants can and should approach their landlords if they want to have a cooling device installed in</p>to<p> their units, he said.</p><p>But mandating that all rental units have a cooling device would push the cost onto the landlords and the tenants, Sutton said.</p><p>"I heard a lot from the city about subsidies for tenants facing extra utility costs," Sutton said. "But what cost would that work mean for the building and the [landlords]?"</p><p>The Los Angeles Department of Water and Power offers </p>a variety of <p>options for low-income residents through the <a href="https://www.ladwp.com/ladwp/faces/ladwp/residential/r-financialassistance/r-fa-assistanceprograms/r-fa-ap-coolla?_afrLoop=834097661846520&amp;_afrWindowMode=0&amp;_afrWindowId=null#%40%3F_afrWindowId%3Dnull%26_afrLoop%3D834097661846520%26_afrWindowMode%3D0%26_adf.ctrl-state%3D14sbrvxbqy_17" target="_blank">Cool L.A. program it launched last summer.</a> Those include subsidies to help pay electric bills during a heat wave, rebates to offset costs and other resources meant to help residents weather the heat.</p><p>The requested report is expected to be presented to the City Council's Housing and Homelessness Committee </p>sometime <p>in the next several weeks.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>It's not just State Farm. Allstate no longer sells new home insurance policies in California</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-06-02/allstate-state-farm-stop-selling-new-home-insurance-in-california</link>
      <description>Allstate tells regulators it has stopped selling new home insurance policies in California. State Farm said it's no longer accepting new applications.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2023 19:20:49 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Eliyahu Kamisher, Max Reyes and Biz Carson</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-06-02/allstate-state-farm-stop-selling-new-home-insurance-in-california</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-06-02/allstate-state-farm-stop-selling-new-home-insurance-in-california">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3ac5e89/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc0%2Fdf%2Ffdafc3ad20d400defed3f6b53d6e%2Fimg-la-photos-1staff-470-2-1-8l631v8h.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/32e0219/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc0%2Fdf%2Ffdafc3ad20d400defed3f6b53d6e%2Fimg-la-photos-1staff-470-2-1-8l631v8h.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5f24a1e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc0%2Fdf%2Ffdafc3ad20d400defed3f6b53d6e%2Fimg-la-photos-1staff-470-2-1-8l631v8h.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5b23d20/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc0%2Fdf%2Ffdafc3ad20d400defed3f6b53d6e%2Fimg-la-photos-1staff-470-2-1-8l631v8h.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2bc0766/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc0%2Fdf%2Ffdafc3ad20d400defed3f6b53d6e%2Fimg-la-photos-1staff-470-2-1-8l631v8h.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Irfan KhanLos Angeles Times A HOUSE BURNS Friday in Santa Clarita, where some residents described a markedly more frightening evacuation process because the states biggest utilities had ordered widespread public safety power shut-offs."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3f128fb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc0%2Fdf%2Ffdafc3ad20d400defed3f6b53d6e%2Fimg-la-photos-1staff-470-2-1-8l631v8h.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/135ac2b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc0%2Fdf%2Ffdafc3ad20d400defed3f6b53d6e%2Fimg-la-photos-1staff-470-2-1-8l631v8h.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/49b6bb8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc0%2Fdf%2Ffdafc3ad20d400defed3f6b53d6e%2Fimg-la-photos-1staff-470-2-1-8l631v8h.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9bd99f0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc0%2Fdf%2Ffdafc3ad20d400defed3f6b53d6e%2Fimg-la-photos-1staff-470-2-1-8l631v8h.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/00ef2b4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc0%2Fdf%2Ffdafc3ad20d400defed3f6b53d6e%2Fimg-la-photos-1staff-470-2-1-8l631v8h.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/00ef2b4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2400x1600+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc0%2Fdf%2Ffdafc3ad20d400defed3f6b53d6e%2Fimg-la-photos-1staff-470-2-1-8l631v8h.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">Irfan KhanLos Angeles Times A HOUSE BURNS Friday in Santa Clarita, where some residents described a markedly more frightening evacuation process because the states biggest utilities had ordered widespread public safety power shut-offs. </div><div class="figure-credit">(Irfan Khan/Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>It&#x27;s not just State Farm. Allstate no longer sells new home insurance policies in California</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">Fires</h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" >        Eliyahu Kamisher, Max Reyes and Biz Carson    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 2, 2023">June 2, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Californians looking to buy a house face some of the countrys most expensive real estate prices and wildfires that threaten scores of housing tracts. Now theres another obstacle: finding an insurer willing to cover their dream home.</p><p>State Farm General Insurance Co. said last week that its<a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-27/state-farm-is-no-longer-accepting-property-insurance-applications-in-california"> no longer accepting new applications</a> for property and casualty coverage in California because of soaring wildfire and construction costs and "a challenging reinsurance market."</p><p>Now, <a href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/california/article/insurance-allstate-fires-18130622.php" target="_blank">Allstate Corp.</a> has told the state Department of Insurance that it stopped selling new home insurance policies last year. The notice was part of a recent request for a nearly 40% rate increase for home and business property and casualty insurance.</p><p>The move by the two insurers  State Farm was <a href="https://www.insurance.ca.gov/01-consumers/120-company/04-mrktshare/2021/upload/Top25grps2021wa_Revised.pdf" target="_blank">California's largest property insurer </a>and Allstate was fourth as of 2021  could worsen what the FAIR Plan, a state-mandated insurance pool, has called an <a href="https://ains.assembly.ca.gov/sites/ains.assembly.ca.gov/files/FAIR%20Plan-Factsheet-2.23.23.pdf" target="_blank">impending insurance unavailability crisis.</a></p><p>We have a lot of people going naked, which means they have no insurance, said Bill Dodd, a Democratic state senator representing fire-scarred Napa County and other parts of Northern California. What my constituents want is insurance.</p> State Farm is no longer accepting property insurance applications in California<p>The FAIR Plan, </p> which<p> offers minimal coverage </p> at and<p> high rates</p> ,<p> is meant to be a provider of last resort, but enrollments have surged 70% since 2019 to 272,846 homes in 2022.</p><p>A series of catastrophic wildfires in recent years has increased calls from insurers to weaken the states consumer-friendly policies that have held down rates for decades.</p><p>The average California homeowner's </p> annual <p>insurance</p> policy premium <p>is $1,300, compared with more than $2,000 in other states with wildfire risk and $4,000 in hurricane-prone Florida, according to </p> the<p> Insurance Information Institute.</p><p>But new home buyers could be forced to pay more, regardless of their homes proximity to wildfire dangers. Before State Farms announcement, the company requested a 28% rate hike on homeowners' insurance; </p>, while<p> Allstate has filed for a 39.6% increase.</p><p>The insurance crunch is affecting buyers across the state already, even in areas where the wildfire risk is low. In San Francisco, real estate agents say they have seen deals fall through because would-be buyers couldnt get insured.</p> California to require insurance discounts for property owners who reduce wildfire risk<p>What were hearing is that now, when buyers present an offer on a property were not only asking them for pre-approval for a lender, were also asking them if theyve spoken to their insurance agent if theyll insure the property, said Joske Thompson, a broker at Compass Inc. with 40 years' experience in the area.</p><p>Home insurance is an essential </p> part step <p>of purchasing a home. Mortgage lenders generally require proof of insurance before approving the transaction to protect their investment in the property. Without insurance, buyers would be forced to make an all-cash purchase in most cases.</p><p>As the states insurance woes accelerate,<a href="https://consumerwatchdog.org/insurance/insurance-commissioner-lara-must-use-prop-103-authority-to-reverse-state-farms-pullback/" target="_blank"> the industry is taking aim </a>at Californias marquee consumer protection law, Proposition 103, a ballot measure voters approved in 1988. The law has saved consumers tens of billions of dollars in reduced insurance rate hikes, according to the states insurance regulator.</p><p>In the last six years, we lost 20 years worth of underwriting profit, and that was due to the catastrophic wildfires that weve faced, said Janet Ruiz, a spokesperson with the Insurance Information Institute.</p><p>Harvey Rosenfield, the author of Proposition 103 and founder of the advocacy group Consumer Watchdog, said climate change might require insurance companies to raise rates, but he argued that companies are using wildfire costs </p>impacts <p>to gouge customers.</p><p>Insurance companies are very opportunistic, he said. They have seized on climate change as an excuse to escape from the regulatory protections that voters enacted.</p>Kamisher, Reyes and Carson write for Bloomberg.                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>We chronicled one homeless woman’s motherhood journey since 2018</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-07-13/hollywoods-finest-pregnant-homeless-woman-how-we-reported</link>
      <description>We met a world of young homeless people above the 101 Freeway in Hollywood, many who had grown up in foster care and the juvenile detention systems.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 10:00:39 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-07-13/hollywoods-finest-pregnant-homeless-woman-how-we-reported</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
