<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Obituaries</title>
    <link>https://www.latimes.com/obituaries</link>
    <description>Obituaries</description>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 00:14:09 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.latimes.com/obituaries.rss" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" />
    <item>
      <title>James Watt, sharp-tongued and pro-development interior secretary under Reagan, dies at 85</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-08/james-watt-sharp-tongued-and-pro-development-interior-secretary-under-reagan-dies-at-85</link>
      <description>James Watt, the Reagan administration’s sharp-tongued, pro-development interior secretary, has died. He was 85.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 00:14:09 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>MEAD GRUVER</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-08/james-watt-sharp-tongued-and-pro-development-interior-secretary-under-reagan-dies-at-85</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-08/james-watt-sharp-tongued-and-pro-development-interior-secretary-under-reagan-dies-at-85">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7dea1bf/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/320x229!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1146681/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/568x406!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0dd9184/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/768x549!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d78b089/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/1024x732!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9c319dd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/1200x858!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="FILE - Interior Secretary nominee James Watt, a Reagan nominee on talks on Dec. 23, 1980 in Washington. Reagan administration Interior Secretary James Watt has died at age 85. Reagan administration Interior Secretary James Watt has died at age 85. Watt died in Arizona on May 27, 2023, son Eric Watt said in a statement Thursday, June 8. (AP Photo/Taylor, File)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7c01a54/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/320x229!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/39f525b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/568x406!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/33cb7b7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/768x549!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/cd3f1d9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/1024x732!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b3339a8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/1200x858!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="858"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b3339a8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/1200x858!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">FILE - Interior Secretary nominee James Watt, a Reagan nominee on talks on Dec. 23, 1980 in Washington. Reagan administration Interior Secretary James Watt has died at age 85. Reagan administration Interior Secretary James Watt has died at age 85. Watt died in Arizona on May 27, 2023, son Eric Watt said in a statement Thursday, June 8. (AP Photo/Taylor, File)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Taylor / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>James Watt, sharp-tongued and pro-development interior secretary under Reagan, dies at 85</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" >        MEAD GRUVER    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 8, 2023">June 8, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>James Watt, the Reagan administrations sharp-tongued, pro-development interior secretary who was beloved by conservatives but ran afoul of environmentalists, Beach Boys fans and eventually the president, has died. He was 85.</p><p>Watt died in Arizona on May 27, his son Eric Watt said in a statement Thursday.</p><p>In an administration divided between so-called pragmatists and hard-liners, few stood as far to the right at the time as Watt, who once labeled the environmental movement as preservation vs. people and the general public as a clash between liberals and Americans.</p><p>In that sense, Watt foreshadowed combative interior secretaries like Ryan Zinke and David Bernhardt, who, like Watt, aggressively pushed to grant oil, gas and coal leases on public land, increase offshore drilling and limit expansion of national parks and monuments. </p><p>While no ones death should be celebrated, he was the worst of MAGA before it was invented," tweeted David Donger of the environmental group Natural Resources Defense Council, referring to former President Trump's Make America Great Again slogan.</p><p>Watt and his supporters saw him as an upholder of President Reagans core conservative values, but opponents were alarmed by his policies and offended by his comments. In 1981, shortly after he was appointed, the Sierra Club collected more than 1 million signatures seeking Watts ouster and criticized such actions as clear-cutting federal lands in the Pacific Northwest, weakening environmental regulations for strip mining and hampering efforts to curtail air pollution in Californias Yosemite Valley.</p><p>With his bald head and thick glasses, he became the rare interior secretary recognizable to the general public, for reasons beyond the environment. He characterized members of a coal advisory panel using derogatory language and in 1983 tried to ban music from Fourth of July festivities on the National Mall, saying it attracted the wrong element.</p><p>The Beach Boys had been recent mall headliners, and their fans included President Reagan and First Lady Nancy Reagan. With Watts statement facing widespread mockery, the Reagans invited the Beach Boys for a special White House visit. Watt, meanwhile, was summoned to receive a plaster model of a foot with a hole in it.</p> Interior secretary seeks to rid U.S. of derogatory place names<p>In his 1985 book The Courage of a Conservative, Watt wrote that the controversy actually arose because I was a conservative. Members of a liberal press saw an opportunity to create a controversy by censoring the facts and avoiding the real issues. He said the initial stories about the rock music ban only mentioned that the Beach Boys had performed in the past. Yet before we knew what was happening, banner headlines proclaimed that I had banned the Beach Boys. I was astonished.</p><p>Cutting regulations was his primary mission. Between the time he was confirmed as interior secretary in 1981 until he resigned under pressure in 1983, Watt implemented an offshore leasing program that offered virtually the entire U.S. coastline for oil and gas drilling and held the largest coal lease sale in history, auctioning off 1.1 billion tons </p>(1 billion metric tons)<p> of coal in the Powder River Basin of Montana and Wyoming.</p><p>Watt tripled the amount of onshore land being leased for oil and gas exploration and doubled the acreage leased for geothermal resources.</p><p>Watt did spend $1 billion to restore and improve national parks and added 2,800 square miles </p>(7,300 square kilometers)<p> to the nations wilderness system. And his efforts to exploit natural resources made America stronger, he wrote to Reagan in October 1983.</p><p>Our excellent record for managing the natural resources of this land is unequaled  because we put people in the environmental equation, Watt wrote.</p><p>But eight days after writing to the president, he rode horseback into a cow pasture down the road from Reagans California ranch to announce his resignation. He was succeeded by a longtime Reagan aide, William Clark.</p><p>I had outworn my usefulness, Watt said of his decision, adding that others wouldn't get off my case about his insulting coal advisory panel comment.</p><p>Watt was born Jan. 31, 1938, in Lusk, Wyo., and his family later moved to Wheatland, Wyo., where his father practiced law. He attended the University of Wyoming, graduating in 1960 and obtaining a law degree two years later.</p> Interior Department adds $103 million for wildfire hazards and land rehabilitation<p>In 1962, Watt became a personal assistant to former Gov. Milward L. Simpson, and he went to Washington after Simpson was elected to the U.S. Senate later that year. In 1966-69, he helped develop policies on such issues as pollution, mining, public lands and energy for the U.S. Chamber of Commerce, then in early 1969 he joined the Nixon administration as an Interior Department undersecretary.</p><p>In 1975, President Ford appointed him to the Federal Power Commission.</p><p>While Jimmy Carter was president, Watt worked in the private sector as president and chief legal officer of the pro-development Mountain States Legal Foundation in Denver.</p><p>He did consulting work after leaving the Reagan administration, at one point turning heads when he agreed to represent </p>Indian Native American<p> tribes in oil operations and hotel developments after previously labeling </p>Indian Indigenous<p> reservations the failure of socialism. He also accepted six-figure consulting fees to represent developers of a federally subsidized housing project.</p><p>He moved back to Wyoming in 1986 and set up a law office in Jackson, taught at his alma mater and served as a legal consultant and speaker.</p><p>But his consulting work involving federal housing money came under scrutiny in the late 1980s when an investigation was launched into corruption in the Department of Housing and Urban Development.</p><p>In 1996, he pleaded guilty to a single misdemeanor for withholding documents from a grand jury investigating HUD. He was fined $5,000, put on five years probation and ordered to perform community service. He said he had made a serious mistake and hoped to get on with a constructive role in society.</p><p>Over the years, Watt expressed fears that unless they were stopped, radical environmental movements like Earth First! would persuade the cowards of Congress to ban all hunting, eliminate all logging and livestock grazing on public lands and further jeopardize the minerals industries.</p><p>He lived in his later years in Wickenburg, Ariz., with his wife, Leilani.</p>Associated Press writer Matthew Daly in Washington, D.C., contributed to this report.                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>After nearly 80 years of work, California's longest-serving state employee dies at 102</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-08/may-lee-dies-california-oldest-longest-serving-state-employee</link>
      <description>California's oldest and longest-serving state employee, May Lee, was a few weeks shy of her 103rd birthday when she died, a year after finishing nearly eight decades on the job.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 21:31:07 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Summer Lin</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-08/may-lee-dies-california-oldest-longest-serving-state-employee</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-08/may-lee-dies-california-oldest-longest-serving-state-employee">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b61936a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4779x3186+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F39%2F633124e146e0b0498a34d0c5db78%2Fap20175775489785.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/25f9b81/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4779x3186+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F39%2F633124e146e0b0498a34d0c5db78%2Fap20175775489785.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ca30014/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4779x3186+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F39%2F633124e146e0b0498a34d0c5db78%2Fap20175775489785.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b5c5863/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4779x3186+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F39%2F633124e146e0b0498a34d0c5db78%2Fap20175775489785.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2842e44/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4779x3186+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F39%2F633124e146e0b0498a34d0c5db78%2Fap20175775489785.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="May Lee, an employee for the California Department Of General Services, poses for a photo on her 100th birthday at the department&#x27;s headquarters in West Sacramento, Calif., Tuesday, June 23, 2020. Lee is California&#x27;s oldest and longest-serving state employee. She has worked for the state for more than 77 years, retiring in 1990 but continuing to work since then as a paid retiree who says she has not intention of quitting anytime soon. She returned to the building Tuesday for the first time in weeks, where fellow employees had initially planned a big birthday celebration until the coronavirus pandemic prompted many, including Lee, to work remotely. (AP Photo/Rich Pedroncelli)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/52a3dde/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4779x3186+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F39%2F633124e146e0b0498a34d0c5db78%2Fap20175775489785.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c2eb836/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4779x3186+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F39%2F633124e146e0b0498a34d0c5db78%2Fap20175775489785.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/241cf69/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4779x3186+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F39%2F633124e146e0b0498a34d0c5db78%2Fap20175775489785.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4bc2bf6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4779x3186+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F39%2F633124e146e0b0498a34d0c5db78%2Fap20175775489785.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/cb00970/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4779x3186+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F39%2F633124e146e0b0498a34d0c5db78%2Fap20175775489785.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/cb00970/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4779x3186+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F10%2F39%2F633124e146e0b0498a34d0c5db78%2Fap20175775489785.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">May Lee, an employee for the California Department Of General Services, poses for a photo on her 100th birthday at the departments headquarters in West Sacramento, Calif., Tuesday, June 23, 2020. Lee is Californias oldest and longest-serving state employee. She has worked for the state for more than 77 years, retiring in 1990 but continuing to work since then as a paid retiree who says she has not intention of quitting anytime soon. She returned to the building Tuesday for the first time in weeks, where fellow employees had initially planned a big birthday celebration until the coronavirus pandemic prompted many, including Lee, to work remotely. (AP Photo/Rich Pedroncelli)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Rich Pedroncelli/Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>After nearly 80 years of work, California&#x27;s longest-serving state employee dies at 102</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/summer-lin">        Summer Lin    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 8, 2023">June 8, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>California's oldest and longest-serving state employee </p> has<p> died at age 102 after nearly eight decades on the job. </p><p>May Lee was a few weeks shy of her </p>103rd <p>birthday when she died May 26, according to Jennifer Iida, a spokesperson for the California Department of General Services. Lee worked for the state for 79 years, starting in accounting at the Department of Finance in 1943, then switching </p>over <p>to the Department of General Services when it was created in 1963. </p>[please keep this in notes for now, trying to clarify whether this is department-specific or for all state employees] She was the first Chinese American employee when she was hired. <p>After retiring from the Department of General Services in the 1980s, Lee worked as a retired annuitant until last year, meaning she was rehired onto the payroll as a part-time worker while drawing retirement benefits. </p><p>"We will greatly miss her enthusiastic and cheerful disposition along with her irreplaceable institutional knowledge," Iida said in a statement. "She was an inspiration to us all." </p><p><a href="https://www.sandiegouniontribune.com/columnists/story/2021-07-03/column-may-lee-is-101-and-still-working-on-state-budgets" target="_blank">Lee was honored by Gov. Gavin Newsom</a> during Older Americans Month in 2019, when she was 99, for being the longest-serving state employee.</p> Pat Robertson, founder of Christian Broadcasting Network and Christian Coalition, dies<p>She was credited with saving millions of dollars through revenue-generating measures, finding accounting errors and cutting costs. She also wrote </p>multiple <p>sections of the California Government Code. </p><p>A relative of Lee's did not respond to a request for comment.</p><p>In a 2021 interview with the San Diego Union-Tribune, Lee said she would work until she could not anymore, pointing to her brother who worked until he died at age 85. </p><p>Her longevity was thanks to good genes and keeping busy, she told the Union-Tribune, adding that she maintained a healthy diet of fish, chicken, vegetables, very few processed foods and no fried foods.</p><p>A party for her 100th birthday with about 2,000 people invited was canceled by the COVID-19 pandemic.</p><p>The next year, colleagues took her out to lunch and brought a cake for her 101st birthday. It had </p>only <p>one candle, a symbol of the start of a new century.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pat Robertson, founder of Christian Broadcasting Network and Christian Coalition, dies</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/obituaries/story/2023-06-08/pat-robertson-dead</link>
      <description>Pat Robertson, who parlayed his TV ministry's success into the first serious bid by an evangelical leader for the U.S. presidency, has died.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2023 12:09:37 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Rebecca Trounson</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/obituaries/story/2023-06-08/pat-robertson-dead</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/obituaries/story/2023-06-08/pat-robertson-dead">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e49ab94/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4758x3354+0+0/resize/320x226!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F66%2F62%2F823a3a0c474586b61bdadc876eb3%2F9e359b8d1d164267902b3db858f2eb18.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5148cb2/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4758x3354+0+0/resize/568x400!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F66%2F62%2F823a3a0c474586b61bdadc876eb3%2F9e359b8d1d164267902b3db858f2eb18.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/07bf880/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4758x3354+0+0/resize/768x541!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F66%2F62%2F823a3a0c474586b61bdadc876eb3%2F9e359b8d1d164267902b3db858f2eb18.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6e8d83e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4758x3354+0+0/resize/1024x722!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F66%2F62%2F823a3a0c474586b61bdadc876eb3%2F9e359b8d1d164267902b3db858f2eb18.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2d99e05/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4758x3354+0+0/resize/1200x846!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F66%2F62%2F823a3a0c474586b61bdadc876eb3%2F9e359b8d1d164267902b3db858f2eb18.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="FILE - Rev. Pat Robertson poses a question to a Republican presidential candidate during a forum at Regent University in Virginia Beach, Va., Oct. 23, 2015. Robertson, a religious broadcaster who turned a tiny Virginia station into the global Christian Broadcasting Network, tried a run for president and helped make religion central to Republican Party politics in America through his Christian Coalition, has died. He was 93. Robertson&#x27;s death Thursday, June 8, 2023 was announced by his broadcasting network. (AP Photo/Steve Helber, File)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4779971/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4758x3354+0+0/resize/320x226!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F66%2F62%2F823a3a0c474586b61bdadc876eb3%2F9e359b8d1d164267902b3db858f2eb18.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b4ee5f0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4758x3354+0+0/resize/568x400!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F66%2F62%2F823a3a0c474586b61bdadc876eb3%2F9e359b8d1d164267902b3db858f2eb18.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/08bf7cd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4758x3354+0+0/resize/768x541!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F66%2F62%2F823a3a0c474586b61bdadc876eb3%2F9e359b8d1d164267902b3db858f2eb18.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2ec402a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4758x3354+0+0/resize/1024x722!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F66%2F62%2F823a3a0c474586b61bdadc876eb3%2F9e359b8d1d164267902b3db858f2eb18.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0f1ec08/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4758x3354+0+0/resize/1200x846!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F66%2F62%2F823a3a0c474586b61bdadc876eb3%2F9e359b8d1d164267902b3db858f2eb18.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="846"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0f1ec08/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4758x3354+0+0/resize/1200x846!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F66%2F62%2F823a3a0c474586b61bdadc876eb3%2F9e359b8d1d164267902b3db858f2eb18.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">FILE - Rev. Pat Robertson poses a question to a Republican presidential candidate during a forum at Regent University in Virginia Beach, Va., Oct. 23, 2015. Robertson, a religious broadcaster who turned a tiny Virginia station into the global Christian Broadcasting Network, tried a run for president and helped make religion central to Republican Party politics in America through his Christian Coalition, has died. He was 93. Robertsons death Thursday, June 8, 2023 was announced by his broadcasting network. (AP Photo/Steve Helber, File)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Steve Helber / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Pat Robertson, founder of Christian Broadcasting Network and Christian Coalition, dies</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" >        Rebecca Trounson    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 8, 2023">June 8, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Pat Robertson, the charismatic religious broadcaster who parlayed the success of his pioneering television ministry into the first serious bid by an evangelical leader for the U.S. presidency, then launched the influential Christian Coalition advocacy group, has died. He was 93.</p><p>Robertson's death Thursday was announced by his broadcasting network. No cause was given.</p><p>The founder of the Christian Broadcasting Network and host of its enormously popular, long-running program, The 700 Club</p> ,<p>" had suffered a stroke in 2018.</p><p>A former Southern Baptist minister who said God had inspired him to run for president, Robertson made a strong start in his campaign for the 1988 Republican nomination, stunning better-known opponents, including Vice President George H.W. Bush, the eventual nominee, by finishing near the top in Iowa and other early contests.</p><p>Although poor showings in later primaries soon forced him to withdraw, Robertsons campaign became a political springboard. In 1989, he founded the Christian Coalition, which gave conservative Christians a voice in the nations capital and helped turn the religious right into a well-organized political movement.</p><p>He saw the possibilities, said Laura R. Olson, a Clemson University political science professor and expert on religion and politics. </p>as of 7/22<p> Pat Robertson was absolutely brilliant at taking his success from the presidential race and transforming that into a powerful interest group.</p><p>A Yale law school graduate and son of a U.S. senator, Robertson had the education, media skills and political experience to build on the foundation laid by another group with conservative Christian roots.</p><p>In 1979, the Rev. Jerry Falwell founded the Moral Majority, which rallied once-apolitical fundamentalist and evangelical Christians into an electoral force. By 1989, amid lackluster fundraising, it was disbanded and the Christian Coalition was born.</p><p>A fundamentalist preacher like Falwell, Robertson urged Christian conservatives to fight what he saw as Americas drift toward moral decay. He pointed to legalized abortion, homosexuality and AIDS, as well as government policies he saw as anti-family and anti-God.</p><p>But the approach favored by Robertson and Ralph Reed, the political activist he hired to run the Christian Coalition, was more sophisticated than the often-blistering attacks of Falwell, creating a more polished style of Christian conservatism. Robertson took what Falwell created, refined it and ensured that it continued, Olson said.</p><p>With an army of fervent followers, Robertson and his grassroots coalition promoted conservative Christian candidates and traditional values across the U.S. By 1995, the group claimed 1.6 million members in 1,600 chapters. The following year, its financial peak, it took in contributions of nearly $25 million.</p><p>Enthusiastic and informal  viewers and most others knew him simply as Pat  Robertson shot to fame in the 1970s as the host of The 700 Club, a groundbreaking religious variety show that aired daily on his Christian Broadcasting Network.</p><p>He combined evangelistic fervor with a comfortable on-air style that drew comparisons to the most popular talk show hosts of the day, including Johnny Carson and Merv Griffin.</p><p>Mixing news with music, a call-in advice segment and interviews with key religious and political figures, the 700 Club made Robertson a familiar face across the U.S. By the 1980s, the Christian Broadcasting Network, the media empire he built from his 1959 purchase of a single Virginia television station, reached about 30 million homes and grossed more than $200 million a year.</p><p>He appealed to a rising middle class among evangelicals, said John C. Green, senior fellow at the Pew Forum on Religion and Public Life. </p>true as of 7/22<p>Yet Robertson, known for his business and political acumen, also had a history of incendiary remarks that repeatedly thrust him into the headlines, particularly in his later years.</p><p>In 2005, he called on the U.S. to assassinate Venezuelas leftist president, Hugo Chavez, saying it would be a whole lot cheaper than starting a war. A few months later, he suggested that the massive stroke suffered by Israeli Prime Minister Ariel Sharon was divine retribution for dividing Gods land, ceding Gaza to the Palestinians. He later apologized for the statements.</p><p>The comments, and many others, brought strong criticism  and jokes from late-night talk show hosts.</p><p>A tendency to shoot from the hip was not new for Robertson, who declared in 1992 that feminism caused women to leave their husbands, kill their children, practice witchcraft, destroy capitalism and become lesbians.</p><p>He later said such comments were the result of impulsive tendencies. My passion runs ahead of me , he told ABCs Good Morning America in 2006. The problem is, I ad lib.</p><p>Marion Gordon Robertson was born March 22, 1930, in Lexington, Va., the younger of two sons in a Southern family steeped in politics and religion. He was nicknamed Pat by his older brother.</p><p>His father, Absalom Willis Robertson, served 34 years in Congress. His mother, the former Gladys Churchill Willis, was deeply religious, and later influenced her younger son to devote his life to God. Both his grandfathers were Baptist clergymen.</p><p>After high school at an elite academy in Tennessee, he graduated in 1950 with a bachelors degree in history from Virginias Washington and Lee University. He studied economics in London before joining the Marine Corps and serving two years during the Korean War, leaving with the rank of lieutenant. </p><p>In 1986, as Robertson was mulling a presidential run, former Rep. Pete McCloskey Jr. (R-San Mateo), who served in Korea and knew him there, released a letter saying Robertson had used his fathers influence to avoid combat duty. Robertson sued for libel, but later dropped the suit and agreed to pay McCloskeys court costs.</p><p>In 1955, Robertson earned a law degree from Yale, but failed the bar and never practiced. At Yale, he met Adelia Elmer, a nursing student known as Dede, and they married in 1954. They had four children, Timothy, Elizabeth, Gordon and Ann, all </p> of<p> who</p> m<p> survive him. <a href="https://www.latimes.com/obituaries/story/2022-04-20/dede-robertson-wife-of-televangelist-and-presidential-candidate-pat-robertson-dies">His wife died </a>in 2022</p> after battling cancer<p>. </p>doublecheck<p>It was during a brief business career, while he and his wife were living in New York City, that Robertson first felt what he would call a God-shaped vacuum in his life. I was so burdened with the futility of life that at one point I actually considered suicide, he wrote in Shout It From the Housetops, his 1972 autobiography.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/5a/21/222028994f7a80101b016af25370/obit-dede-roberson-56441.jpg"></figure><p>After meeting with a Baptist evangelist sent by his mother, Robertson said he had a born-again experience and rushed home to tell his stunned wife that he had been saved. He enrolled at New York Theological Seminary, earning a masters degree in divinity in 1959.</p><p>Although he was soon an ordained Southern Baptist minister  he resigned when he ran for president  Robertson embraced the charismatic movement, characterized by a personal relationship with God and a belief in faith-healing, prophesy and the ability to speak in tongues.</p><p>Through his ministry, Robertson claimed credit for healing illnesses and even diverting natural disasters. In 1986, he said on the air that the previous year, he had prayed away Hurricane Gloria, which skipped his home base of Virginia Beach, Va., but slammed into North Carolina and later Long Island.</p><p>Robertson often said God gave him personal guidance, including directing him in 1959 to buy the TV station he used to create his religious channel, the nations first. He then had the idea of asking 700 viewers to pledge $10 a month to meet the stations monthly expenses, which became the basis for the 700 Club show. He was also a pioneer in the use of satellite transmissions to cable television systems.</p><p>In 1980, concerned about a lack of wholesome programming elsewhere, he bought the rights to old TV series, including </p>W<p>westerns and family-friendly shows such as Father Knows Best, which helped expand the Christian Broadcasting Networks viewership. Its family entertainment arm was eventually spun off and in 1997, sold to Fox Kids for a reported $1.9 billion, and later to Disney.</p><p>Among his other enterprises were Regent University, a Christian </p>U<p>university in Virginia Beach with graduate programs and an accredited law school, and Operation Blessing, a global charity.</p><p>Robertson was edging toward politics by the early 1980s, focusing on national and global issues on The 700 Club. I have always thought that Christians should get involved in public life, he told the Chicago Tribune in 1985.</p><p>When he ran for president, he shared much of the agenda of other Republicans seeking the nomination. But, moved by what he saw as the nations moral decline, he went beyond what then was the standard conservative line.</p><p>He not only called for measures against abortion, but tax breaks for stable family units, in which mothers stayed home with their children. He offered ringing endorsements of school prayer, implying it would ease the problems of illiteracy and drug use. And he said landlords should be able to discriminate without criminal penalty against people with AIDS.</p><p>With strong donations and dedicated volunteers, Robertson finished second in Iowas GOP caucuses to Kansas Sen. Bob Dole, with Bush coming in third. He did well in several other states but poorly in New Hampshire and the Super Tuesday primaries. He withdrew soon afterward</p>s<p>, endorsing Bush, who went on to win the presidency.</p><p>Armed with a database of thousands of donors and supporters, he founded the Christian Coalition the next year. As the group gained political clout, Robertson was invited to the White House and Capitol Hill. In 1995, he was on the cover of U.S. News </p>and  &amp;<p> World Report for a story about the power of the religious right.</p><p>But the influence of the Christian Coalition  and Robertson  soon began to fade. Reed stepped down in 1997 and the coalition struggled with financial and other problems. In 2001, Robertson resigned too, both as president and from the coalitions board, saying he wanted to focus on other interests. By then, the organization was in debt.</p><p>Robertson continued to appear on The 700 Club into his 90s, although his son Gordon, appointed chief executive officer of CBN in 2007, became the programs primary host. Robertson retired in 2021.</p><p>By 2006, after </p> his<p> increasingly provocative statements, old allies and friends in the evangelical movement began to distance themselves. He speaks for an ever-diminishing number of American evangelicals, said Richard Land, president of the Southern Evangelical Seminary. </p>As of 7/22<p>But Robertson was undaunted and continued to speak out, whether it was to blame the destructive nature of storms or hurricanes on the LGBTQ community or </p> to make<p> wild predictions, such as his forecast that asteroids would soon destroy Earth. He cheered Donald Trump's election but later said he found the president "very erratic" and someone who "lives in an alternate reality."</p><p>Some analysts suggested Robertson was simply dialing up his rhetoric in an attempt to reclaim his position as the face of the religious right.</p><p>As his influence waned and the movement diversified, Olson said, maybe he was trying to insert himself back into a position of relevance.</p>Trounson is a former Times staff writer.                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>George Winston, million-selling new age pianist, dies at age 73</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/music/story/2023-06-07/george-winston-new-age-pianist-dead-73</link>
      <description>The Grammy-winning musician had been battling cancer for a decade.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 17:23:34 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/music/story/2023-06-07/george-winston-new-age-pianist-dead-73</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/music/story/2023-06-07/george-winston-new-age-pianist-dead-73">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ae1e951/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2578x2000+0+0/resize/320x248!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fd4%2F18eff68af914924c1bd7947081af%2F409cc946e7d848c6884c3956f5cf0d08 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/11af164/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2578x2000+0+0/resize/568x441!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fd4%2F18eff68af914924c1bd7947081af%2F409cc946e7d848c6884c3956f5cf0d08 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/fd6dde9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2578x2000+0+0/resize/768x596!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fd4%2F18eff68af914924c1bd7947081af%2F409cc946e7d848c6884c3956f5cf0d08 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b4e006e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2578x2000+0+0/resize/1024x794!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fd4%2F18eff68af914924c1bd7947081af%2F409cc946e7d848c6884c3956f5cf0d08 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a5f6fc1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2578x2000+0+0/resize/1200x931!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fd4%2F18eff68af914924c1bd7947081af%2F409cc946e7d848c6884c3956f5cf0d08 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="FILE - George Winston makes an adjustment on his piano during a sound check before his performance at the Cerritos Center for the Performing Arts in Cerritos, Calif., on Nov. 4, 2004. Winston, the Grammy-winning pianist who blended jazz, classical, folk and other stylings on such million-selling albums as Autumn, Winter Into Spring and December, died Sunday, June 4, 2023, after a 10-year battle with cancer. He was 73. (AP Photo/Reed Saxon, File)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c6416f8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2578x2000+0+0/resize/320x248!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fd4%2F18eff68af914924c1bd7947081af%2F409cc946e7d848c6884c3956f5cf0d08 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6f082db/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2578x2000+0+0/resize/568x441!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fd4%2F18eff68af914924c1bd7947081af%2F409cc946e7d848c6884c3956f5cf0d08 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/57c07b0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2578x2000+0+0/resize/768x596!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fd4%2F18eff68af914924c1bd7947081af%2F409cc946e7d848c6884c3956f5cf0d08 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/eeaea30/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2578x2000+0+0/resize/1024x794!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fd4%2F18eff68af914924c1bd7947081af%2F409cc946e7d848c6884c3956f5cf0d08 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e9c4ed3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2578x2000+0+0/resize/1200x931!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fd4%2F18eff68af914924c1bd7947081af%2F409cc946e7d848c6884c3956f5cf0d08 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="931"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e9c4ed3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2578x2000+0+0/resize/1200x931!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fd4%2F18eff68af914924c1bd7947081af%2F409cc946e7d848c6884c3956f5cf0d08"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">FILE - George Winston makes an adjustment on his piano during a sound check before his performance at the Cerritos Center for the Performing Arts in Cerritos, Calif., on Nov. 4, 2004. Winston, the Grammy-winning pianist who blended jazz, classical, folk and other stylings on such million-selling albums as Autumn, Winter Into Spring and December, died Sunday, June 4, 2023, after a 10-year battle with cancer. He was 73. (AP Photo/Reed Saxon, File)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Reed Saxon / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>George Winston, million-selling new age pianist, dies at age 73</h1>                                                                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 7, 2023">June 7, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>George Winston, the Grammy-winning pianist who blended jazz, classical, folk and other stylings on such million-selling albums as Autumn, Winter Into Spring" and December, has died at age 73.</p><p>According to an announcement on his website www.georgewinston.com, confirmed by a spokesman, Winston died Sunday after a 10-year battle with cancer. </p><p>Throughout his cancer treatments, George continued to write and record new music, and he stayed true to his greatest passion: performing for live audiences while raising funds for Feeding America to help fight the national hunger crisis along with donating proceeds from each of his concerts to local food banks, a statement on his website reads.</p><p>His most recent album, Night, came out last year.</p> 32 best recording studios (for every budget) in Southern California<p>Winston was a native of Hart, Mich.</p>igan<p>, who grew up in Montana, Florida and Mississippi and drew upon influences ranging from Fats Waller to the Doors. He released more than a dozen solo piano albums, along with soundtracks for the TV miniseries This Is America, Charlie Brown and The Velveteen Rabbit, which featured Meryl Streep's narration of the children's classic. His 1995 release Forest won a Grammy for best New Age recording, while his Doors tribute Night Divides the Day received a Grammy nomination in 2004 for best contemporary instrumental album.</p><p>I came up with the melodic style that I play in 1971, and I have always called it Folk Piano, [or more accurately Rural Folk Piano], since it is melodic and not complicated in its approach, like folk guitar picking and folk songs, and has a rural sensibility, reads a quote from a Q &amp; A section on his website.</p><p>I just play the songs the best I can, inspired by the seasons and the topographies and regions, and, occasionally, by sociological elements, and try to improve as a player over time.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tina Turner, a rock star for the ages, shouldn't be defined just by what she endured</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/music/story/2023-05-24/tina-turner-dies-whats-love-got-to-do-with-it-proud-mary</link>
      <description>As she put it night after night singing 'Proud Mary': 'I never lost one minute of sleeping worrying about the way that things might have been.'</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 02:58:24 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Mikael Wood</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/music/story/2023-05-24/tina-turner-dies-whats-love-got-to-do-with-it-proud-mary</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/music/story/2023-05-24/tina-turner-dies-whats-love-got-to-do-with-it-proud-mary">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/22d5072/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5489x3280+0+0/resize/320x191!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F89%2F72%2F69a376cd4d26b5eb8b38f25fb8e9%2Fhttps-delivery-gettyimages.com%2Fdownloads%2F110058731 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b94726e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5489x3280+0+0/resize/568x339!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F89%2F72%2F69a376cd4d26b5eb8b38f25fb8e9%2Fhttps-delivery-gettyimages.com%2Fdownloads%2F110058731 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/168be16/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5489x3280+0+0/resize/768x459!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F89%2F72%2F69a376cd4d26b5eb8b38f25fb8e9%2Fhttps-delivery-gettyimages.com%2Fdownloads%2F110058731 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/81035eb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5489x3280+0+0/resize/1024x612!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F89%2F72%2F69a376cd4d26b5eb8b38f25fb8e9%2Fhttps-delivery-gettyimages.com%2Fdownloads%2F110058731 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6b7238b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5489x3280+0+0/resize/1200x717!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F89%2F72%2F69a376cd4d26b5eb8b38f25fb8e9%2Fhttps-delivery-gettyimages.com%2Fdownloads%2F110058731 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="LONDON - 1st APRIL: Tina Turner performs live on stage at Hammersmith Odeon in London in April 1982. (Photo by Fin Costello/Redferns)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7b17dac/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5489x3280+0+0/resize/320x191!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F89%2F72%2F69a376cd4d26b5eb8b38f25fb8e9%2Fhttps-delivery-gettyimages.com%2Fdownloads%2F110058731 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/adf7bc5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5489x3280+0+0/resize/568x339!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F89%2F72%2F69a376cd4d26b5eb8b38f25fb8e9%2Fhttps-delivery-gettyimages.com%2Fdownloads%2F110058731 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d837871/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5489x3280+0+0/resize/768x459!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F89%2F72%2F69a376cd4d26b5eb8b38f25fb8e9%2Fhttps-delivery-gettyimages.com%2Fdownloads%2F110058731 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4d4236a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5489x3280+0+0/resize/1024x612!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F89%2F72%2F69a376cd4d26b5eb8b38f25fb8e9%2Fhttps-delivery-gettyimages.com%2Fdownloads%2F110058731 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0e20db7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5489x3280+0+0/resize/1200x717!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F89%2F72%2F69a376cd4d26b5eb8b38f25fb8e9%2Fhttps-delivery-gettyimages.com%2Fdownloads%2F110058731 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="717"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0e20db7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5489x3280+0+0/resize/1200x717!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F89%2F72%2F69a376cd4d26b5eb8b38f25fb8e9%2Fhttps-delivery-gettyimages.com%2Fdownloads%2F110058731"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">LONDON - 1st APRIL: Tina Turner performs live on stage at Hammersmith Odeon in London in April 1982. (Photo by Fin Costello/Redferns)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Fin Costello / Redferns)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Tina Turner, a rock star for the ages, shouldn&#x27;t be defined just by what she endured</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/mikael-wood">        Mikael Wood    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="May 24, 2023">May 24, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Think of it as rock n rolls original spoiler alert.</p><p>Sermonizing in her low, throaty croon as her husband Ike Turner strums an electric guitar, Tina Turner famously introduces the couples indelible 1971 recording of Proud Mary by informing the listener, Every now and then, I think you might like to hear something from us, nice and easy. Theres just one thing, she adds. You see, we never, ever  in her telling, the words are more like nevah, evah  do nothing nice and easy. We always do it nice and rough. Pause for effect. But were gonna take the beginning of this song and do it easy. Another beat.</p><p>But then were gonna do the finish  </p>rough<p>.</p> Tina Turner, resilient star who sang 'Proud Mary' and 'What's Love Got to Do With It,' dies<p>Did this little spiel, a version of which Turner would go on to deliver for decades every time she did Proud Mary in concert, ever </p> prevent anyone from being bowled over<p> when she got to the rough part? Unlikely. Thats how volcanic Turners performance of Proud Mary was, particularly onstage, where shed turn the Creedence Clearwater Revival tune into a shaking, shimmying soul-rock rave-up that made you half-expect the fringe to come flying off her sparkly mini-dress.</p><p>Watch any of the dozens of live Proud Marys on YouTube, and what youll be struck by  beyond her mastery of tone and timing  is how gloriously sweaty the singer is by the end, as though the effort shed put into the song had come as a surprise even to her (or at least to her body). Yet there shed be the next time she sang it, trying to warn everybody about what was coming before flipping wigs all over again.</p> https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hzQnPz6TpGc&amp;ab_channel=Beat-Club<p>Turner, who died Wednesday at age 83, lived a life that defied expectation. She made it through a hardscrabble childhood in rural Tennessee to become a dynamo of 60s R&amp;B in a duo with Ike, whose horrific abuse she survived to reinvent herself as one of the biggest solo acts of the 80s; she toured the world until she was almost 70, then retired in 2009 without going back on it like virtually every other pop star in history.</p><p>Her story is one of resilience, no doubt  Basically, the message is determination, she told The Times in 1996  yet she wasnt defined by what shed endured; instead, she found new ways to thrive.</p><p>As she put it night after night in that borrowed song about rolling on the river: I never lost one minute of sleeping worrying about the way that things might have been.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/78/85/df46ce7d4f3b9c4ba3ed98e42a52/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/1182295694"></figure><p>Born Anna Mae Bullock and raised in tiny Nutbush, Tenn., Turner made her name  the one Ike gave her without asking  as the electrifying star attraction of her and her husbands revue. Her first single as lead vocalist, 1960s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0ky_Y1v94rM&amp;ab_channel=grooveaddict" target="_blank">A Fool in Love</a>, is staggeringly raw: She growls, howls and grunts over a rollicking groove that bounces and thumps like a hand-me-down coach rattling toward the next gig. The voice is powerful but haunted by the knowledge that behind Turner looms her tormentor. Listen to the couples <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Rj9Um8T88KM&amp;ab_channel=tioquety" target="_blank">Its Gonna Work Out Fine</a>, a No. 2 R&amp;B and top 20 pop hit in 1961, in which she refers to Ike as thriller, only to have him correct her: The killer, honey.</p><p>The vision was Ikes but the emotional energy derived from Tina  one reason producer Phil Spector (who abused his wife Ronnie Spector much the way Ike did Tina) sought to cut Ike out of the recording of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uj0wPrN_Y_4&amp;ab_channel=amajor2002" target="_blank">River Deep  Mountain High</a>, the quasi-operatic 1966 single that showed a more melodic side of her singing and helped endear Turner to a generation of white British rockers including the Rolling Stones, who promptly took Ike </p>&amp; and <p>Tina on the road.</p><p>The cross-pollination proved a win-win: Mick Jagger learned to dance, more or less, by observing the full-body physicality of Turners movement, while Tina got access to a trove of rock tunes  the Stones <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sTM17bmV4wg&amp;ab_channel=Beat-Club" target="_blank">Honky Tonk Women</a> and the Beatles <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yqAkdxjneig&amp;ab_channel=DownInNutbush" target="_blank">Come Together</a> among them  that shed go on happily to make her own. In 1973, she wrote a great one herself: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=I07249JX8w4&amp;ab_channel=Musikladen" target="_blank">Nutbush City Limits</a>, a stomping and funky soul-rock jam about her rural upbringing.</p><p>Turner left Ike three years later but not without the name shed turned into a brand. I felt I had earned it, she told Spin magazine in 1990. That name Tina opened doors. That name went my on drivers license and passport. That was my heritage from all the money that was taken away from me.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/b2/5a/49710126496c84c8ee48968cf285/et-tina-turner-gettyimages-020.JPG"></figure><p>The beginning of her solo career was bumpy; she made records with unclear ideas about where she wanted to fit into the world. But to see Tina Turner in person was still to be wowed by her live-wire intensity. Watch Rod Stewart, another of her admirers, bring her out by surprise to do <a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=848296222627003" target="_blank">Hot Legs</a> on Saturday Night Live in 1981. Hes wearing a shiny pink suit, yet shes the one you cant keep your eyes off.</p><p>Teamed with a new manager, Roger Davies, Turner found her lane at age 45 with 1984s Private Dancer, which set her gritty vocals against gleaming electro-pop arrangements. Thats not to say the songs were fluff: In <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d4QnalIHlVc&amp;ab_channel=TinaTurner" target="_blank">the title track</a>, written by Mark Knopfler of Dire Straits, a sex worker describes the numbing monotony of her job; Whats Love Got to Do with It, a Grammy winner for both record and song of the year, wonders, Who needs a heart when a heart can be broken?</p><p>Yet the fortitude in Turners singing  the sense that here was a woman whod chosen to look at hard things because she knew </p> she<p> was capable of it  made a commercial smash of the album, which sold 5 million copies in the U.S. alone and established Turners lions-mane hairdo as one of the iconic looks of the 1980s.</p><p>If you havent seen it in a while, revisit the music video for Whats Love Got to Do With It; the extreme close-ups feel almost radical in how unflinching they are, as though shes daring us to hold her gaze.</p> https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oGpFcHTxjZs&amp;ab_channel=TinaTurner<p>That comfort onscreen led to a star acting turn in 1985s Mad Max Beyond Thunderdome, and the hit records continued for the rest of the 80s. Im just using my female attraction on a typical male, she sang, hilariously, over a thwacking Phil Collins drum beat in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3JH28-aDfXY&amp;ab_channel=TinaTurner-Topic" target="_blank">Typical Male</a>; <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GC5E8ie2pdM&amp;ab_channel=TinaTurner" target="_blank">The Best</a> followed a few years later, its inspirational message already destined for countless sports-highlight reels (though, as usual, Turner cut the songs optimism with a cold splash of reality: Tear us apart / Baby, I would rather be dead).</p><p>She spent the final decades of her career as a top-grossing live act, thrilling audiences with the routines shed long since perfected and scooping up lifetime-achievement awards including a Kennedy Center Honor and an induction into the Rock &amp; Roll Hall of Fame. Her dramatic life story became fodder for, among other things, a biopic starring Angela Bassett, a Broadway stage musical and an <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/movies/story/2021-03-26/review-tina-turner-documentary-music-hbo">HBO documentary</a> for which she was interviewed in Switzerland, where she moved in 1995.</p> 10 hidden Tina Turner gems that hold their own against her hits<p>Who might we say has carried on Turners musical legacy? Certainly Beyonc, whos further explored the indelible ties between singing and dancing and who posted a note to Turner on her website in which she said she was so grateful for your inspiration and all the ways you have paved the way. Among the other celebrity testimonials that surfaced Wednesday was one from former President </p>Barack <p>Obama, who said Turner was unapologetically herself  speaking and singing her truth through joy and pain; triumph and tragedy.</p><p>You could hear that commitment to the truth in the work of Amy Winehouse; you could hear the conversation between rock and soul in Janet Jacksons music from the late 80s. But its easy to wonder whether Turners precise type of pop stardom may have died with her. These days rawness and finesse seem to exist at opposite ends of a spectrum. Turner embodied both for her entire life.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making tamales with Gloria Molina and other stories</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-15/column-making-tamales-with-gloria-molina-and-other-stories</link>
      <description>The eulogies are coming in for pioneering Chicana politician Gloria Molina, who died Sunday night — Mother’s Day — after a three-year battle with cancer.</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 19:05:16 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Gustavo Arellano</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-15/column-making-tamales-with-gloria-molina-and-other-stories</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-05-15/column-making-tamales-with-gloria-molina-and-other-stories">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4a9eb7a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1277+0+0/resize/320x227!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff5%2Ffa%2F16d13761417da3c889bc0cee510b%2Fgloria-molina-life-0014.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7309583/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1277+0+0/resize/568x403!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff5%2Ffa%2F16d13761417da3c889bc0cee510b%2Fgloria-molina-life-0014.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ac116ca/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1277+0+0/resize/768x545!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff5%2Ffa%2F16d13761417da3c889bc0cee510b%2Fgloria-molina-life-0014.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4d5267b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1277+0+0/resize/1024x726!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff5%2Ffa%2F16d13761417da3c889bc0cee510b%2Fgloria-molina-life-0014.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b2a8277/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1277+0+0/resize/1200x851!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff5%2Ffa%2F16d13761417da3c889bc0cee510b%2Fgloria-molina-life-0014.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Los Angeles County Supervisor Gloria Molina, Wednesday dedicated the East Los Angeles City Hall before hundreds of residents and local politicans with music and speeches. January 31, 2007"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ec471a4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1277+0+0/resize/320x227!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff5%2Ffa%2F16d13761417da3c889bc0cee510b%2Fgloria-molina-life-0014.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/400d032/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1277+0+0/resize/568x403!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff5%2Ffa%2F16d13761417da3c889bc0cee510b%2Fgloria-molina-life-0014.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/278b23d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1277+0+0/resize/768x545!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff5%2Ffa%2F16d13761417da3c889bc0cee510b%2Fgloria-molina-life-0014.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2819d41/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1277+0+0/resize/1024x726!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff5%2Ffa%2F16d13761417da3c889bc0cee510b%2Fgloria-molina-life-0014.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7957765/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1277+0+0/resize/1200x851!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff5%2Ffa%2F16d13761417da3c889bc0cee510b%2Fgloria-molina-life-0014.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="851"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7957765/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1277+0+0/resize/1200x851!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff5%2Ffa%2F16d13761417da3c889bc0cee510b%2Fgloria-molina-life-0014.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Los Angeles County Supervisor Gloria Molina, Wednesday dedicated the East Los Angeles City Hall before hundreds of residents and local politicans with music and speeches. January 31, 2007</div><div class="figure-credit">(Carlos Chavez/Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Making tamales with Gloria Molina and other stories</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">California Politics ,L.A. Politics </h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/gustavo-arellano">        Gustavo Arellano    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="May 15, 2023">May 15, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>The eulogies are coming in for pioneering Chicana politician Gloria Molina, who died </p>  Sunday<p> night  Mothers Day  after a three-year battle with cancer. She was 74.</p><p>The longtime L.A. County supervisor <a href="https://www.latimes.com/obituaries/story/2023-05-14/gloria-molina-dead">is rightfully being remembered as a trailblazer</a> many times over: for women, for Latinos, for the Eastside. There will be more tributes in the weeks and months to come, Im sure.</p><p>As we place her in the pantheon of L.A. political legends, though, I think she would be the first person to quote Dorothy Day, co-founder of the Catholic Worker movement:</p> "<p>Dont call me a saint. I dont want to be dismissed so easily.</p> "<p>Those who knew Molina best told me about her many political accomplishments. But they also shared anecdote after anecdote about the Gloria they loved: Someone<a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-03-14/gloria-molina-legacy-column"> who was as sharp-tongued as she was big-hearted</a>. A selfless taskmaster. A mother hen who pecked when necessary but more often took everyone under her wing. </p><p>That flesh-and-blood Gloria, they insisted, should be remembered just as much as the political Gloria. That way, the public would forever know she was one of them.</p><p>Antonia Hernandez, an icon in her own right because of the 1989 voting rights lawsuit she filed while lead counsel for the Mexican American Legal Defense and Education Fund that helped Molina become a councilmember and supervisor, told me about the vacations the two of them took with longtime friends. Their circle included lawyers, U.S. ambassadors, businesswomen and other fellow powerhouses.</p><p>But one time, we all go down to Baja, Hernandez said. She got her quilting friends, they took their sewing machines, and quilted for three or four days. No pretension at all. You think of Gloria as this professional leader, but theres a side of her thats traditional and homey that totally informed her politics.</p><p>Another time, the two were in a market in Oaxaca</p> , Mexico,<p> when Molina saw a woman sewing patterns on a dress. She looked at me and said, This is fascinating,  Hernandez said. Then she went to the </p>mujer<p> and said, If I pay you, can I sit here and watch you so I can do it? We told her, Gloria, we have to go. But she wouldnt leave. She was determined, and she learned the pattern.</p><p>Supervisor Kathryn Barger knew Molina for almost 30 years, going back to the days when she served as chief of staff for former supervisor and frequent Molina adversary Mike Antonovich. We were always jealous of her team, Barger said. When we did Christmas lunches for our staff, we made reservations. When she did it, she opened up her home for days. Our team would tell me, Why are we going to a Chinese restaurant when her staff is going to her house for amazing food?</p><p>The tamales stuck with her, because Barger mentioned it to Molina one year in passing while the latter was still supervisor. She suddenly said, Come to my office.' She had made the filling from scratch, had the corn husks. And we start doing tamales right there and then.</p><p>Former L.A. councilmember Joy Picus was a key early supporter of Molina's first campaign back in 1982, for an Eastside Assembly seat. When Molina announced in 1987 she was going to run for City Council, Picus immediately endorsed her and volunteered to make phone calls and knock on doors in Boyle Heights.</p><p>Well, when I did that, I realized that most of the people I had to talk to only spoke Spanish, Picus said. So I was no help at all.</p><p>Until she was.</p><p>One morning before a meeting, Gloria was speaking to a journalist and asked me, Joy, whats the Spanish word for bridge? Picus said. And I thought, Youre asking me? I closed my eyes, and said </p>puente<p>? And we both laughed hard!</p><p>Few took more of Molina's barbs than former Mayor Antonio Villaraigosa, who was best man at her wedding and described himself as Gloria's little brother.</p><p>Once I became speaker and once I became mayor, I almost became the big brother, Villaraigosa said. But I still wasn't the big brother. Instead of trying to talk to me about [things], she was raising her voice, talking down to me. After that, Id call Alma [Martinez, Molinas longtime chief of staff] and say, Man, she's a piece of work. I want to help her. I'm going to help her. But she wont let me talk. </p><p>Six months before he left office, Molina told Villaraigosa she wanted to honor him at LA Plaza de Cultura y Arte</p> s<p> first gala. It seemed so incongruous after the way she always treated me, he said. But when he showed up, every table had a booklet about his life and a mini-shoebox to commemorate one of his first jobs.</p><p>It was very emotional, it was a big surprise. It was typical Gloria.</p><p>Martinez's Molina memory dated to 1976, when she and some of her classmates at Sacred Heart of Mary High School in Montebello volunteered for Jimmy Carters presidential run, for which Molina headed Latino outreach. During an event in Hollywood, she tasked Henry Lozano, a legendary Eastside consigliere to politicians, to get dinner for Martinez and other volunteers.</p><p>He was supposed to bring good food, but he brought something ridiculous, Martinez said. Gloria was like, What, you didnt bring anything warm and nice? Go get something better for these chickies. She would not accept the fact that there was not going to have properly fed volunteers."</p><p>Molina wasnt as persnickety in her own life. In 2009, Molina and about a dozen of her family members traveled to Washington, D.C.</p> ,<p> for Barack Obama's inauguration. We got one of those big passenger vans from Rent-a-Wreck, and the windows were held down with duct tape, said Bertha Molina Mejia, Glorias sister. She drove  if youre in the car with her, shes always the driver.</p><p>They headed to one of the presidential balls, and Molinas family begged her not to park their van with the valet. She ignored their pleas, and pulled up to the valet right in time for the window to fall out.</p><p>We tell her, Gloria, this is embarrassing," Bertha continued. We all jump out of the van, right in front of all these people in line, beautifully decked out. Gloria walks out with her head up, and said, Lets get in line.' I pretended that we fit in. She never acted.</p><p>One of Molina's biggest political allies and rivals was Zev Yaroslavsky, who was with her on the City Council and Board of Supervisors for 24 years. Although both Democrats, their clashes made for great political theater. It was like a brother and sister relationship, he said. If she trusted your competence and your word was good, you had a good relationship with her. If you crossed her once, it was curtains.</p><p>When the two were termed out in 2014, they exchanged gifts at their final supervisor meeting. He gave Molina a painting of her; she gifted him a quilt done in the form of a crossword puzzle complete with clues about his career. Yaroslavsky and his family use it to this day.</p><p>When I saw her for the last time, he joked, I told Gloria, Even if I try to get you out of my head, I sleep with you every day. Theres a reason were all talking about her. Its not just because she was the first Latina. Its because she was Gloria Molina.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tony Valdez, trailblazing Latino news reporter with an  encyclopedic knowledge of L.A.</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/obituaries/story/2023-05-11/tony-valdez</link>
      <description>Tony Valdez was a local broadcast news legend, respected by viewers and peers alike for covering crime and for his encyclopedic knowledge of L.A.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 21:05:50 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Priscella Vega</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/obituaries/story/2023-05-11/tony-valdez</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/obituaries/story/2023-05-11/tony-valdez">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/90091f2/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1327x1017+0+0/resize/320x245!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F69%2Fe2%2F6e33fead44dcaaf01e501ea3ae1a%2Ftony-valdez-crop.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a5dd8b0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1327x1017+0+0/resize/568x435!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F69%2Fe2%2F6e33fead44dcaaf01e501ea3ae1a%2Ftony-valdez-crop.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9bcad55/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1327x1017+0+0/resize/768x589!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F69%2Fe2%2F6e33fead44dcaaf01e501ea3ae1a%2Ftony-valdez-crop.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/904aa0f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1327x1017+0+0/resize/1024x785!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F69%2Fe2%2F6e33fead44dcaaf01e501ea3ae1a%2Ftony-valdez-crop.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/bd83822/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1327x1017+0+0/resize/1200x920!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F69%2Fe2%2F6e33fead44dcaaf01e501ea3ae1a%2Ftony-valdez-crop.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Tony Valdez and Azalea Iniguez present on stage at the Television Academys 66th Los Angeles Area Emmy Awards on Saturday, July 26, 2014 at The Leonard H. Goldenson Theater in the NoHo Arts District in Los Angeles. (Photo by Vince Bucci/Invision for the Television Academy/AP Images)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1639453/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1327x1017+0+0/resize/320x245!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F69%2Fe2%2F6e33fead44dcaaf01e501ea3ae1a%2Ftony-valdez-crop.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1cfee46/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1327x1017+0+0/resize/568x435!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F69%2Fe2%2F6e33fead44dcaaf01e501ea3ae1a%2Ftony-valdez-crop.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/105c4eb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1327x1017+0+0/resize/768x589!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F69%2Fe2%2F6e33fead44dcaaf01e501ea3ae1a%2Ftony-valdez-crop.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4e77ee0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1327x1017+0+0/resize/1024x785!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F69%2Fe2%2F6e33fead44dcaaf01e501ea3ae1a%2Ftony-valdez-crop.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/51dddb3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1327x1017+0+0/resize/1200x920!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F69%2Fe2%2F6e33fead44dcaaf01e501ea3ae1a%2Ftony-valdez-crop.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="920"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/51dddb3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1327x1017+0+0/resize/1200x920!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F69%2Fe2%2F6e33fead44dcaaf01e501ea3ae1a%2Ftony-valdez-crop.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Tony Valdez and Azalea Iniguez present on stage at the Television Academys 66th Los Angeles Area Emmy Awards on Saturday, July 26, 2014 at The Leonard H. Goldenson Theater in the NoHo Arts District in Los Angeles. (Photo by Vince Bucci/Invision for the Television Academy/AP Images)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Vince Bucci/Vince Bucci/Invision/AP)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Tony Valdez, trailblazing Latino news reporter with an  encyclopedic knowledge of L.A.</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/priscella-vega">        Priscella Vega    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="May 11, 2023">May 11, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>In the fall of 2021, Tony Valdez visited the East Los Angeles College newsroom, carrying envelopes stamped with his organization's emblem. He stood before a group of student journalists eager to be like him. </p><p>As chairman of the <a href="https://www.8balljournalists.org/" target="_blank">8 Ball Emergency Fund for Journalists</a>, Valdez explained its mission to financially support working professionals. Layoffs, low pay</p>,<p> and furloughs amid the COVID-19 pandemic  the former KTTV-TV Channel 11 broadcaster knew first-hand how grueling the industry could be. </p><p>Valdez was a local broadcast news legend, respected by viewers and peers alike for covering crime and for his encyclopedi</p> ca<p> knowledge of the city. The Mexican Filipino reporter lacked the typical journalism credentials to break into the business, but proved </p> that <p>infinite curiosity and insatiable doggedness </p> werewas<p> more than enough to thrive in the industry. He took pride in his heritage and told stories through a cultural prism,</p> <p>believing L.A.s multi</p>-<p>ethnic communities deserved to be informed.</p><p>That day </p> in before<p> the East L.A. College newsroom, though, he was there to help fellow journalists. Valdez explained that the 8 Ball board distributed grants to student journalists if funds remained, though it wasn't frequent. But that day, four students would receive $250 each. He pulled $100</p>  bills<p> from his wallet to add to each envelope. </p><p>It was the first time some had ever received such help.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/c4/98/13a75be64464be42e94aaa918941/img-0241-1.jpg"></figure><p>"I was excited, felt supported by the community," said Teresa Acosta, the managing editor of Campus News newspaper, who plans to transfer to Cal Poly Pomona at the end of spring. "He was a really warm person. He didn't feel removed or like he was this celebrity, even though I had been watching him for a long time." </p><p>Those in Valdezs circle knew how seriously he took his role as a leader.</p><p>"I think he saw himself giving a boost to kids who were in the situation he was in 60 years ago," said Doug Smith, Los Angeles Times reporter and fellow 8 Ball board member. "He thought these young people needed that boost and needed to be told they deserved it, and that it was going to make a difference in their lives."</p><p>"He knew what it was like to be poor," said Bob Tarlau, former senior news producer at </p>of<p> KTTV</p> Channel 11<p>. "He knew what it was like to struggle. He knew what it was like to be a minority. And those things forged a fire in him that never died."</p> A mentor to many<p>, Valdez died </p> May 4<p> of kidney failure in his Hollywood home, said his son, Steve Valdez. He was 78. </p><p>Born in downtown Los Angeles in 1944 to a homemaker and blue-collar father, Valdez</p>'s life<p> gravitated toward journalism since he was boy. He enjoyed lingering around the old <a href="https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2021-09-10/historic-herald-examiner-newspaper-opens-downtown-los-angeles">L.A. Herald Examiner building</a> and treated the Central Library's children</p> 's<p> section as a shrine. As a Bell Gardens High School student, he delved into photography and would occasionally emcee and DJ during lunch or </p> at <p>dances. </p><p>He took <a href="https://www.lacitycollege.edu/about/famous-alumni" target="_blank">some courses</a> at Los Angeles City College, but found himself working at a local record store, where he made a name for himself in the East L.A. music scene. By the mid-1960s, </p> he was serving in Vietnam after being <p>drafted by the U.S. Army. He lived in Fort Bliss, Texas where he met his future wife. </p><p>The couple returned to the Golden State where Valdez worked as a copywriter for a small advertising agency. He took on freelance assignments to bring in extra cash. The way he would tell his family years later, a KTLA -TV Channel 5 employee invited him off the street to work for the</p>m station<p> on an as-needed basis, even though he didn't have a journalism degree. By 1978, Valdez accepted a full-time job with the company. </p><p>"The talent was there, but he didn't really know what to do with that talent," Steve Valdez said. "But on some level, he was impressing people with freelance pieces that he may have been doing." </p><p>That job didn't last long, and the newly divorced father briefly wrote for La Opinin, relying on the Spanish he learned while living in East L.A., and then worked a stint with KCET-TV Channel 28. Then came a freelance offer from KTTV</p> Channel 11<p> in 1981 that turned Valdez into a household name. </p><p>He led "Tony's L.A.", highlighting </p> L.A. County's hidden<p> secrets. He hosted "Midday Sunday" and co-anchored the 10 p.m. </p>o'clock evening <p>news with Christine Devine. Throughout his tenure, the station gave him leeway to tell in-depth stories on historic L.A. </p> events<p> such as the Watts Riots.</p><p>But the reporters specialty was crime. His crime segment "L.A.'s Most Wanted," </p> ran <p>for 27 years and spotlighted cases, featuring law enforcement officials recounting events. Viewers were encouraged to play detective and call in with any tips. He enjoyed the challenge of trying to make sense of murder and mayhem. Steve Valdez said his father had the time of his life covering Richard Ramirez, the "Night Stalker" serial killer who terrorized California with a spate of break-in murders in the 1980s.</p><p>Accolades soon followed </p> in the form of<p> Emmys and </p> awards from<p> the Los Angeles Press Club. With a steady paycheck, Valdez purchased his prized 1985 Honda Prelude.</p><p>Valdez credited his upbringing, living in a housing project and being surrounded by L.A.s rich multiethnic community </p> with shapingas to<p> how he approached stories.</p><p>Longtime colleague Tarlau said Valdez was a dynamite reporter and the best at winging pursuits because of his vast knowledge of L.A. If a pursuit cut through Boyle Heights, Valdez could talk about the neighborhoods background and say where the driver could turn or pinpoint the nearest offramp.</p><p>Like any good reporter, the veteran was a stickler for accuracy and called it out.</p><p>In 1991, he wrote a <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1991-06-23-tm-1611-story.html">letter to the editor</a> in response to a Los Angeles Times L.A. Speak column, chastising the paper for incorrectly using Spanish "gang jargon." "Please let me emphasize that these are not criticisms of the piece but rather an effort to be factual," he wrote. </p><p>The day Pel died in 2022, Valdez chastised broadcasters who mispronounced the professional soccer player's name. He wrote on his Facebook: "Note to news broadcasters in the USA: there's an accent mark over the second 'e' in Pel's name because it is supposed to be pronounced 'pay-LAY.' All the reports of his passing I heard today pronounced it incorrectly as 'PAY-lay' except for the Spanish, Korean and Armenian newscasts along with CNN and the BBC where they got it right."</p><p>Longtime followers of Valdez shared their memories of the broadcaster on Devines Facebook post. Some described the newsman as a "truth seeking bulldog" and as the "human Thomas Guide, which I suppose would be today's version of the human Waze." </p><p>"He knew every street in LA and didn't need a map to get around, either on paper or a phone," commented Pat Anson on Devine's post. "Behind the gruff exterior was a guy who would always go to bat for a colleague on a union issue and quietly bought Thanksgiving dinner for everyone working that day when the company stopped doing it."</p><p>Despite his success and love for telling stories, the job slowly turned into a grind. A few years before </p> his father he<p> retired in 2016, Steve Valdez said, </p> their <p>weekly lunches </p>with his father <p>changed. Conversations no longer focused on his </p> dad's<p> latest story, but on the duties he had to fulfill as a union shop steward.</p><p>He always loved the news, but he hated the business, Steve Valdez said.</p><p>His time as a volunteer docent for the Los Angeles Conservancy helped alleviate the grind from his main job, such as the <a href="https://spectrumnews1.com/ca/la-west/socal-scene/2023/01/26/the-icon-that-is-union-station#" target="_blank">Union Station tours</a> </p> he led<p>. </p><p>Valdez remained busy in retirement, holding various positions with the 8 Ball board and going on early morning drives to shoot photos of his beloved L.A. He loved sharing stories of his time in the business with his grandchildren.</p><p>Although he was diagnosed as a Type 1 diabetic, he had a penchant for oysters and loved eating at King Taco and dining at classic Hollywood eateries such as Musso &amp; Frank Grill.</p><p>On his final segment for </p> KTTV, KTVT, Fox 11,<p> Valdez reflected on his time in the industry before affirmative action or equal opportunity laws were enacted.</p><p>I never gave up and I kept trying, he told Devine. Every time I failed, I tried to learn something from that experience and keep going.</p><p>Valdez is survived by his son </p> Steve<p>, daughters Mariana Micheli and Paola Micheli, and three grandchildren. </p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Denny Crum's Louisville dynasty left UCLA fans wondering what might have been</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/sports/ucla/story/2023-05-10/appreciation-denny-crum-louisville-ucla-basketball</link>
      <description>Denny Crum built a dynasty at Louisville and had chances to take a head coaching job at UCLA. The John Wooden disciple built his own story with the Cardinals.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2023 12:00:34 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Ben Bolch</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/sports/ucla/story/2023-05-10/appreciation-denny-crum-louisville-ucla-basketball</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/sports/ucla/story/2023-05-10/appreciation-denny-crum-louisville-ucla-basketball">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8bb003e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1992x1464+0+0/resize/320x235!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F9c%2Fa3ff7776439f919736672a91dfde%2Fobit-crum-basketball-60248.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e6fc252/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1992x1464+0+0/resize/568x417!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F9c%2Fa3ff7776439f919736672a91dfde%2Fobit-crum-basketball-60248.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/51c5301/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1992x1464+0+0/resize/768x564!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F9c%2Fa3ff7776439f919736672a91dfde%2Fobit-crum-basketball-60248.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/54de6dd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1992x1464+0+0/resize/1024x753!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F9c%2Fa3ff7776439f919736672a91dfde%2Fobit-crum-basketball-60248.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/50b3512/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1992x1464+0+0/resize/1200x882!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F9c%2Fa3ff7776439f919736672a91dfde%2Fobit-crum-basketball-60248.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="FILE - Louisville coach Denny Crum gestures towards his team as players from the bench begin to celebrate during the closing moments of their 88-77 victory over LSU in the NCAA college basketball semifinals in Dallas, March 29, 1986. Denny Crum, who won two NCAA mens basketball championships and built Louisville into one of the 1980s dominant programs during a Hall of Fame coaching career, died Tuesday, May 9, 2023. He was 86. (AP Photo/David Longstreath, File)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4c6f0cd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1992x1464+0+0/resize/320x235!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F9c%2Fa3ff7776439f919736672a91dfde%2Fobit-crum-basketball-60248.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2c69e65/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1992x1464+0+0/resize/568x417!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F9c%2Fa3ff7776439f919736672a91dfde%2Fobit-crum-basketball-60248.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a588765/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1992x1464+0+0/resize/768x564!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F9c%2Fa3ff7776439f919736672a91dfde%2Fobit-crum-basketball-60248.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/fbd6d10/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1992x1464+0+0/resize/1024x753!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F9c%2Fa3ff7776439f919736672a91dfde%2Fobit-crum-basketball-60248.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b6a2b54/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1992x1464+0+0/resize/1200x882!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F9c%2Fa3ff7776439f919736672a91dfde%2Fobit-crum-basketball-60248.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="882"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b6a2b54/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1992x1464+0+0/resize/1200x882!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff2%2F9c%2Fa3ff7776439f919736672a91dfde%2Fobit-crum-basketball-60248.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">FILE - Louisville coach Denny Crum gestures towards his team as players from the bench begin to celebrate during the closing moments of their 88-77 victory over LSU in the NCAA college basketball semifinals in Dallas, March 29, 1986. Denny Crum, who won two NCAA mens basketball championships and built Louisville into one of the 1980s dominant programs during a Hall of Fame coaching career, died Tuesday, May 9, 2023. He was 86. (AP Photo/David Longstreath, File)</div><div class="figure-credit">(DAVID LONGSTREATCH / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Denny Crum&#x27;s Louisville dynasty left UCLA fans wondering what might have been</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/ben-bolch">        Ben Bolch    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="May 10, 2023">May 10, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Only minutes after losing to <a href="https://www.latimes.com/sports/ucla/story/2020-06-04/plaschke-ucla-john-wooden-anniversary-of-his-death-missing-him">John Wooden</a>s <a href="https://www.latimes.com/sports/ucla">UCLA Bruins</a> in the 1975 Final Four, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/sports/story/2023-05-09/denny-crum-john-wooden-louisville-dies-at-86">Denny Crum</a> heard the same rumors as everybody else.</p><p>He was the likely successor to the coaching legend who had just announced that he would retire after facing Kentucky in the championship game two days later.</p><p>Even then, relatively early in his coaching career, Crum was a star. He had taken Louisville to two Final Fours by age 38. He was a relentless recruiter and unfailingly charismatic. He knew the Wooden Way as well as anyone, the San Fernando native having played for the coach and apprenticed under him for three more seasons.</p><p>To the surprise of many, Crum stayed at Louisville and the Bruins hired <a href="https://www.sports-reference.com/cbb/coaches/gene-bartow-1.html">Gene Bartow</a>. It was the first of several flirtations between Crum and <a href="https://www.latimes.com/sports/ucla">UCLA</a> that left many Bruins wondering what might have been given the long line of failed Wooden successors.</p><p>Well, he would have won, Gary Cunningham, a longtime friend of Crums who coached alongside him under Wooden, said by telephone Tuesday after <a href="https://www.latimes.com/sports/story/2023-05-09/denny-crum-john-wooden-louisville-dies-at-86">Crum died at 86</a>. He would have done a good job.</p><p>For Louisville fans, there were no what-ifs, only what was: a basketball dynasty. Crum stayed for 30 years, guiding the Cardinals to two national championships (including a triumph over Larry Browns Bruins in the 1980 title game), six Final Fours and a 675-295 record before retiring in 2001.</p><p>His teams won with many of the principles he had learned under Wooden. Louisville used the same defensive practice drills and ran a version of the same high-post offense. Crum even mimicked Wooden in his sideline demeanor, clutching a rolled-up program in one hand.</p> Denny Crum, a John Wooden disciple who coached Louisville to two NCAA titles, dies at 86<p>In 1994, Crum became just the third active college coach to be inducted into the Naismith Memorial Basketball Hall of Fame, following Dean Smith and Bob Knight. Wooden traveled from Los Angeles to Springfield, Mass., to accompany Crum to the stage during the ceremony.</p><p>By then, UCLA was nearly two decades removed from its last national title under Wooden and a year away from its next championship, under <a href="https://www.sports-reference.com/cbb/coaches/jim-harrick-1.html">Jim Harrick</a>. To many, it felt like an eternity of darkness that could have been avoided had the Bruins not repeatedly dropped the ball with Crum.</p><p>What else did the guy have to prove when it came to his Bruin bonafides? After starting his career at Pierce College, Crum spent two eager but unremarkable years as a UCLA guard, averaging 8.7 points in his final season while winning a most-improved-player award. He also hosted Cunningham on the high school prospects official visit, taking him to Lawrys in Beverly Hills inside a Volkswagen that could barely accommodate the 6-foot-6 forward.</p><p>After graduating in 1959, Crum coached at Pierce while making an evening commute to Westwood to help UCLA assistant Jerry Norman coach the Bruins freshmen for free.</p><p>Crums first break came in 1968. Fed up with UCLAs notoriously cheap ways, Norman left to become a stockbroker and Crum moved onto Woodens staff alongside Cunningham. Crum told former Times writer Mark Heisler in They Shoot Coaches, Dont They? that the move entailed a $3,000 pay cut. It proved worthwhile given that the Bruins won a national title in each of the three seasons Crum coached under Wooden.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/a8/e3/6f414010421fa79c12561fecd9c1/john-wooden-and-denny-crum-aphs262109.jpg"></figure><p>Eager to show that he could make it as a head coach while putting himself in the running to become Woodens successor, whenever that chance might arise, Crum took the Louisville job in 1971. He told Heisler that he believed UCLA athletic director J.D. Morgan would not hire an assistant coach to replace Wooden.</p><p>Immediately proving his worth, Crum took his new school to the Final Four in his first season. Too bad the Cardinals had the misfortune of running into Woodens Bruins in a national semifinal. Final score: UCLA 96, Louisville 77.</p><p>Three years later, the teams met again on the same stage. The Bruins were on the verge of needing a new coach after Richard Washingtons jumper in overtime had vaulted his team into the final game of the Wooden era following his surprise retirement announcement.</p><p>Morgan very well might have gone with an assistant as Woodens replacement had Cunningham not removed himself from consideration, taking a job with the UCLA Alumni Assn. Crum called a </p> newspress<p> conference to say he was staying at Louisville because he had not accomplished what he wanted to at the school even with the two Final Four appearances. Skeptics pointed to another reason for that press conference  the UCLA job was going to Bartow and Crum knew it.</p><p>Morgan, who died in 1980, never told anyone why he didnt go with Crum when he first had the chance. An offer would come two years later, after a disgruntled Bartow essentially ran himself out of town following the 1976-77 season.</p><p>Crum accepted the job before backing out, saying the pay was too low and the cost of living in L.A. too high. One person close to the situation told Heisler that Morgan had given Crum a lowball offer of $33,000  matching Woodens final salary  knowing that he wouldnt accept so the athletic director could tell alumni pining for Crum that he had tried.</p><p>Crum, who lived on a 55-acre ranch outside Louisville, considered the cost of a comparable plot should he take the UCLA job.</p><p>Where could I afford 55 acres in Southern California? he once said in explaining his decision to turn down the Bruins. Probably not even in the Mojave Desert.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/3b/cf/ca8288ea4d84a66d69f027e8c74d/obit-crum-basketball-51787.jpg"></figure><p>By the time UCLA athletic director Peter Dalis finally circled back to Crum with a legitimate offer, after Walt Hazzards dismissal in 1988, Crum had lost interest. The homecoming would never happen.</p><p>Cunningham, who took the job that Crum wouldnt touch as Bartows successor in 1977, said he didnt know the mechanics of any offers that were or werent made to Crum.</p><p>I just know Bob Fischer, who was J.D.s right-hand man and later A.D., came over and talked to me and asked me if I would be interested, Cunningham said, but thats all I know.</p><p>Cunningham, who had also played and coached under Wooden, didnt need any familiarizing with the frugal ways of UCLAs athletic department. He had made $20,000 as an assistant coach, getting a bump to $30,000 as head coach and a $3,000 raise after his first season ended in a Pac-8 Conference title as well as a Sweet 16 loss in the NCAA tournament. Cunningham pocketed just $6,000 a year for his coachs TV show and had to hold summer camps off campus because UCLA would not make Pauley Pavilion available.</p> How many times has UCLA men's basketball team won the NCAA title? <p>The gulf between the lifestyle Crum enjoyed at Louisville and what he would have experienced at UCLA was obvious. Cunningham saw it himself when he dined with Crum in Louisville, watching his longtime friend ask for the check only to be told another patron  undoubtedly a huge Cardinals fan  had picked up the tab.</p><p>I dont believe UCLA would match what Louisville was paying him and the benefits he had and bonuses for winning and so forth, said Cunningham, who lasted only two seasons as UCLAs coach before resigning to begin a career in athletic administration. In those days, coaches at Long Beach State and places like that were making more than the UCLA head coaches, but the expectation was always to win  big-time  at UCLA.</p><p>For better or worse, it was a burden Crum never had to bear.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The staying power of Joe Kapp's 'The Toughest Chicano' Sports Illustrated cover</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/sports/story/2023-05-09/joe-kapp-the-toughest-chicano-sports-illustrated</link>
      <description>Joe Kapp, the former quarterback and coach once labeled 'The Toughest Chicano' by Sports Illustrated, made a big impact as a Latino role model.</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 19:49:47 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/sports/story/2023-05-09/joe-kapp-the-toughest-chicano-sports-illustrated</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>He was a California kingmaker and political genius. But Michael Berman preferred anonymity</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/politics/story/2023-05-09/michael-berman-waxman-california-political-machine-power-influence</link>
      <description>Michael Berman, who died last week, was the shadowy mastermind behind Los Angeles' vaunted Berman-Waxman machine. For years, it was an irresistible force in California politics.</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 12:00:50 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Mark Z. Barabak</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/politics/story/2023-05-09/michael-berman-waxman-california-political-machine-power-influence</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/politics/story/2023-05-09/michael-berman-waxman-california-political-machine-power-influence">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/053dcc5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5330x3959+0+0/resize/320x238!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_HANDOUTS%2F2014_01%2Fla_me_0130_Waxman.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5a3a788/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5330x3959+0+0/resize/568x422!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_HANDOUTS%2F2014_01%2Fla_me_0130_Waxman.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ab24721/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5330x3959+0+0/resize/768x570!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_HANDOUTS%2F2014_01%2Fla_me_0130_Waxman.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8a08413/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5330x3959+0+0/resize/1024x760!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_HANDOUTS%2F2014_01%2Fla_me_0130_Waxman.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7d61c92/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5330x3959+0+0/resize/1200x891!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_HANDOUTS%2F2014_01%2Fla_me_0130_Waxman.JPG 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="March 8, 1984: California Democratic Congressmen from left Mel Levine, Henry Waxman and Howard Berman hold a press conference in support of Sen. Gary Hart for the Democratic Presidential Nomination."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b80dd27/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5330x3959+0+0/resize/320x238!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_HANDOUTS%2F2014_01%2Fla_me_0130_Waxman.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8f43fdd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5330x3959+0+0/resize/568x422!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_HANDOUTS%2F2014_01%2Fla_me_0130_Waxman.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e952c99/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5330x3959+0+0/resize/768x570!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_HANDOUTS%2F2014_01%2Fla_me_0130_Waxman.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0069bbc/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5330x3959+0+0/resize/1024x760!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_HANDOUTS%2F2014_01%2Fla_me_0130_Waxman.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/725c7cb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5330x3959+0+0/resize/1200x891!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_HANDOUTS%2F2014_01%2Fla_me_0130_Waxman.JPG 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="891"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/725c7cb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5330x3959+0+0/resize/1200x891!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_HANDOUTS%2F2014_01%2Fla_me_0130_Waxman.JPG"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">March 8, 1984: California Democratic Congressmen from left Mel Levine, Henry Waxman and Howard Berman hold a press conference in support of Sen. Gary Hart for the Democratic Presidential Nomination. </div><div class="figure-credit">(UPI)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>He was a California kingmaker and political genius. But Michael Berman preferred anonymity</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">California Politics </h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/mark-z-barabak">        Mark Z. Barabak    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="May 9, 2023">May 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>A visit with Michael Berman, the political savant and California kingmaker who died last week, was a throwback to another time.</p><p>He worked</p> <p>from a shabby office, blinds drawn to thwart any ray of sunlight. A blue pall of smoke hung from the ceiling, like a nicotine curtain.</p><p>Lunch might have involved a distilled drink, or two.</p><p>But it's not Berman's defiantly unhealthy lifestyle that stood out among the tanned and beautiful who surrounded him in the glossy climes of Beverly Hills and </p>Los Angeles'<p> the Westside.</p><p>Rather, it was his extraordinary political acumen, coupled with a passion for anonymity.</p><p>It was a striking trait decades ago, when Berman was at the height of his powers as the operational brains behind Los Angeles' powerful Berman-Waxman political machine.</p> <p>It is all the more notable in today's era of relentless self-promotion, when even the most middling political strategist turns up at postelection seminars, in podcasts and on the gaseous cable talk-show circuit.</p><p>Berman spoke sparingly to reporters and rarely agreed to be identified when he did so. After <a href="https://twitter.com/markzbarabak/status/1655035998508847110?s=20" target="_blank">news broke Saturday </a>night of his passing at age 75, the L.A. Times scrambled to find a photograph to<a href="https://www.latimes.com/obituaries/story/2023-05-08/michael-berman-force-in-california-politics-dies"> illustrate Berman's obituary</a>.</p><p>There was none to be had.</p><p>"He ran stuff," said Sherry Bebitch Jeffe, a retired USC political science professor and longtime friend of Berman. "He didn't run for stuff."</p><p>Before time and technique overtook it, the Berman-Waxman machine was an irresistible force in California politics, grooming candidates for positions from City Hall to Sacramento to Washington.</p><p>The principals were Michael Berman; his older brother, Howard; and their former colleague in the UCLA Young Democrats, Henry Waxman.</p><p>"Machine" is a word they loathed. </p><p>"It connotes patronage and corruption," said Waxman, who became one of country's most prolific and influential liberal lawmakers during 40 years in Congress. "That was not what we were all about.</p><p>The Berman-Waxman machine  and we'll stick with that appellation, given its currency  didn't revolve around greased palms or leveraging public services, like garbage pickup, in exchange for votes. Rather, its forte was campaigns and political communication. And it was years ahead of its time.</p><p>Michael Berman and his cohorts were pioneers in the bundling of campaign cash to elect like-minded ideological allies as well as the art of refined targeting and voter persuasion. It is standard political practice today, but one that was relatively new and quite labor-intensive decades ago.</p><p>Tom Epstein recalled how it worked in a 1977 special election for state Assembly. After data </p>was  were <p>hand-collected from voter records, canvassers received specific demographic information to use as they knocked on doors in West L.A. and Santa Monica. </p><p>"We were given four color-coded brochures with different photos and messages targeted at different audiences," said Epstein, a campaign staffer in the Assembly contest, who went on to work as a political strategist in the Clinton White House.</p><p>"One was for older people," Epstein recalled, "one for younger people, one for Republicans and one for middle-aged Democrats."</p><p>It was decidedly low-tech, but effective. Democrat Mel Levine won the race and eventually served alongside Waxman and Howard Berman in Congress.</p><p>Beyond campaign consulting, Michael Berman was long the Democrats' indispensable man in the highly partisan process of redistricting, the once-a-decade drawing of political maps that follows each census. With an encyclopedic knowledge of statewide population and voting patterns, he helped the party bolster its power in Washington and Sacramento.</p><p>Theres no way to trace it all back to him, former Democratic Party chairman John Burton said. But we know.</p><p>Of course, Berman was hardly infallible.</p><p>Before his brother moved to Congress in 1983, he helped wage a costly, ugly and ultimately unsuccessful fight to install Howard Berman as Assembly speaker, which tore the Legislature apart.</p><p>In 1988, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1988-08-11-me-343-story.html">a leaked strategy memo</a>, in which Michael Berman made racist and sexist comments among a number of insults, helped undermine the mayoral prospects of then-Los Angeles City Councilman Zev Yaroslavsky.</p><p>Berman, who did not believe in polling, suffered the consequences when he struck out <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1992-06-06-me-702-story.html">in a pair</a> of 1992 U.S. Senate races. (Levine and Gray Davis were defeated by Barbara Boxer and Dianne Feinstein, respectively, </p> in the Democratic primaries<p>).</p><p>In perhaps the greatest indignity, Howard Berman lost his place in Congress when he and fellow Democrat Brad Sherman squared off in 2012 for a newly drawn seat in the San Fernando Valley. By then, California voters had taken redistricting<a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/blogs/politi-cal/story/2010-11-02/california-passes-prop-20-redistricting-reform"> out of the hands </a>of politicians, and the likes of Michael Berman, and given it over to a nonpartisan citizens panel.</p><p>Whatever Michael Berman thought of those</p> <p>highs and lows remained unspoken  for public consumption, anyway.</p><p>"He saw no percentage in getting his face out there," said Bill Boyarsky, a former L.A. Times political writer and city editor, who <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1989-11-15-me-1819-story.html">often sparred with Berman</a>.</p><p>"He saw no percentage in being nice to a reporter, doing a reporter any favor or having any dealings with the press," said Boyarsky, who hosts a podcast, "Inside Golden State Politics," with Jeffe. "It wasn't of any value to him."</p><p>What Berman cared about was winning elections, which, for a long time, he did more often than not.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>For Angelenos like my parents, Harry Belafonte had one title: King of the Greek</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2023-04-25/harry-belafonte-dies-king-of-the-greek-theatre</link>
      <description>Senior writer Greg Braxton recalls the late crooner's summer performances at L.A.'s Greek Theatre -- Belafonte's most popular tunes and shout-outs to 'the people in the trees.'</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 19:39:25 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Greg Braxton</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2023-04-25/harry-belafonte-dies-king-of-the-greek-theatre</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2023-04-25/harry-belafonte-dies-king-of-the-greek-theatre">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c3f1d7f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2662+0+0/resize/320x284!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff8%2Fab%2F3f7275c94d31a798045446c04a5a%2Fgettyimages-110501879.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/20e0419/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2662+0+0/resize/568x504!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff8%2Fab%2F3f7275c94d31a798045446c04a5a%2Fgettyimages-110501879.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4a2bcec/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2662+0+0/resize/768x682!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff8%2Fab%2F3f7275c94d31a798045446c04a5a%2Fgettyimages-110501879.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/989d7be/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2662+0+0/resize/1024x909!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff8%2Fab%2F3f7275c94d31a798045446c04a5a%2Fgettyimages-110501879.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/94ce541/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2662+0+0/resize/1200x1065!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff8%2Fab%2F3f7275c94d31a798045446c04a5a%2Fgettyimages-110501879.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Singer Harry Belafonte performs at International Radio and Television Society Anniversary Gala on March 9, 1967 n NY"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/06cd049/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2662+0+0/resize/320x284!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff8%2Fab%2F3f7275c94d31a798045446c04a5a%2Fgettyimages-110501879.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/060178d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2662+0+0/resize/568x504!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff8%2Fab%2F3f7275c94d31a798045446c04a5a%2Fgettyimages-110501879.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/562fcea/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2662+0+0/resize/768x682!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff8%2Fab%2F3f7275c94d31a798045446c04a5a%2Fgettyimages-110501879.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2302298/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2662+0+0/resize/1024x909!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff8%2Fab%2F3f7275c94d31a798045446c04a5a%2Fgettyimages-110501879.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b0b4870/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2662+0+0/resize/1200x1065!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff8%2Fab%2F3f7275c94d31a798045446c04a5a%2Fgettyimages-110501879.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="1065"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b0b4870/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2662+0+0/resize/1200x1065!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ff8%2Fab%2F3f7275c94d31a798045446c04a5a%2Fgettyimages-110501879.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">NEW YORK CITY - MARCH 9: Singer Harry Belafonte performs at International Radio and Television Society Anniversary Gala on March 9, 1967 at the Waldorf Hotel in New York City. (Photo by Ron Galella, Ltd./Ron Galella Collection via Getty Images)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Ron Galella Collection via Getty Images)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>For Angelenos like my parents, Harry Belafonte had one title: King of the Greek</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/greg-braxton">        Greg Braxton    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="April 25, 2023">April 25, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Harry Belafonte kissed my mother once. I don't believe she ever recovered.</p><p>Belafonte, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/obituaries/story/2023-04-25/la-me-harry-belafonte-2050">who died Tuesday</a> in New York, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-04-25/harry-belafonte-death-reactions-twitter-instagram-hollywood">is being celebrated</a> as a</p>n incredibly<p> versatile entertainer </p> andwho was also a<p> dedicated civil rights activist. He traveled the globe to care for poorer people, and his later years were marked by his candid political perspective and outspokenness.</p><p>But for me and my family, he will always be </p> known by one moniker above all:the <p>King of the Greek Theatre.</p><p>From the 1950s into the 1980s, Belafonte would perform at the outdoor theater nestled in the hills of Griffith Park. For his legions of Los Angeles fans, which included my parents, these appearances were more than a pleasant night of music and dance. They were must-see events, and always sold out. My mom and dad would never miss an opportunity to bask in the magic of his charisma and musical </p> prowesscharm<p>.</p><p>I can vividly recall when Belafonte would touch down at the Greek during summers of the 1960s and </p>19<p>70s. I was too young to go, and my sister and I would have to be overseen by a babysitter or spend the evening with a neighbor. But I was very familiar with Belafonte's music. It was the soundtrack of our house.</p><p>It seemed </p>like <p>only a few days would pass before his "Calypso" or another </p>one <p>of his albums would once again get spun on our hi-fi turntable. Naturally, "Day-O (The Banana Boat Song)" and "Man Smart (Woman Smarter)" were household favorites. My father would clench his fists and swing his arms, echoing the chorus of Belafonte's declaration, "That's right, de woman is, UH, smarter! That's right! That's right!" I thought it was a tribute to my mother.</p><p>They also loved his ballads like "Come Back Liza," and his delivery was my early introduction to how powerful and lovely a singing voice could be.</p><p>But it was the Belafonte date nights at the Greek </p> thatwhich <p>really stood out. My parents would go out pretty often, but there was always an extra level of excitement before they went to see Belafonte. My mother would look especially pretty in her gorgeous dress, and my dad would dress up like he was going to church. </p><p>They would get home late, still bubbling with excitement. I would sit in bed as they described the concert in detail: Belafonte's tireless energy, the audience's endless cheers for more. He would tease them about encores: "Now you're on </p>myMY <p>time." He would give a shout</p> -<p>out to the "people in the trees"  fans who had not been able to secure tickets and had climbed into the high trees around the Greek to get a view of the stage.</p>They  My parents<p> always brought home a program, and I would sit on the floor the next day gazing at the pictures of Belafonte in performance, with his family and doing charitable work around the world.</p><p>I was an adult when my parents saw Belafonte for the last time. A friend who lived in my apartment building was an usher at the Greek</p>,<p> and managed to secure backstage passes for my parents. After the show, they </p> wenthad gone <p>to the green room and watched patiently as Belafonte worked the room, greeting family and friends. </p><p>He eventually made his way to my parents. ("He came up to </p>us!<p>") I'm not sure what their exact exchange was. But I do know that Belafonte kissed my mother, sending her into a near-swoon. He followed that gesture with a wink for my father.</p><p>I related that story to Belafonte, who </p>also <p>recorded a live album at the Greek, when I interviewed him many years later in an office in Culver City. He and Taylor Branch <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1999-jan-24-ca-974-story.html">were developing a TV version</a> of Branch's Pulitzer Prize-winning history of the civil rights movement, "Parting The Waters: America in the King Years </p> 1954-63<p>." </p><p>By then, Belafonte's performance days were long behind him. I was still struck by the power of his presence, his raspy voice, his commanding vision.</p><p>I was almost embarrassed</p>,<p> but felt compelled to tell him how happy he had made my mother that particular night. He said nothing, but I thought I saw a gleam in his eye.</p><p>And he smiled.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Big role or small, Lance Reddick elevated every scene he was in</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2023-03-18/lance-reddick-appreciation-wire-fringe-bosch-john-wick</link>
      <description>Lance Reddick was, at heart, the definition of a supporting actor, strengthening whatever show or movie he was in, including "John Wick," "The Wire" and "Lost."</description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 01:47:03 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Robert Lloyd</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2023-03-18/lance-reddick-appreciation-wire-fringe-bosch-john-wick</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2023-03-18/lance-reddick-appreciation-wire-fringe-bosch-john-wick">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8a88568/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1200+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fe5%2Fb03cde264639a074e20237e43bca%2Famericas-book-of-secrets-2.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/23ab6ba/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1200+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fe5%2Fb03cde264639a074e20237e43bca%2Famericas-book-of-secrets-2.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/bfd720c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1200+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fe5%2Fb03cde264639a074e20237e43bca%2Famericas-book-of-secrets-2.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3fb219b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1200+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fe5%2Fb03cde264639a074e20237e43bca%2Famericas-book-of-secrets-2.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/995e75c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1200+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fe5%2Fb03cde264639a074e20237e43bca%2Famericas-book-of-secrets-2.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="America&#x27;s Book of Secrets -- History TV Series, Lance Reddick, host ofHISTORY&#x27;s series &quot;America&#x27;s Book of Secrets&quot; Photo by HISTORY Copyright 2021 Lance Reddick hosts&quot;America&#x27;s Book of Secrets&quot; on History."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a3b6d2d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1200+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fe5%2Fb03cde264639a074e20237e43bca%2Famericas-book-of-secrets-2.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b4c664e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1200+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fe5%2Fb03cde264639a074e20237e43bca%2Famericas-book-of-secrets-2.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/16087fa/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1200+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fe5%2Fb03cde264639a074e20237e43bca%2Famericas-book-of-secrets-2.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e055072/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1200+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fe5%2Fb03cde264639a074e20237e43bca%2Famericas-book-of-secrets-2.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/99fba60/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1200+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fe5%2Fb03cde264639a074e20237e43bca%2Famericas-book-of-secrets-2.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/99fba60/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1800x1200+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F46%2Fe5%2Fb03cde264639a074e20237e43bca%2Famericas-book-of-secrets-2.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">Americas Book of Secrets -- History TV Series, Lance Reddick, host ofHISTORYs series Americas Book of Secrets Photo by HISTORY Copyright 2021 Lance Reddick hostsAmericas Book of Secrets on History.</div><div class="figure-credit">(History)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Big role or small, Lance Reddick elevated every scene he was in</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/robert-lloyd">        Robert Lloyd    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="March 18, 2023">March 18, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>It seems somehow absurd that Lance Reddick, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-03-17/lance-reddick-dead-at-60-the-wire-fringe">who died</a> Friday at </p>age <p>60, is gone. An impressively solid presence wherever he turned up, </p>one would have thought him  Reddick appeared<p> invincible, immortal. That one of his last </p>jobs roles<p> was </p>playing <p>Zeus in the upcoming Disney+ adaptation of <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/movies/story/2023-03-17/lance-reddick-death-completed-projects-percy-jackson-ballerina-white-men-cant-jump-more">     "Percy Jackson and the Olympians"  </a></p>  ju<p>st seems like typecasting.</p><p>A marvelously centered performer, he could elevate any scene without breaking a sweat. Reddick, whose voice was well-trained, resonant and easy on the ear, didnt have to get loud to put the fear of </p> G<p>od into a character or viewer; you could sense well enough the roiling currents beneath a placid surface. He made an art of the low boil</p>, and <p>the stern stare. When asked</p> , he<p> could deploy a toothy smile fit to charm birds from the trees.</p><p>Best known for crime dramas (The Wire, Bosch), genre exercises (Lost," last years Resident Evil series) or combinations of the two <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/blogs/show-tracker/story/2009-05-13/review-fringe-finale-leaves-planet-plot-for-planet-mood">("Fringe"),</a> </p>there were  Reddick<p> also </p> had<p> guest shots on sitcoms (Young Sheldon, Its Always Sunny in Philadelphia) and alternative comedies (Tim &amp; Erics Bedtime Stories, Key &amp; Peele, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-03-17/lance-reddick-death-reactions-eric-andre-wire-john-wick">"The Eric Andre Show"</a> and Comedy Bang! Bang!"). There was<b> </b>voice work in cartoons and video games. He appeared in Regina Kings historical drama <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/movies/story/2021-01-07/one-night-in-miami-review-regina-king-ali-malcolm-x">One Night in Miami </a> and will be </p>seen <p>in an upcoming remake of White Men Cant Jump. </p>Which This <p>is to say that any generalizations I make about his career are surely contradicted somewhere within it.</p>The The face was familiar even if you couldn't place the name; <p>seeing him once, you were happy to see him again. Reddick was handsome, almost pretty, in an individual</p>, alien<p> way. Tall,</p> and<p> lean and subtly muscular with a body built for clothes, he made suits look good, and his parts tended to put him in them. Whatever he wore, he looked neat and dignified. (</p> In <p>Oz, in which </p>where<p> he played a police detective undercover in prison, was something of an exception</p>, but, . T<p>hen again, he was a character playing a character more disheveled than himself.)</p><p>Although we can dream of the series or movie that now will never be built around him, Reddick was at heart the definition of a supporting actor</p>  he strengthened whatever show or movie he was cast in, a flying buttress of the dramatic arts<p>. As a figure who radiated authority, he was often cast as an authority figure. Often, as in Fringe or The Wire</p>,<p> </p> <p> not the only shows </p>in which where<p> he played a senior officer of the law  hes called upon to act as a preserver of order, a guide to just what in the hell is going on</p>: .<p> No one was better at making the unloading of expository detail sound like a poetry recital.</p><p>Even when he didnt have a lot to do, Reddick made a big impression. He appeared in only four episodes of Lost, and yet his mysterious </p> Matthew Abaddon<p> is one </p> of<p> the series most memorable characters; he is barely onscreen in the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment/movies/la-et-chang-john-wick-chapter-2-20170209-premiumvideo.html">"John Wick"</a> franchise, though he registers as among its stars. As the unflappable concierge of a hotel for assassins, Reddicks </p> Charon <p>grounds the film's violent nonsense with something like an air of morality.</p><p>Indeed, though he rarely played a capital-H Hero  most often hes just a man devoted to a job, and doing it as well as possible  his characters will read as heroic. And even when they're flawed  </p>as<p> and who in The Wire is not?  they will strive to do the right thing.</p><p>To some unavoidable extent, his stature steered his career. Physiognomy is destiny, in show business even more than in normal life, and Reddick </p>literally <p>wasnt built to play weakness. </p>Not that he couldnt: . <p>Perhaps the best reason to spend time with Netflixs "Resident Evil is that Reddick gets to play extreme variations on his multiply</p> -<p>cloned character, demonstrating his range within </p>a single series, <p>even a single scene. </p><p>And there was more to him than fans </p>of his screen work <p>might have </p>ever <p>suspected. Before graduating from the </p>prestigious <p>Yale School of Drama, Reddick earned a bachelors degree from the Eastman School of Music </p> in Rochester, N.Y.<p> His 2007 album, <a href="https://open.spotify.com/album/78EGCVqaE7suYaeaBpk4Xi" target="_blank">Contemplations &amp; Remembrances,</a> available </p>from  on <p>multiple streaming platforms, is not the wannabe pop/folk/soul pastiche common to moonlighting actors</p>, .but  It's <p>an original, personal and quite lovely work, with art-song melodies laid over jazz harmonies and Latin rhythms, sung in a higher, sweeter key than one might have expected.</p><p>It suggests that in another world, Reddick might have had a career performing or writing musical theater. But in the one we shared, he left us a lot.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Raquel Welch was labeled a sex symbol. But she always knew she was much more than that</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-02-15/raquel-welch-dies-quotes-sex-symbol-status-interviews</link>
      <description>Actor Raquel Welch, who died Wednesday, spoke to The Times over the years about breaking out as a sex symbol and moving beyond that stereotype.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 02:07:19 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Alexandra Del Rosario</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-02-15/raquel-welch-dies-quotes-sex-symbol-status-interviews</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-02-15/raquel-welch-dies-quotes-sex-symbol-status-interviews">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/253d6b6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1695x1287+0+0/resize/320x243!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F29%2Fa2%2Fb9e4415c45a19ecaec7343dd2a99%2Fraquel-welch-deceso-68766.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/30ae7e2/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1695x1287+0+0/resize/568x431!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F29%2Fa2%2Fb9e4415c45a19ecaec7343dd2a99%2Fraquel-welch-deceso-68766.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4a7db3d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1695x1287+0+0/resize/768x583!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F29%2Fa2%2Fb9e4415c45a19ecaec7343dd2a99%2Fraquel-welch-deceso-68766.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ea47462/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1695x1287+0+0/resize/1024x777!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F29%2Fa2%2Fb9e4415c45a19ecaec7343dd2a99%2Fraquel-welch-deceso-68766.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/98c5769/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1695x1287+0+0/resize/1200x911!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F29%2Fa2%2Fb9e4415c45a19ecaec7343dd2a99%2Fraquel-welch-deceso-68766.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="A woman in a tight-fitting gold gown wearing a sailor&#x27;s hat surrounded by men in uniform"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f396982/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1695x1287+0+0/resize/320x243!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F29%2Fa2%2Fb9e4415c45a19ecaec7343dd2a99%2Fraquel-welch-deceso-68766.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c9279d3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1695x1287+0+0/resize/568x431!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F29%2Fa2%2Fb9e4415c45a19ecaec7343dd2a99%2Fraquel-welch-deceso-68766.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/fc612bb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1695x1287+0+0/resize/768x583!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F29%2Fa2%2Fb9e4415c45a19ecaec7343dd2a99%2Fraquel-welch-deceso-68766.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/68fd0a1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1695x1287+0+0/resize/1024x777!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F29%2Fa2%2Fb9e4415c45a19ecaec7343dd2a99%2Fraquel-welch-deceso-68766.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/20d9711/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1695x1287+0+0/resize/1200x911!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F29%2Fa2%2Fb9e4415c45a19ecaec7343dd2a99%2Fraquel-welch-deceso-68766.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="911"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/20d9711/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1695x1287+0+0/resize/1200x911!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F29%2Fa2%2Fb9e4415c45a19ecaec7343dd2a99%2Fraquel-welch-deceso-68766.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">Raquel Welch, seen in 1982, died Wednesday. She was 82. </div><div class="figure-credit">(David Handschuh / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Raquel Welch was labeled a sex symbol. But she always knew she was much more than that</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/alexandra-del-rosario">        Alexandra Del Rosario    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="Feb. 15, 2023">Feb. 15, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/story/2023-02-15/raquel-welch-photos-life-career">Raquel Welch</a> was well aware </p>that <p>that her work in the 1960s films </p>"Bedazzled"  "One Million Years B.C." <p>and "Fantastic Voyage" made her an international sex symbol. But </p>she also said  she was also determined to let Hollywood know<p> there was more to her than her looks. </p><p>Also a mother and author, Welch used her </p>preliminary early<p> status as </p>film cinematic<p> eye candy to promote her talents and </p>additional<p> ambitions. Over the years, the Golden Globe winner got real with the Los Angeles Times about aging </p> and<p> being a role model for other women</p> , among other topics. and more. <p>The </p>Chicago-  Chicago-born<p> actor, also known </p>for "Fantastic Voyage" for her work in films such as <p>"The Three Musketeers"</p>  and "Legally Blonde,"<p> <a href="https://www.latimes.com/obituaries/story/2023-02-15/raquel-welch-dies">died Wednesday at age 82</a>.</p><p>Here are some of her musings from conversations with The Times dating back to 1986.</p> Raquel Welch, international icon who starred in 'Fantastic Voyage,' dies at 82<b>The pros and cons of those revealing costumes</b><p>When she came onto the scene with roles in "Fantastic Voyage," "One Million Years B.C." and "Bedazzled," Welch caught viewers' attention with her </p>curvy body <p>curves  which were </p>only<p> accentuated by revealing </p>or<p> and body-hugging costumes. </p> (Think of <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gSYmJur0Npw" target="_blank">     that fur bikini  </a></p>  in "One Million.")<p>"Every time I left the theater, there would be a crowd of women waiting to ask me questions, such as: What do you eat?, What kind of exercises do you do? and How do you look like that?</p> ,<p></p>,<p>" Welch <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1986-05-23-vw-23575-story.html">told The Times in 1986</a>, </p>twenty  20<p> years after her One Million debut. "Well, I wasnt about to stand there and explain my daily hour-and-a-half exercise routine or what I had for breakfast.</p><p>Being a sex symbol was a tremendous responsibility and a constant battle, she added. It used to bother me at first, but I now know you can have that and be respected as well. You can have both.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/41/1b/f8870a55416f86f95235262da02e/france-raquel-welch-91020.jpg"></figure><p>In the following years, Welch looked back on her early work as <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1990-04-15-ca-1639-story.html">my ticket to ride,</a> but </p> she<p> didnt want her roles as pinups to<b> </b>be my complete legacy. </p><p>After working on the 1972 film "Kansas City Bomber, in which she starred </p>in<p> as a single mother who becomes a roller-derby star, Welch admitted her </p>early<p> first roles werent so </p>glamorous virtuous<p>.</p><p>I felt a rite of passage where I am over that part where I have to run around in a bikini forever, she told <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-2010-apr-07-la-et-classic-hollywood7-2010apr07-story.html">The Times in 2010</a>. Its just so painfully uncomfortable and in a way kind of humiliating.</p> Raquel Welch's life and career in photosWhen r R<p>eflecting on her </p> status as an international sex symbol, days and her talents,<p> Welch kept it real with The Times.</p><p>I am not a fool, she said. I realized when I came along, I wasnt Meryl Streep who had been put into a bikini. I was somebody that got rocketed into the spotlight and superstardom overnight. I knew this was going to give me an opportunity and I should make the best of it."</p><p>In <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment/movies/la-ca-mn-classic-hollywood-raquel-welchd20160815-snap-story.html">2016</a>, Welch told </p>t<p>The Times, There were so many things going for me, but with it came a lot of stereotypical opinions about my abilities and who I was."</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/f1/fe/3559d1cb4da485cd77e816cb7052/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/517446674"></figure><p>In the end, Ive gotten a lot of opportunities to do various things I am very proud of, including Broadway and the physical comedy in The Three Musketeers [for which she won a Golden Globe]. So I would probably say to [my younger self,] Good for you.</p><b>Accepting her age and finding beauty in it</b><p>Welch started her Hollywood career in her 20s and continued acting well into her 70s. As the years went by, the bombshell embraced her age</p>and acknowledged she could not return to the roles made her a "sex symbol" in the first place<p>.</p><p>Here I am an actress in my late 40s  I dont look like that, but thats where I am emotionally and personally, she told <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1990-04-15-ca-1639-story.html">The Times in 1990</a>.</p> Reese Witherspoon honors her 'Legally Blonde' co-star Raquel Welch: 'Simply stunning'<p>I am grown up and I dont have any yen to play in Splash, you know?," she added, </p> referring to the 1984 film starring Daryl Hannah.<p>Decades later, she </p>reunited caught up <p>with </p>t<p>The Times </p>for to discuss<p> her memoir, Raquel: Beyond </p> the<p> Cleavage, and mused on the wisdom </p> that came with age.she said shes gained with age.<p>As life goes on, you get more valuable as a person. Many women look better, she told The Times in 2010. Personally, I think I look better because I have lived and I have a different kind of aura about me having lived.</p><b>Standing up for herself, and other women, in Hollywood&nbsp;</b><p>Welch might have distanced herself from her One Million Years B.C. looks, but she liked that there was something very superhero" about her character, she said in 2016. </p><p>In addition to being an actor, producer and author, </p>thats what <p>Welch said she wanted to be </p> <p>someone to look up to. Especially for other women.</p><p>In June 1986, Welch used her multimillion legal victory against MGM over </p>Canery  Cannery<p> Row as a moment to speak up for other </p>women female<p> actors. A jury decided the studio had breached its contract with Welch</p>,<p> when it replaced her with Debra Winger.</p> Raquel Welch Awarded $10.8 Million Over Firing<p>I think what this shows is that its important to stand up for your rights, and I hope that women in and out of Hollywood stand up for their rights when they feel theyve been wronged, </p> Welch <p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1986-06-25-me-20292-story.html">said outside the courtroom</a></p> .<p> <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1986-06-25-me-20292-story.html">The Times reported.</a></p>Decades later,  In 2010, as she was <p>approaching 70, </p> years-old,<p> Welch told </p>t<p>The Times she wanted to share her life knowledge through her memoir.</p><p>I desperately wanted to speak to women of my generation and, being a mother, to younger girls as well. I wanted to speak about my experience being a woman because it might help by knowing that even if you are touted as some big doo</p> <p>dah, the trials and tribulations and the beauty of being a woman is something that we all experience in our own way, she said</p> in 2010<p>.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/fa/b6/99d303f54c1ca0f052e9faa9c1dc/la-et-raquel-welch-l0g21cnc.JPG"></figure><p>She continued: I wanted to speak about the unspeakable, like menopause. What we really dont need to talk about much has to do with plain old sex. But if we are talking about real life-changing experiences  I thought I would be useful and helpful.</p><b>How those sex-symbol roles eventually helped her as a mother</b><p>By the time Welch landed her first movie role,</p>  as a call girl in 1964's "A House Is Not a Home," <p>she was a mother to two young children. In Nov</p>m<p>e</p> m<p>ber 1959, she and ex-husband</p>  James Welch<p> welcomed their son</p> , Damon Welch<p>. Two years later</p> , theywelcomed their had a <p>daughter, </p> Latanne "Tahnee" Welch<p>.</p><p>In 2016, she told The Times those early roles might have been a blessing in disguise, especially as a young mom.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/1e/4b/8618822848f29a10b8adb26cedc3/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/159821830"></figure><p>I thought, This is not at all who I am, but then at the same time, I was thinking, Maybe thats the way fate has planned it so I could at least get aboard,</p> '<p> she said. Otherwise, I was a young mother, and if I would have had to wait around for a really wonderful role that more established actresses would be more likely to be cast in, I might not have been able to have a career.</p>Back i<p>In <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1986-05-23-vw-23575-story.html">1986</a>, Welch also spoke out against critics who said she couldnt balance motherhood and her Hollywood fame.</p><p>People kept telling me that combining children with a career at an early age just wasnt done. But I think it helped, she said. It gave me a kind of stability and determination I might not have had otherwise. If nothing else, I owed it to them not to trash myself.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Iron Sheik, wrestling legend known for camel clutch hold and tweets, dies at 81</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/sports/story/2023-06-07/the-iron-sheik-dies-wrestler-wwe-wwf-hossein-khosrow-ali-vaziri</link>
      <description>The Iron Sheik, a World Wrestling Entertainment Hall of Famer from Iran, has died at 81, according to a statement  on his social media accounts.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 16:45:59 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Chuck Schilken</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/sports/story/2023-06-07/the-iron-sheik-dies-wrestler-wwe-wwf-hossein-khosrow-ali-vaziri</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/sports/story/2023-06-07/the-iron-sheik-dies-wrestler-wwe-wwf-hossein-khosrow-ali-vaziri">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e848bc0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x1995+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F36%2F54%2F8a7187e34bf5a4ac36159c897fc0%2Fgettyimages-111602836.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b6464ef/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x1995+0+0/resize/568x378!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F36%2F54%2F8a7187e34bf5a4ac36159c897fc0%2Fgettyimages-111602836.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d13b50a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x1995+0+0/resize/768x511!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F36%2F54%2F8a7187e34bf5a4ac36159c897fc0%2Fgettyimages-111602836.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a7784a4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x1995+0+0/resize/1024x681!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F36%2F54%2F8a7187e34bf5a4ac36159c897fc0%2Fgettyimages-111602836.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/70dbc4e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x1995+0+0/resize/1200x798!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F36%2F54%2F8a7187e34bf5a4ac36159c897fc0%2Fgettyimages-111602836.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="The Iron Sheik, wrestling legend, dies at 81"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1bddd0c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x1995+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F36%2F54%2F8a7187e34bf5a4ac36159c897fc0%2Fgettyimages-111602836.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b62b502/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x1995+0+0/resize/568x378!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F36%2F54%2F8a7187e34bf5a4ac36159c897fc0%2Fgettyimages-111602836.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4bf32b5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x1995+0+0/resize/768x511!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F36%2F54%2F8a7187e34bf5a4ac36159c897fc0%2Fgettyimages-111602836.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0ab1c08/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x1995+0+0/resize/1024x681!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F36%2F54%2F8a7187e34bf5a4ac36159c897fc0%2Fgettyimages-111602836.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a5fc168/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x1995+0+0/resize/1200x798!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F36%2F54%2F8a7187e34bf5a4ac36159c897fc0%2Fgettyimages-111602836.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="798"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a5fc168/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x1995+0+0/resize/1200x798!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F36%2F54%2F8a7187e34bf5a4ac36159c897fc0%2Fgettyimages-111602836.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">The Iron Sheik during Big Apple Con: Comic Book, Art, Toy and SciFi Expo - September 16, 2006 at Penn Plaza Pavilion in New York City, New York, United States. (Photo by Bobby Bank/WireImage)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Bobby Bank/WireImage)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>The Iron Sheik, wrestling legend known for camel clutch hold and tweets, dies at 81</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/chuck-schilken">        Chuck Schilken    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 7, 2023">June 7, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Hossein Khosrow Ali Vaziri, better known as professional wrestling legend the Iron Sheik, has died, according to a statement posted </p> Wednesday<p> on his social media accounts. He was 81.</p><p>"Today, we gather with heavy hearts to bid farewell to a true legend, a force of nature, and an iconic figure who left an incredible mark on the world of professional wrestling," the <a href="https://twitter.com/the_ironsheik/status/1666462933604265990?s=20" target="_blank">statement read on his Twitter account</a>. "It is with great sadness that we share the news of the passing of The Iron Sheik, but we also take solace in knowing that he departed this world peacefully, leaving behind a legacy that will endure for generations to come."</p><p>World Wrestling Entertainment retweeted the statement, writing: "WWE is saddened to hear of the passing of WWE Hall of Famer The Iron Sheik, and extends its condolences to his family, friends, and fans."</p> https://twitter.com/WWE/status/1666471010986500096?s=20<p>Born on March 15, 1942, in Damghan, Iran, Vaziri won the Amateur Athletic Union Greco Roman wrestling title in 1971 and served as an assistant coach in the sport for two U.S. Olympic teams.</p><p>He started wrestling professionally in 1972 and defeated Bob Backlund on Dec. 26, 1983, at Madison Square Garden to become the World Wrestling Federation World Heavyweight Champion. Vaziri lost the title less than a month later to <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1993-10-07-ca-43266-story.html">Hulk Hogan</a> in a famous match that is said to have launched <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1992-03-12-mn-5287-story.html">Hogans superstar career</a>.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/61/a7/5e6b20444691880bfbdbd8aec7a5/ap090715026879.jpg"></figure><p>One of wrestling's most beloved heels, the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1986-02-18-ca-9398-story.html">Iron Sheik was known for his camel clutch</a> finishing hold, his fierce rivalry with fellow wrestler <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1991-01-25-mn-766-story.html">Sgt. Slaughter</a> and a signature look that included a shaved head, a waxed mustache and curled boots.</p><p>The Iron Sheik teamed with <a href="https://www.latimes.com/sports/sportsnow/la-sp-nikolai-volkoff-brian-christopher-20180729-story.html">Nikolai Volkoff</a> to win the World Tag Team Championship at the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1985-06-07-vw-16163-story.html">first WrestleMania in 1985</a>. He was inducted into the WWE Hall of Fame in 2005.</p><p>Vaziri is survived by his wife, Caryl; three children, Tanya, Nikki and Marissa; and five grandchildren.</p><p>The Iron Sheik was a man of immense passion and dedication, the statement on his social media accounts read. He embodied resilience. He overcame countless challenges in his life, both inside and outside the wrestling ring. His journey from a small village in Iran to becoming one of the most recognizable figures in the world of wrestling is a testament to his unwavering determination.</p> The Iron Sheik has more than 645,000 followers on <p><a href="https://twitter.com/the_ironsheik" target="_blank">his Twitter account</a></p> , which has been known to feature often-funny, often-profane and often anti-Hulk Hogan tweets. Appropriately enough, members of the professional wrestling community took to Twitter to share tributes to  and amusing anecdotes about  the Iron Sheik.<p><a href="https://twitter.com/RicFlairNatrBoy/status/1666474877258280964?s=20" target="_blank">     Ric Flair tweeted  </a></p> : "My Dear Friend Khosrow Vaziri!!! We Started Wrestling Together In 1972. Seems Like So Long Ago! We Crossed Paths So Many Times Over The Years &amp; You Were Always So Entertaining. The Greatest Line You Ever Said To Me In 1972: 'If I Had Your Hair, I Would Be With Elizabeth Taylor!' Rest In Peace My Friend. Be As Entertaining To God As You Were To All Of Us!" https://twitter.com/TripleH/status/1666485146499915777?s=20<p><a href="https://twitter.com/foleyispod/status/1666479859709739013?s=20" target="_blank">Mick Foley wrote</a></p> : "Although I never got to know The Sheik well, I was fortunate to have been on hand for two of his most iconic matches  his WWE title victory over Bob Backlund at Madison Square Garden on December 26, 1983 and his 'Boot Camp Match' with Sgt Slaughter at MSG in August, 1984," . "I also had the honor of wrestling the iron sheik for the first and only time  on a tour of Dominica in 1987. Khosrow Vaziri was truly one of a kind."<p><a href="https://twitter.com/JCLayfield/status/1666486066289729546?s=20" target="_blank">From John "Bradshaw" Layfield</a></p> : "He thought my name was Brad Shaw, two names. He met my dad and said 'ah, Mr Shaw, your boy Brad is such a fine young man'. Love you Mr Sheik. RIP you legend."                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Françoise Gilot, French painter who inspired then left Picasso, dead at 101</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-06-06/francoise-gilot-french-painter-who-inspired-then-left-picasso-dead-at-101</link>
      <description>A prolific painter, Gilot was likely more famous for her turbulent relationship with Pablo Picasso — and for leaving him.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2023 00:27:50 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Jocelyn Noveck</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-06-06/francoise-gilot-french-painter-who-inspired-then-left-picasso-dead-at-101</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-06-06/francoise-gilot-french-painter-who-inspired-then-left-picasso-dead-at-101">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/75bfed8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3705x2469+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F64%2F35%2Fe44d65994e3dbfbe9fa15b6fdde7%2Fgettyimages-582214125.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ebae966/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3705x2469+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F64%2F35%2Fe44d65994e3dbfbe9fa15b6fdde7%2Fgettyimages-582214125.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/34f4091/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3705x2469+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F64%2F35%2Fe44d65994e3dbfbe9fa15b6fdde7%2Fgettyimages-582214125.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2e9dbb3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3705x2469+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F64%2F35%2Fe44d65994e3dbfbe9fa15b6fdde7%2Fgettyimages-582214125.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1402558/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3705x2469+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F64%2F35%2Fe44d65994e3dbfbe9fa15b6fdde7%2Fgettyimages-582214125.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Francoise Gilot in her art studio in La Jolla."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/efe40f2/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3705x2469+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F64%2F35%2Fe44d65994e3dbfbe9fa15b6fdde7%2Fgettyimages-582214125.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/83830bf/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3705x2469+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F64%2F35%2Fe44d65994e3dbfbe9fa15b6fdde7%2Fgettyimages-582214125.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/249eaaa/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3705x2469+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F64%2F35%2Fe44d65994e3dbfbe9fa15b6fdde7%2Fgettyimages-582214125.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/08184ff/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3705x2469+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F64%2F35%2Fe44d65994e3dbfbe9fa15b6fdde7%2Fgettyimages-582214125.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a475503/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3705x2469+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F64%2F35%2Fe44d65994e3dbfbe9fa15b6fdde7%2Fgettyimages-582214125.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a475503/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3705x2469+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F64%2F35%2Fe44d65994e3dbfbe9fa15b6fdde7%2Fgettyimages-582214125.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Francoise Gilot in her art studio in La Jolla.</div><div class="figure-credit">(Images Press/Getty Images)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Franoise Gilot, French painter who inspired then left Picasso, dead at 101</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" >        Jocelyn Noveck    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 6, 2023">June 6, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Franoise Gilot, a prolific and acclaimed painter who produced art for more than a half-century but was nonetheless more famous for her turbulent relationship with Pablo Picasso  and for leaving him  died Tuesday in New York City, where she had lived for decades. She was 101.</p><p>Gilots daughter, Aurelia Engel, said her mother ha</p> ds<p> been suffering from both lung and heart problems. She was an extremely talented artist, and we will be working on her legacy and the incredible paintings and works she is leaving us with, Engel said.</p><p>The French-born Gilot had long made her frustration clear that despite acclaim for her art, which she produced from her teenage years until five years ago, she would still be best known for her relationship with the older and more famous Picasso, whom she met in 1943 at age 21, his junior by four decades. </p><p>The union produced two children  Claude and Paloma Picasso. But unlike the other key women in Picassos life  wives or paramours  Gilot eventually walked out.</p><p>He never saw it coming, Engel said of her mother's departure. She was there because she loved him and because she really believed in that incredible passion of art which they both shared. (But) she came as a free, though very, very young, but very independent person."</p><p>Gilot herself told </p> t<p>he Guardian newspaper in 2016 that "I was not a prisoner in the relationship.</p><p>Id been there of my own will, and I left of my own will," she said, then 94. "Thats what I told him once, before I left. I said: Watch out, because I came when I wanted to, but I will leave when I want. He said, Nobody leaves a man like me. I said, Well see. </p><p>Gilot wrote several books, the most famous of which was Life </p> W<p>ith Picasso, written in 1964 with Carlton Lake. An angry Picasso sought unsuccessfully to ban its publication.</p><p>He attacked her in court, and he lost three times," said Engel. "After the third loss he called her and said congratulations. He fought it, but at the same time, I think he was proud to have been with a woman who had such guts like he had.</p><p>Born on Nov. 26, 1921, in leafy Neuilly-sur-Seine in suburban Paris, Gilot was an only child. She knew at the age of </p> 5five <p>that she wanted to be a painter, Engel said. In accordance with her parents' wishes, she studied law, however, while maintaining art as her true passion. She first exhibited her paintings in 1943.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/64/b6/0355b54e413685f33503d1cc6c88/ap530415050.jpg"></figure><p>That was the year she met Picasso, by chance, when she and a friend visited a restaurant on the Left Bank, amid a gathering that included his then-companion, Dora Maar.</p><p>"I was 21 and I felt that painting was already my whole life," she wrote in Life With Picasso. When Picasso asked Gilot and her friend what they did, the friend responded that they were painters, to which Picasso responded, That's the funniest thing I've heard all day. Girls who look like that can't be painters. The two were invited to visit Picasso in his studio, and the relationship soon began.</p><p>Not long after leaving Picasso in 1953, Gilot reunited with a former friend, artist Luc Simon, and married him in 1955. The had a daughter  Engel  and divorced in 1962. In 1970, Gilot married Jonas Salk, the American virologist and researcher famed for his work with the polio vaccine, and began living between San Diego and Paris, and later New York. </p><p>Her art only increased in value over the years. In 2021 her Paloma  la Guitare (1965) sold for $1.3 million at a Sothebys auction. Her work has </p> been <p>shown in many prominent museums, including the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Museum of Modern Art. Her life with Picasso was illustrated in the 1996 movie Surviving Picasso, directed by James Ivory.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/b3/32/e49f63aa4a3384f92aec8450dc08/ap500129014.jpg"></figure><p>Engel noted that although the relationship with Picasso was clearly a difficult one, it gave her mother a certain freedom from her parents and the constraints of a bourgeois life  and perhaps enabled her to pursue her true dream of being a professional painter, a passion she shared with Picasso above all else.</p><p>They both believed that art was the only thing in life worth doing, she said. And she was able to be her true self, even though it was not an easy life with him. But still she was able to be her true self.</p><p>And for Engel, her mother's key legacy was not only her creativity but her courage, which was reflected in her art, which was always changing, never staying safe.</p><p>She was not without fear. But she would always confront her fears and jump in the void and take risks, no matter what, Engel said.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jeanette Rowe, who brought homeless services to people in the streets of L.A., dies at 72</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-06/jeanette-rowe-homeless-outreach-pioneer-dies</link>
      <description>Rowe rejected the idea homeless people were 'service-resistant,' feeling they would come indoors if people would only listen to them.</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 18:12:26 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Gale Holland</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-06/jeanette-rowe-homeless-outreach-pioneer-dies</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-06/jeanette-rowe-homeless-outreach-pioneer-dies">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/906d2a9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/784f939/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/71cb368/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/046e6e7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2f22e75/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Jeanette Rowe, left, meets Beverly Walker, who was living on a sidewalk in Los Angeles."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/12508db/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/dc32754/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/887ddba/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/694fe96/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0a09b75/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0a09b75/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5184x3456+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fzbk%2Fdamlat_images%2FLA%2FLA_PHOTO_SELECTS%2F2016_12%2F2493761_ME_1206_ln_Homeless_Outreach_Worker_003.IK.JPG"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption"> Jeanette Rowe, left, meets Beverly Walker, who was living on a sidewalk in Los Angeles. </div><div class="figure-credit">(Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Jeanette Rowe, who brought homeless services to people in the streets of L.A., dies at 72</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/gale-holland">        Gale Holland    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 6, 2023">June 6, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Jeanette Rowe, a pioneer in bringing homeless services into the streets instead of dumping people on Skid Row, or expecting them to scale bureaucratic mountains, has died at 72.</p><p>Mayor Karen Bass' Inside Safe encampment clearances and other modern homeless programs were "built on the shoulders" of Rowe, the agency's current director said. Rowe took the Los Angeles Homeless Services Authority's emergency response team from two to 85 staff members. </p><p>"Not everyone would feel comfortable seeking help because of levels of depression, hopelessness and other challenges," said LAHSA executive director Va Lecia Adams Kellum. "The notion someone goes to the encampment gives inspiration to them."</p><p>Within a year of her 2016 retirement from LAHSA, Rowe took a position as head of programs at the Midnight Mission on Skid Row, where she overcame institutional resistance to build the 110-year-old shelter's first women's program.</p><p>Rowe called herself "an old hippie," but few hippies ever worked her punishing six-day </p>work<p> weeks, helping people at encampments from the San Gabriel riverbed to Union Station, where she spent a two-day Christmas holiday helping relocate hundreds of people swept out of the landmark's ornate lobby. </p><p>Homeless people were not "service resistant," she believed  if only </p>anyone someone <p>would listen to what they needed. Besides, she said, "I dig that these people have a choice." </p><p>Rowe died May 26 at a hospital after a short illness. She is survived by her wife, Karen Jenkins-Galloway; brother Eddie Rowe and sister Marilyn Silver. </p>Midnight Mission president G. Michael Arnold said.  <p>Rowe grew up in Newark, N.J., in a poor household that never felt that way. My mother always said you only need one pair of shoes, she said.</p><p>Her mother kept the back door, and her dinner table, open to people facing hard times.</p><p>I never slept by myself until I left home for college at Cal State Los Angeles and Dominguez Hills, where she studied music, Rowe said. </p><p>She was working as an accountant when the plight of young homeless people in Hollywood drew her into homeless services. At first she worked with homeless families and children, who she found thrived if their bonds to church, school and community were preserved while they got back on their feet.</p><p> Midnight Mission President G. Michael Arnold said what passed for outreach back then was rounding up homeless people to drop off at Skid Row shelters, or handing out appointment slips.</p><p> "Jeanette realized what she learned applies to everyone being traumatized on the street," said Arnold, who also headed LAHSA during Rowe's tenure there. </p><p>The homeless service system had floundered for years in fits and starts, Rowe said. Sobering centers, serviced by Skid Rows boozer cruise, and short-term rent vouchers were cut off for lack of funding. Until 2005, officials had no reliable homeless count, which she likened to trying to cook without knowing whos coming to dinner.</p><p>After the 2016 passage of the city's $1.2-billion homeless housing bond, she felt Los Angeles was heading in the right direction and retired from LAHSA. "Housing is key," she said. </p><p>Her plan was to rescue animals and organize concerts for homeless people with a musician friend from New York. She did rescue street animals, particularly in her longtime neighborhood of Leimert Park, and organize Skid Row concerts  but her retirement was barely a year old when Arnold hired her at the Midnight Mission, where she worked until her death. </p><p> "Her heart just wouldn't keep her out of the streets," Arnold said.</p><p>Doris Starling, the Midnight Mission's director of street services access center, called Rowe her friend and mentor. </p><p>"She taught me how to motivate people," said Starling, adding that they often </p> attendedbought tickets to<p> women's basketball games together.</p>Starlng said she would never ask users to give up drugs. Instead, she'd ask how much they could cut back, pointing out the money they saved could go for rent in housing. "And when they started cooking for themselves and showering and going to the movies and on dates, they'd come to me and say , 'I got to get into a [drug] program,' "she said.<p>Rowe</p>r<p> was a gifted writer, and her program proposals generally won the day  even when they arrived by email at 3 in the morning, Starling said. </p><p>"We'd say, 'Jeanette. Go to bed. Please go to bed,'" Starling said. </p>Memorial plans are pending.                                     </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astrud Gilberto, Brazilian singer who gave us 'The Girl From Ipanema,' dies at 83</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/music/story/2023-06-06/astrud-gilberto-brazilian-singer-who-gave-us-the-girl-from-ipanema-dies</link>
      <description>'The Girl From Ipanema' made Astrud Gilberto the worldwide voice of bossa nova. The Brazilian singer and songwriter died Monday at 83.</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 16:52:20 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Hillel Italie</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/music/story/2023-06-06/astrud-gilberto-brazilian-singer-who-gave-us-the-girl-from-ipanema-dies</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/music/story/2023-06-06/astrud-gilberto-brazilian-singer-who-gave-us-the-girl-from-ipanema-dies">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/959b0f2/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3691x2425+0+0/resize/320x210!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F6b%2F10%2F4b57d43648bbb735541d4d6664c8%2Fgettyimages-86103973.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/779b00a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3691x2425+0+0/resize/568x373!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F6b%2F10%2F4b57d43648bbb735541d4d6664c8%2Fgettyimages-86103973.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0a5adaa/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3691x2425+0+0/resize/768x504!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F6b%2F10%2F4b57d43648bbb735541d4d6664c8%2Fgettyimages-86103973.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0e86cbd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3691x2425+0+0/resize/1024x672!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F6b%2F10%2F4b57d43648bbb735541d4d6664c8%2Fgettyimages-86103973.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/740fdf9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3691x2425+0+0/resize/1200x788!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F6b%2F10%2F4b57d43648bbb735541d4d6664c8%2Fgettyimages-86103973.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Undated photo of Astrud Gilberto"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/aab1a3b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3691x2425+0+0/resize/320x210!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F6b%2F10%2F4b57d43648bbb735541d4d6664c8%2Fgettyimages-86103973.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/651f71e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3691x2425+0+0/resize/568x373!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F6b%2F10%2F4b57d43648bbb735541d4d6664c8%2Fgettyimages-86103973.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a475407/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3691x2425+0+0/resize/768x504!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F6b%2F10%2F4b57d43648bbb735541d4d6664c8%2Fgettyimages-86103973.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a5d8f42/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3691x2425+0+0/resize/1024x672!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F6b%2F10%2F4b57d43648bbb735541d4d6664c8%2Fgettyimages-86103973.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f3defe7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3691x2425+0+0/resize/1200x788!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F6b%2F10%2F4b57d43648bbb735541d4d6664c8%2Fgettyimages-86103973.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="788"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f3defe7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3691x2425+0+0/resize/1200x788!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F6b%2F10%2F4b57d43648bbb735541d4d6664c8%2Fgettyimages-86103973.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">Undated photo of Astrud Gilberto<br></div><div class="figure-credit">(Simon Ritter/Redferns)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Astrud Gilberto, Brazilian singer who gave us &#x27;The Girl From Ipanema,&#x27; dies at 83</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">Grammys</h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" >        Hillel Italie    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 6, 2023">June 6, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Astrud Gilberto, the Brazilian singer, songwriter and entertainer whose off-hand, English-language cameo on The Girl From Ipanema made her a worldwide voice of bossa nova, has died at 83.</p><p>Musician Paul Ricci, a family friend, confirmed that she died Monday. He did not provide additional details.</p><p>Born in Salvador in the state of Bahia and raised in Rio de Janeiro, Gilberto became an overnight, unexpected superstar in 1964, thanks to knowing just enough English to be recruited by the makers of Getz/Gilberto, the classic bossa nova album featuring saxophonist Stan Getz and her then-husband, singer-songwriter-guitarist Joo Gilberto.</p><p>The Girl From Ipanema, the wistful ballad written by Antnio Carlos Jobim and Vincius de Moraes, was already a hit in South America. But Getz/Gilberto producer Creed Taylor and others thought they could expand the records appeal by including both Portuguese and English language vocals. In a 2002 interview</p> with friends posted on her website <p><a href="https://www.astrudgilberto.com" target="_blank">www.astrudgilberto.com</a>, Astrud Gilberto remembered her husband saying he had a surprise for her at the recording studio.</p><p>I begged him to tell me what it was, but he adamantly refused, and would just say: Wait and see .... Later on, while rehearsing with Stan, as they were in the midst of going over the song The Girl From Ipanema, Joo casually asked me to join in, and sing a chorus in English, after he had just sung the first chorus in Portuguese. So, I did just that, she explained.</p><p>When we were finished performing the song, Joo turned to Stan, and said something like: Tomorrow Astrud sing on record . What do you think? Stan was very receptive, in fact very enthusiastic; he said it was a great idea. The rest, of course, as one would say, is history.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/64/d6/72cc30994f3aa84e1adce9720aeb/ap23157464803075.jpg"></figure><p>Astrud Gilberto sings The Girl From Ipanema in a light, affectless style  as if she had already moved on to other matters  that </p> decades later<p> influenced </p> singers such as<p> Sade and Suzanne Vega among others. But her words, translated from the Portuguese by Norman Gimbel, would be remembered like few others from the era.</p>Tall and tan and young and lovelyThe girl from Ipanema goes walkingAnd when she passesEach one she passes goes, Ah<p>Getz/Gilberto sold more than 2 million copies and The Girl From Ipanema, released as a single with Astrud Gilberto the only vocalist, became an all-time standard, often ranked just behind the Beatles' Yesterday as the most covered song in modern times.</p><p>The Girl From Ipanema won a Grammy in 1965 for record of the year and Gilberto received nominations for best new artist and best vocal performance. The poised, dark-haired singer was so closely associated with The Girl From Ipanema that some assumed she was the inspiration; </p> in fact,<p> de Moraes had written the lyrics about a Brazilian teenager, Helosa Eneida Menezes Paes Pinto.</p><p>Over the next few years, Gilberto toured with Getz among others and released eight albums (with songs in English and Portuguese), among them The Astrud Gilberto Album, Beach Samba and The Shadow of Your Smile. But after 1969, she made just seven more albums and by 2002 had essentially retired from the business and stopped giving interviews, dedicating her latter years to animal rights activism and a career in the visual arts. </p><p>She would allege that she received no money for The Girl From Ipanema and that Taylor and Getz (who would refer to her as just a housewife) took undue credit for discovering her. She also felt estranged from her native country, alleging she was treated dismissively by the press, and rarely performed there after she became a star.</p><p>Isnt there an ancient proverb to the effect that No one is a prophet in his own land? she said in 2002. I have no qualms with Brazilians, and I enjoy myself very much when I go to Brazil. Of course, I go there as an incognito visitor, and not as a performer.</p><p>Astrud Weinert was the youngest of three sisters, born into a family both musical and at ease with foreign languages: Her mother was a singer and violinist, her father a linguistics professor. By her teens, she was among a circle of musical friends and had met Joo Gilberto, a rising star in Rios emerging bossa nova scene.</p><p>She was married twice and had two sons, Joo Marcelo Gilberto and Gregory Lasorsa, both of whom would work with her. Well after her commercial peak, she remained a popular live act, her singing becoming warmer and jazzier as she sang both covers and original material. She also had some notable moments as a recording artist, whether backed by trumpeter Chet Baker on Fly Me to the Moon or crooning with George Michael on the bossa nova standard Desafinado. </p><p>In 2008, she received a Latin Grammy for lifetime achievement.</p><p>I have been labeled by an occasional frustrated journalist as a recluse. The dictionary clearly defines recluse as a person who withdraws from the world to live in seclusion and often in solitude. Why should anybody assume that just because an artist chooses not to give interviews, he/she is a recluse? she said in 2002.</p><p>I firmly believe that any artist who becomes famous through their work  be it music, motion pictures or any other  does not have any moral obligation to satisfy the curiosity of journalists, fans or any members of the public about their private lives, or anything else that does not have any direct reflection on their work. My work, whether perceived as good, bad or indifferent, speaks for itself.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Former FBI agent Robert Hanssen, who was convicted of spying for Russia, dies in prison</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-05/former-fbi-agent-robert-hanssen-who-was-convicted-of-spying-for-russia-dies-in-prison</link>
      <description>Former FBI agent Robert Hanssen, who got cash and diamonds to spy for Russia and the Soviet Union in a notorious case, has died in prison.</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2023 21:06:22 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>LINDSAY WHITEHURST</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-05/former-fbi-agent-robert-hanssen-who-was-convicted-of-spying-for-russia-dies-in-prison</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-05/former-fbi-agent-robert-hanssen-who-was-convicted-of-spying-for-russia-dies-in-prison">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a11bc7f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1350x948+0+0/resize/320x225!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F26%2F24%2Fdfcdfe9a0e755a92f2713a76da96%2Fc2efa340912c4444a8ebd7963f6e30bd 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8624194/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1350x948+0+0/resize/568x399!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F26%2F24%2Fdfcdfe9a0e755a92f2713a76da96%2Fc2efa340912c4444a8ebd7963f6e30bd 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/bdbcb13/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1350x948+0+0/resize/768x540!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F26%2F24%2Fdfcdfe9a0e755a92f2713a76da96%2Fc2efa340912c4444a8ebd7963f6e30bd 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2539b27/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1350x948+0+0/resize/1024x719!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F26%2F24%2Fdfcdfe9a0e755a92f2713a76da96%2Fc2efa340912c4444a8ebd7963f6e30bd 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/79afa74/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1350x948+0+0/resize/1200x843!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F26%2F24%2Fdfcdfe9a0e755a92f2713a76da96%2Fc2efa340912c4444a8ebd7963f6e30bd 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="FILE - In this artist depiction, U.S. Attorney Randy Bellows, right, addresses the court during the sentencing of convicted spy Robert Hanssen, center, seen with his attorney Plato Cacheris, left, at the federal courthouse in Alexandria, Va., May 10, 2002. Hanssen was given a life sentence. The former FBI agent who took more than $1.4 million in cash and diamonds to trade secrets with Russia and the former Soviet Union in one of the most notorious spying cases in American history has died in prison.(William Hennessy, Jr. via AP)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/22c9d68/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1350x948+0+0/resize/320x225!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F26%2F24%2Fdfcdfe9a0e755a92f2713a76da96%2Fc2efa340912c4444a8ebd7963f6e30bd 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1808636/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1350x948+0+0/resize/568x399!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F26%2F24%2Fdfcdfe9a0e755a92f2713a76da96%2Fc2efa340912c4444a8ebd7963f6e30bd 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b24346c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1350x948+0+0/resize/768x540!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F26%2F24%2Fdfcdfe9a0e755a92f2713a76da96%2Fc2efa340912c4444a8ebd7963f6e30bd 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d47ebfa/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1350x948+0+0/resize/1024x719!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F26%2F24%2Fdfcdfe9a0e755a92f2713a76da96%2Fc2efa340912c4444a8ebd7963f6e30bd 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ff8ca89/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1350x948+0+0/resize/1200x843!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F26%2F24%2Fdfcdfe9a0e755a92f2713a76da96%2Fc2efa340912c4444a8ebd7963f6e30bd 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="843"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ff8ca89/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1350x948+0+0/resize/1200x843!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F26%2F24%2Fdfcdfe9a0e755a92f2713a76da96%2Fc2efa340912c4444a8ebd7963f6e30bd"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">FILE - In this artist depiction, U.S. Attorney Randy Bellows, right, addresses the court during the sentencing of convicted spy Robert Hanssen, center, seen with his attorney Plato Cacheris, left, at the federal courthouse in Alexandria, Va., May 10, 2002. Hanssen was given a life sentence. The former FBI agent who took more than $1.4 million in cash and diamonds to trade secrets with Russia and the former Soviet Union in one of the most notorious spying cases in American history has died in prison.(William Hennessy, Jr. via AP)</div><div class="figure-credit">(William Hennessy Jr. / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Former FBI agent Robert Hanssen, who was convicted of spying for Russia, dies in prison</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" >        LINDSAY WHITEHURST    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 5, 2023">June 5, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Robert Hanssen, a <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-2001-may-29-mn-3802-story.html">former FBI agent</a> who took more than $1.4 million in cash and diamonds to trade secrets with Russia and the Soviet Union in one of the most <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-2002-may-11-na-hanssen11-story.html">notorious spying cases</a> in American history, died in prison Monday.</p><p>Hanssen, 79, was found unresponsive in his cell at a federal prison in Florence, Colo., and later pronounced dead, prison officials said.</p><p>Hanssen is believed to have died of natural causes, a person familiar with the matter told the Associated Press. The person was not authorized to publicly discuss details of Hanssens death and spoke to the AP on condition of anonymity.</p><p>He had been serving a <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-2001-jul-13-mn-21891-story.html">sentence of life in prison</a> without the possibility of parole since 2002, after <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-2001-jul-04-mn-18534-story.html">pleading guilty</a> to 15 counts of <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-2001-oct-03-mn-52886-story.html">espionage and other charges</a>.</p><p>Hanssen had divulged a wealth of information about American intelligence-gathering, including extensive detail about how U.S. officials had tapped into Russian spy operations, since at least 1985.</p><p>He was believed to have been partly responsible for the deaths of at least three Soviet officers who were working for U.S. intelligence and executed after being exposed.</p><p>He got more than $1.4 million in cash, bank funds, diamonds and Rolex watches in exchange for providing highly classified national security information to the Soviet Union and later Russia.</p><p>He didnt adopt an obviously lavish lifestyle, instead living in a modest suburban home in Virginia with his family of six children and driving a Taurus and minivan.</p><p>Hanssen would later say he was motivated by money rather than ideology, but a letter to his Soviet handlers in 1985 explains a large payoff could have caused complications because he could not spend it without setting off warning bells.</p><p>Using the alias Ramon Garcia, he passed some 6,000 documents and 26 computer disks to his handlers, authorities said. They detailed eavesdropping techniques, helped to confirm the identity of Russian double agents, and spilled other secrets. Officials also believed he tipped off Moscow to a secret tunnel the Americans built under the Soviet Embassy in Washington for eavesdropping.</p><p>He went undetected for years, but later investigations found missed red flags. After he became the focus of a hunt for a Russian mole, Hanssen was caught taping a garbage bag full of secrets to the underside of a footbridge in a park in a dead drop for Russian handlers.</p><p>The story was made into a movie titled Breach in 2007, starring Chris Cooper as Hanssen and Ryan Phillippe as a young bureau operative who helps bring him down.</p><p>The FBI has been notified of Hanssens death, according to the Bureau of Prisons. </p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Billionaire ‘Bling Empire’ heiress Anna Shay dies. She was 62</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-06-05/billionaire-bling-empire-heiress-anna-shay-dies-she-was-62</link>
      <description>'Bling Empire' billionaire heiress Anna Shay, known for her sharp wit, unexpectedly died Monday after suffering a stroke. She was 62.</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2023 20:45:54 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Emily St. Martin</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-06-05/billionaire-bling-empire-heiress-anna-shay-dies-she-was-62</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-06-05/billionaire-bling-empire-heiress-anna-shay-dies-she-was-62">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5832391/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fc1%2F7e47a31c490c80a8f844f1b5de1b%2Fgettyimages-1396986816-1.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3ff9595/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fc1%2F7e47a31c490c80a8f844f1b5de1b%2Fgettyimages-1396986816-1.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/19891bf/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fc1%2F7e47a31c490c80a8f844f1b5de1b%2Fgettyimages-1396986816-1.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f95a37d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fc1%2F7e47a31c490c80a8f844f1b5de1b%2Fgettyimages-1396986816-1.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e266baa/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fc1%2F7e47a31c490c80a8f844f1b5de1b%2Fgettyimages-1396986816-1.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="LOS ANGELES, CALIFORNIA - MAY 12: Anna Shay attends the season 2 launch celebration party for Netflix&#x27;s &quot;Bling Empire&quot; on May 12, 2022 in Los Angeles, California. (Photo by Rodin Eckenroth/Getty Images)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f50e83a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fc1%2F7e47a31c490c80a8f844f1b5de1b%2Fgettyimages-1396986816-1.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/66d5fbb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fc1%2F7e47a31c490c80a8f844f1b5de1b%2Fgettyimages-1396986816-1.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/50f0fac/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fc1%2F7e47a31c490c80a8f844f1b5de1b%2Fgettyimages-1396986816-1.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/756b870/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fc1%2F7e47a31c490c80a8f844f1b5de1b%2Fgettyimages-1396986816-1.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/be6ca29/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fc1%2F7e47a31c490c80a8f844f1b5de1b%2Fgettyimages-1396986816-1.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/be6ca29/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F37%2Fc1%2F7e47a31c490c80a8f844f1b5de1b%2Fgettyimages-1396986816-1.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">LOS ANGELES, CALIFORNIA - MAY 12: Anna Shay attends the season 2 launch celebration party for Netflixs Bling Empire on May 12, 2022 in Los Angeles, California. (Photo by Rodin Eckenroth/Getty Images)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Rodin Eckenroth/Getty Images)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Billionaire Bling Empire heiress Anna Shay dies. She was 62</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/emily-st-martin">        Emily St. Martin    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 5, 2023">June 5, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Bling Empire star <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2021-01-15/netflix-bling-empire-cast-anna-shay-crazy-rich-asians">Anna Shay</a> has died unexpectedly. The 62-year-old reality TV star suffered a stroke on Monday. </p><p>A Netflix representative confirmed Shay's death </p>with  to<p> The Times. </p><p>It saddens our hearts to announce that Anna Shay, a loving mother, grandmother, charismatic star, and our brightest ray of sunshine, has passed away at the early age of 62 from a stroke, her family told The Times in a statement. </p><p>Anna taught us many life lessons on how not to take life too seriously and to enjoy the finer things. Her impact on our lives will be forever missed but never forgotten.</p><p>Shay appeared on Netflixs <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2021-01-15/netflix-bling-empire-cast-anna-shay-crazy-rich-asians">Bling Empire</a> when the reality series premiered in 2021. A billionaire heiress whose parents accumulated their riches in the arms and defense technology trade, Shay was the wealthiest of the cast members. Known for her sharp one-liners, she was a fan favorite, with <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rUzbyBGCBgw" target="_blank">Best Burn</a> reels dedicated to her savage wit.</p> Her American father, Edward Shay, who founded the global defense contractor Pacific Architects and Engineers, met her part-Japanese, part-Russian mother, Ai Oizumi Shay, in Japan, and together they moved from Japan to Los Angeles when Shay was a child  along with her pet pocket monkey. Shays father  passed away    died  in 1995 and her mother in 2015.  Meet Anna Shay, the rich, unbothered Angeleno at the top of Netflix's 'Bling Empire' Due in part to her unique upbringing, and in part because Shay believed in taking advantage of everything life had to offer, she had a wealth of stories and talents that she had acquired over the course of her extravagant life. She could pilot a helicopter and run a military obstacle course. She learned to speak Spanish so she could manage a Cuban salsa band, and took a sledgehammer to the walls of her Sunset Boulevard estate, insisting she'd renovate it herself.  She was also known for her incredible generosity. She told <p><a href="https://www.townandcountrymag.com/leisure/arts-and-culture/a35252105/bling-empire-anna-shay-interview/" target="_blank">     Town &amp; Country  </a></p>  that she'd met a homeless man at a flower market at 4 a.m. , he who introduced himself as Elvis, and she put him up in an apartment and filled it with groceries for a month. She was also known to buy the salesperson the same item she bought for herself at luxury stores, and loved a good trip to Target, where she would  she'd often spend  drop several grand on groceries and goodies only to take them home and give them away. <p>According to <a href="https://www.marieclaire.com.au/anna-shay-bling-empire" target="_blank">Marie Claire</a>, Shay was married and divorced four times. But Shay, not one to kiss</p>-<p> and</p>-<p> tell, never revealed the identities of her four elusive husbands.</p><p>She is survived by her son, Kenny Kemp, who also briefly appeared on Bling Empire and was featured on <a href="https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/amandachicagolewis/weed-businesses-cant-put-their-money-in-banks-so-they-put-th" target="_blank">BuzzFeed News</a> in 2015 for his extensive collection of bongs and glass pipes valued at half a million dollars (at the time of publication) and stored in his mother's basement.</p><p>Shay told <a href="https://people.com/tv/bling-empire-anna-shay-interview/" target="_blank">People</a> in 2021 that she wasnt expecting Bling Empire to garner so much attention. Did I expect the show to be successful? No. I wasn't even expecting to be in front of the camera. I'm very shy and I went along with whatever situation was happening, she said. I was just being me.</p> Shay was known both for her love of diamonds , and for her pearls of wisdom , which that she dropped on  fellow castmates and during confessionals during her three seasons on the show.  You dont let the clothes wear you, you dont let the car drive you," Shay said. "Dont be impressed by things. I dont get impressed by things, but by people and who they are   .  ... This is not a dress rehearsal, you have to live life to its fullest. 'Crazy Rich Asians': Why the historic Hollywood rom-com matters Despite her opulence, Shay had a down-to-   e arth outlook on life and luxury, and bragging about wealth was one of the heiress' biggest pet peeves.  I think the ones who talk about it dont really have it, <p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/tv/story/2021-01-15/netflix-bling-empire-cast-anna-shay-crazy-rich-asians">she told The Times' Ashley Lee</a></p>  in 2021. Why would you wear something to show it off? My mother came from aristocracy, and my dad came from the South Side of Chicago. They told me that if they ever saw the clothes wearing me or the cars driving me, they would take it all away and never buy anything for me ever again. Im glad they did that. Shay's close friend One of Shays closest friends <p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/florentbonadei" target="_blank">Florent Bonadei</a></p> , a client executive at the Parisian luxury jewelry house Boucheron who was also featured on Bling Empire, spoke with The Times on Monday about Shays untimely passing.  I am so saddened by the loss of Anna Shay. Truly, I would not be where I am today without her friendship," he said. "Anna was as glamorous as she was eccentric. She was incredibly generous with her wealth, but even more so with her love and her loyalty. To be Annas friend was to be invited into a magical world where one day you are eating caviar in Paris and the next night you are watching TV in L.A. on her sofa surrounded by animals, laughter and joy. Her heart was humongous and knew no boundaries. I take some comfort in the fact that so many people had the chance to see how incredibly special Anna Shay was through the show. I will always be incredibly grateful to have the honor to call her my friend. I am sending love to her son and all those who loved her as we all mourn the fabulous, one-of-a-kind Anna.                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beloved artist and professor Jim Melchert taught us the value of paying attention</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-06-05/appreciation-artist-ceramics-professor-uc-berkeley-jim-melchert</link>
      <description>Artist Jim Melchert, who died earlier this month, was a central figure in the Bay Area arts community, as well as a professor and mentor at UC Berkeley.</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2023 19:26:48 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Sharon Mizota</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-06-05/appreciation-artist-ceramics-professor-uc-berkeley-jim-melchert</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-06-05/appreciation-artist-ceramics-professor-uc-berkeley-jim-melchert">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/88ceceb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1349x1174+0+0/resize/320x278!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbf%2F05%2Fe7d9c854476797081198d33fc455%2Funnamed.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/77cd90d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1349x1174+0+0/resize/568x494!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbf%2F05%2Fe7d9c854476797081198d33fc455%2Funnamed.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5255e59/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1349x1174+0+0/resize/768x668!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbf%2F05%2Fe7d9c854476797081198d33fc455%2Funnamed.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/80c93a5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1349x1174+0+0/resize/1024x891!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbf%2F05%2Fe7d9c854476797081198d33fc455%2Funnamed.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9b59f30/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1349x1174+0+0/resize/1200x1044!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbf%2F05%2Fe7d9c854476797081198d33fc455%2Funnamed.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Jim Melchert poses for a photograph."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/34ee913/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1349x1174+0+0/resize/320x278!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbf%2F05%2Fe7d9c854476797081198d33fc455%2Funnamed.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8938823/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1349x1174+0+0/resize/568x494!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbf%2F05%2Fe7d9c854476797081198d33fc455%2Funnamed.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b1dbb86/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1349x1174+0+0/resize/768x668!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbf%2F05%2Fe7d9c854476797081198d33fc455%2Funnamed.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b537e20/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1349x1174+0+0/resize/1024x891!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbf%2F05%2Fe7d9c854476797081198d33fc455%2Funnamed.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/901bf2b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1349x1174+0+0/resize/1200x1044!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbf%2F05%2Fe7d9c854476797081198d33fc455%2Funnamed.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="1044"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/901bf2b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1349x1174+0+0/resize/1200x1044!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fbf%2F05%2Fe7d9c854476797081198d33fc455%2Funnamed.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Jim Melchert poses for a photograph.</div><div class="figure-credit">(Griff Williams/Gallery 16, San Francisco)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Beloved artist and professor Jim Melchert taught us the value of paying attention</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">Museums &amp; Art,Arts</h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" >        Sharon Mizota    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 5, 2023">June 5, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>In 1992, I took an art class in narrative forms at UC Berkeley. The instructor was Jim Melchert, then in his 60s and a central figure in the Bay Area art community. Our primary medium in the class was the photocopy. Every week, we each made an artists book with enough copies for each student to have one. </p><p>Near the end of the semester, Jim (we never called him Professor Melchert) invited our small class over to his house for dinner. Video artist Bill Viola was in town and screened one of his works. Afterward</p>s<p>, buoyed by conviviality, a few of my classmates and I drove around all night, talking and smoking. On the day of our last class, the driver from that night presented the ashtray from his car, overflowing with cigarette butts: gross, yes, but a narrative form we made together, catalyzed by Jim.</p><p>Throughout his career, Jim remained open to serendipity. He created elegant, conceptually driven work in clay, film, photography</p>,<p> and performance, where he embraced experimentation, play</p>,<p> and improvisation. Unfailingly friendly, he was beloved and respected as a teacher and mentor, but his skills extended beyond the studio and the classroom. He was the first artist to serve as </p>V v<p>isual </p>A a<p>rts </p>P p<p>rogram </p>D d<p>irector for the National Endowment for the Arts, and later served as the </p>D d<p>irector of the American Academy in Rome. Jim passed away at the age of 92 on June 1 at his home in Oakland of complications from a stroke. He is survived by his three children, five grandchildren</p>,<p> and three great</p> -<p>grandchildren.</p><p>James Frederick Melchert was born on Dec</p> .ember<p> 2, 1930</p> ,<p> in New Bremen, Ohio. The third and youngest son of Rev</p> .erend<p> John Carl Melchert and Hulda Egli, he graduated with a degree in art history from Princeton University in 1952. Declaring himself a conscientious objector during the Korean War, he was given alternative service teaching English in Sendai, Japan, where he lived for four years. There he met and married Mary Ann Hostetler, the daughter of Mennonite missionaries. They had two sons before moving back to the United States in 1956 so he could pursue a master of fine arts in painting at the University of Chicago. Mary Ann passed away in 2005.</p><p>In Chicago, Melchert was introduced to Abstract Expressionism, the dominant American style of painting at the time, although he worked in a representational style, mostly still lifes. After graduating</p> ,<p> he became the only art instructor at Carthage College, where he was also required to teach ceramics. To keep ahead of his students, Melchert enrolled in a summer class in Missoula, Montana</p> ,<p> taught by Peter Voulkos, who was then radically reshaping ceramic art in an Abstract Expressionist mode. Voulkos made such an impression that in 1959 Melchert became his studio assistant, moving his young family to California, where Voulkos taught at UC Berkeley. Melchert earned a second masters degree in ceramics there.</p><p>In the early 1960s, Melchert taught ceramics and sculpture at the San Francisco Art Institute and immersed himself in the Bay Area art scene, befriending artists such as Carlos Villa, with whom he once shared a studio, Manuel Neri, Nathan Olive</p> i<p>ra</p>,<p> and Joan Brown. Through Voulkos, he also made connections in the L.A. ceramics world, including John Mason, Henry Takemoto</p>,<p> and Michael Frimkess. Melcherts early ceramic work combined qualities of Abstract Expressionism with the eclectic, figurative impulses of the emerging California Funk movement. His sculptures from this time look like whimsical industrial castoffs or colorful</p>,<p> yet mangled theatrical masks, toeing the line between objects and bodies, abstraction and figuration. In 1964</p> ,<p> he joined the art faculty at UC Berkeley, where he taught until </p> his retirement in <p>1994.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/5f/5a/256c9cc549b98f15e78504f5cb3a/unnamed-1.jpg"></figure><p>In the 1970s, Melcherts work began to move in a more conceptual direction, influenced by concrete poetry and the work of composer John Cage. In 1972, he organized a performance called Changes</p>,<p> at Hetty Heisman Studio in Amsterdam, in which he and a group of Dutch artists each dunked their heads in a bucket of wet clay slip and sat on a bench as the slip dried and cracked, becoming a kind of living sculpture.</p><p>In 1976, Melchert left the Bay Area for the National Endowment for the Arts in Washington</p> ,<p> D.C., where he strengthened and diversified grant programs supporting artists and non</p>-<p>profit art spaces. He returned in 1981, but three years later was tapped as director of the American Academy in Rome, where he served until 1988.</p><p>His travels around the Mediterranean led to his interest in ceramic tiles, a preoccupation that lasted for the rest of his life. He was fascinated by the myriad ways a tile cracked when broken, learning from a physicist that the resulting lines and fissures happen</p>ed<p> where molecular bonds were the weakest. He created numerous works in tandem with these cracks, creating abstract designs on broken tiles that could resemble constellations, sound waves</p>,<p> or flowers. He continued making these works and exhibiting until very recently; the last artwork posted on <a href="http://jimmelchert.com/portfolio-items/shards-2-21-22/" target="_blank">his website</a> is Shards 2 dated 2021-22.</p><p>It was in Jims class that I first felt the inkling that there was more to being an artist than simply expressing yourself. It was also about paying attention  looking closely and curiously  and being open to where it might take you. In <a href="https://brooklynrail.org/2020/12/art/JIM-MELCHERT-with-Constance-Lewallen">a 2020 interview</a> with Constance Lewallen for </p>T t<p>he Brooklyn Rail, Melchert said of his broken tile works, Like rivers will take the path of least resistance, so will the energy shooting through a tile</p> . <p> It's a wonderful thing, that you can just liberate something from a material. I loved that.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Roger Broggie Jr. dies at 73; audio-animatronics whiz for Disney</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-me-roger-broggie-20130116-story.html</link>
      <description>Roger Broggie Jr., began work for Walt Disney by tending his backyard railway. He helped give life to Great Moments With Mr. Lincoln and other theme park marvels.</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2013 19:51:17 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Valerie J. Nelson</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-me-roger-broggie-20130116-story.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-me-roger-broggie-20130116-story.html">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c7fa4dd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/600x449+0+0/resize/320x239!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F49%2F67%2F24350ef5cd4fe086b5a189e22876%2Fla-me-2012notables-carey 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7432140/2147483647/strip/true/crop/600x449+0+0/resize/568x425!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F49%2F67%2F24350ef5cd4fe086b5a189e22876%2Fla-me-2012notables-carey 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f8b494f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/600x449+0+0/resize/768x575!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F49%2F67%2F24350ef5cd4fe086b5a189e22876%2Fla-me-2012notables-carey 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7d3e941/2147483647/strip/true/crop/600x449+0+0/resize/1024x766!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F49%2F67%2F24350ef5cd4fe086b5a189e22876%2Fla-me-2012notables-carey 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e17423a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/600x449+0+0/resize/1200x898!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F49%2F67%2F24350ef5cd4fe086b5a189e22876%2Fla-me-2012notables-carey 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="The son of silent-film western star Harry Carey Sr., Carey Jr. was a venerable character actor who was believed to be the last surviving member of director John Ford&#x27;s legendary western stock company. His career spanned more than 50 years and included such Ford classics as &quot;She Wore a Yellow Ribbon&quot; and &quot;The Searchers.&quot; He was 91. Full obituary Notable deaths of 2012"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3ef70f5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/600x449+0+0/resize/320x239!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F49%2F67%2F24350ef5cd4fe086b5a189e22876%2Fla-me-2012notables-carey 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/544de8a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/600x449+0+0/resize/568x425!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F49%2F67%2F24350ef5cd4fe086b5a189e22876%2Fla-me-2012notables-carey 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4c6842a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/600x449+0+0/resize/768x575!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F49%2F67%2F24350ef5cd4fe086b5a189e22876%2Fla-me-2012notables-carey 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9e9d80d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/600x449+0+0/resize/1024x766!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F49%2F67%2F24350ef5cd4fe086b5a189e22876%2Fla-me-2012notables-carey 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b1c69d4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/600x449+0+0/resize/1200x898!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F49%2F67%2F24350ef5cd4fe086b5a189e22876%2Fla-me-2012notables-carey 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="898"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b1c69d4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/600x449+0+0/resize/1200x898!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F49%2F67%2F24350ef5cd4fe086b5a189e22876%2Fla-me-2012notables-carey"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">The son of silent-film western star Harry Carey Sr., Carey Jr. was a venerable character actor who was believed to be the last surviving member of director John Fords legendary western stock company. His career spanned more than 50 years and included such Ford classics as She Wore a Yellow Ribbon and The Searchers. He was 91. <a class="link" href="http://www.latimes.com/news/obituaries/la-me-harry-carey-20121229,0,4888843.story" target="_blank" >Full obituary</a> <br> <a class="link" href="http://www.latimes.com/news/obituaries/la-me-2012notables-gallery,0,1269713.photogallery" target="_blank" ><span class="center_label">Notable deaths of 2012</span></a></div><div class="figure-credit">(Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Roger Broggie Jr. dies at 73; audio-animatronics whiz for Disney</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/valerie-j-nelson">        Valerie J. Nelson    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="Jan. 15, 2013">Jan. 15, 2013</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>The son of Disney's original Imagineer, Roger Broggie Jr. began working for the man he called "Uncle Walt" as a boy in 1950 when he tended the backyard railway at the studio mogul's Holmby Hills home.</p><p> Broggie was 11 when he and his younger brother, Michael, started serving as the crew for Walt Disney's miniature steam-engine railroad. The siblings pulled cars out of storage, dusted them off and rolled them down the track to a "Valley" called Yensid  "Disney" spelled backwards.</p><p> "We had chores," said Michael Broggie, whose father helped Disney build and install the train. "As Dad and Walt got the engine ready, we would fill up the tenders with coal and water."</p><p> The rarefied pastime lasted until 1953, when Disney shut down the train that neighbors had lined up to ride. The small-scale attraction had served a historic purpose, helping to inspire the creation of Disneyland.</p><p> At 18, Roger Broggie Jr. joined Disney's company as an apprentice in the machine shop managed by his father, Roger Broggie Sr. The junior Broggie became an audio-animatronics pioneer, making key contributions to such attractions as Great Moments With Mr. Lincoln, the Enchanted Tiki Room and Pirates of the Caribbean.</p><p> He died Dec. 11 at a medical center in Bend, Ore., from complications of a head injury sustained when he fell while working on a float for a parade near his home in LaPine, Ore. Broggie was 73.</p><p> His family announced his death last week.</p><p> "Roger was one of the finest mechanical craftsmen who ever worked for the company, an absolute master," Marty Sklar, a retired longtime Disney executive, told The Times last week.</p><p> While helping to build several Disney attractions for the 1964 New York's World Fair, Broggie became known for his hands-on technical wizardry while helping to create the now-familiar form of Disney robotics known as audio-animatronics.</p><p> Making President Lincoln lifelike for Great Moments, which debuted at the fair, "was particularly challenging because no one had made a figure move like that before," said his brother Michael, a Disney historian.</p><p> All of the electronic gizmos had to be contained within the framework of the sculpted head, a task that fell to Roger Broggie. An "interesting cheat" solved the problem, according to Jim Hill, who has tracked Disney history for more than 30 years. The wig was stretched out on the Lincoln head to make room for the bulky first-generation parts.</p><p> For the Enchanted Tiki Room, Broggie did an exceptional job building a flock of mechanical exotic birds, Sklar said, and his technical wizardry helped persuade Disney to open the Tiki Room in 1963 as a full-fledged attraction instead of a restaurant.</p><p> Broggie also played a lead role in the development and installation of audio-animatronic figures in Pirates of the Caribbean and the Haunted Mansion, which both opened in the late 1960s.</p><p> Disneyland pays homage to Broggie on Main Street, where his name appears in the window of the Little Gremlins Mechanical Toys shop.</p><p> He was born April 12, 1939, in Los Angeles. His father and mother divorced when he was 12, and he spent his teen years watching Disneyland evolve, playing at the park as a construction site and test-driving cars for the Autopia.</p><p> "They gave the first two prototypes to the Broggie brothers to drive around the lot," according to Hill. "They said, 'If they can't break them, the kids at Disneyland can't break them.'"</p><p> Of the eight Broggies who eventually worked for Disney, six have been Imagineers. Roger Broggie Jr.'s son, Garry, runs the machine shop once operated by his grandfather, who was instrumental to the development of Disneyland's railroad.</p><p> When Disney made the 1969 film "The Love Bug," the junior Broggie's mechanical fascination with cars helped him build "something like 17 Volkswagens" to play the Beetle of the movie's title, his brother said. Each car was made to do a different trick, such as flying or floating.</p><p> In the late 1970s, Broggie founded the Only Animated Display and Design Company with two other former Imagineers. Their projects included developing attractions for Disney and other theme parks and creating mechanisms for Rose Parade floats.</p><p> His technological sleight-of-hand also helped bring a memorable end to the 1984 Summer Olympics when the "spaceship" Broggie helped fabricate appeared to hover over the Los Angeles Coliseum and "converse" in light and sound. The contraption was actually suspended from a helicopter.</p><p> The low-key Broggie "was a really selfless guy," Hill said. "How he died was so in character  doing volunteer work on a Christmas float."</p><p> Broggie is survived by his wife, Marilyn; five children from his first marriage, Scott, Garry, Richard, Robert and Deborah; his brothers, Michael and Brian; 15 grandchildren; and two great-grandchildren.</p><p> A memorial service will be held at 11 a.m. Feb. 2 at Grace Baptist Church, 22833 Copper Hill Drive, Santa Clarita.</p><a href="mailto:valerie.nelson@latimes.com">valerie.nelson@latimes.com</a>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Masao Yoshida dies at 58; led response to Fukushima nuclear disaster</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-xpm-2013-jul-09-la-me-masao-yoshida-20130710-story.html</link>
      <description>Masao Yoshida dies at 58; led response to Fukushima nuclear disaster</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-xpm-2013-jul-09-la-me-masao-yoshida-20130710-story.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-xpm-2013-jul-09-la-me-masao-yoshida-20130710-story.html">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f0fc681/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1600x1170+0+0/resize/320x234!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb8%2F7b%2F337e61aa5f36549064a3d96d271f%2Fla-xpm-photo-2013-jul-09-la-me-masao-yoshida-20130710 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/81eddce/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1600x1170+0+0/resize/568x416!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb8%2F7b%2F337e61aa5f36549064a3d96d271f%2Fla-xpm-photo-2013-jul-09-la-me-masao-yoshida-20130710 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3d388ae/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1600x1170+0+0/resize/768x562!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb8%2F7b%2F337e61aa5f36549064a3d96d271f%2Fla-xpm-photo-2013-jul-09-la-me-masao-yoshida-20130710 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6826c82/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1600x1170+0+0/resize/1024x749!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb8%2F7b%2F337e61aa5f36549064a3d96d271f%2Fla-xpm-photo-2013-jul-09-la-me-masao-yoshida-20130710 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e4b910d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1600x1170+0+0/resize/1200x878!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb8%2F7b%2F337e61aa5f36549064a3d96d271f%2Fla-xpm-photo-2013-jul-09-la-me-masao-yoshida-20130710 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Masao Yoshida, left, talks to former Japanese Prime Minister Yoshihiko Noda, center, at the crippled Fukushima Daiichi nuclear power plant in September 2011. Yoshida led the fight to bring the damaged plant under control after the March 2011 earthquake and tsunami."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b81bfb9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1600x1170+0+0/resize/320x234!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb8%2F7b%2F337e61aa5f36549064a3d96d271f%2Fla-xpm-photo-2013-jul-09-la-me-masao-yoshida-20130710 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9f6239f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1600x1170+0+0/resize/568x416!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb8%2F7b%2F337e61aa5f36549064a3d96d271f%2Fla-xpm-photo-2013-jul-09-la-me-masao-yoshida-20130710 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1171c03/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1600x1170+0+0/resize/768x562!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb8%2F7b%2F337e61aa5f36549064a3d96d271f%2Fla-xpm-photo-2013-jul-09-la-me-masao-yoshida-20130710 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/77e5e4d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1600x1170+0+0/resize/1024x749!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb8%2F7b%2F337e61aa5f36549064a3d96d271f%2Fla-xpm-photo-2013-jul-09-la-me-masao-yoshida-20130710 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/284aad6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1600x1170+0+0/resize/1200x878!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb8%2F7b%2F337e61aa5f36549064a3d96d271f%2Fla-xpm-photo-2013-jul-09-la-me-masao-yoshida-20130710 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="878"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/284aad6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1600x1170+0+0/resize/1200x878!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb8%2F7b%2F337e61aa5f36549064a3d96d271f%2Fla-xpm-photo-2013-jul-09-la-me-masao-yoshida-20130710"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Masao Yoshida, left, talks to former Japanese Prime Minister Yoshihiko Noda, center, at the crippled Fukushima Daiichi nuclear power plant in September 2011. Yoshida led the fight to bring the damaged plant under control after the March 2011 earthquake and tsunami.</div><div class="figure-credit">(Prime ministers office of Japan / EPA)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Masao Yoshida dies at 58; led response to Fukushima nuclear disaster</h1>                                                                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="July 9, 2013">July 9, 2013</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Masao Yoshida, the plant manager who led the fight to bring Japan's Fukushima atomic station under control during the 2011 nuclear disaster, has died. He was 58.</p><p>He died Tuesday of esophagus cancer at a Tokyo hospital, according to a statement from Tokyo Electric Power Co., the operator of the Fukushima Daiichi nuclear plant. The illness was unrelated to the radiation exposure after the nuclear accident, according to the company.</p><p>Yoshida, an engineer by training, directed workers to stop the reactors from overheating after Japan's strongest earthquake on record and an ensuing tsunami hit the plant on March 11, 2011, causing the worst nuclear disaster since Chernobyl. He stayed at the plant, overseeing the disaster response for almost nine months.</p><p>"I cannot imagine how hard it was for him," Tatsujiro Suzuki, vice chairman of the Japan Atomic Energy Commission, said. "He had to make a decision that most of the on-site workers should leave because the situation was getting worse, and he also had to have some of his staff remain to work with him. That was probably the hardest decision he ever had to make."</p><p>Yoshida stepped down from his post on Dec. 1, 2011. Officials from Tepco, as Tokyo Electric is known, disclosed his cancer eight days later.</p><p>"We deeply appreciate his contribution and the way he handled the accident," Tepco President Naomi Hirose said in the statement. "It is very sad that we cannot work together with him to rebuild the company."</p><p>Yoshida was born in Osaka in 1955. After studying nuclear engineering at the Tokyo Institute of Technology, Yoshida joined Tepco in 1979. He was appointed head of the Fukushima Daiichi plant in June 2010.</p><p>As radiation levels spiked in the early days of the crisis, workers were pulled out of the plant  leaving behind those who became known as the Fukushima 50, risking their lives to bring the reactors under control.</p><p>On March 12, a day after the tsunami, Yoshida ignored an order from Tepco headquarters to stop pumping seawater into a reactor to try to cool it because of concerns that ocean water would corrode the equipment.</p><p>Tepco initially said it would penalize Yoshida, even though Sakae Muto, then a vice president at the company, said it was a technically appropriate decision. Yoshida received no more than a verbal reprimand after then-Prime Minister Naoto Kan defended the plant chief, the Yomiuri newspaper reported.</p><p>The 2011 earthquake and tsunami left more than 18,000 people dead or missing and forced the evacuation of 160,000, eventually prompting the idling of all but two of Japan's 50 functioning reactors for safety checks.</p><p>Yoshida thought several times that workers at the plant would die, he told reporters who visited the Fukushima station in November 2011. Yoshida had thought plant operators might completely lose control as the meltdowns accelerated, he told reporters.</p><p>"If Yoshida wasn't there, the disaster could have been much worse," said Reiko Hachisuka, the head of a business group in the town of Okuma, where the station was located, and one of the panel members who investigated the accident. His charisma made "workers at the Fukushima plant believe they could die for Yoshida," she said.</p><p>"He was such a born leader that his subordinates were ready to die alongside him," said Ryusho Kadota, who interviewed Yoshida and other members of the Fukushima 50 for his book, loosely translated as "The Man Who Stared Down Death." "If Yoshida hadn't been plant manager, Tokyo would be a no-man's land right now."</p><a href="mailto:news.obits@latimes.com">news.obits@latimes.com</a>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joanne Carson dies at 83; ex-wife of 'Tonight Show' host</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-me-joanne-carson-20150509-story.html</link>
      <description>She was a struggling model and he was the host of a TV game show who shyly asked her if she wanted to watch some film clips of his comedy.</description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2015 03:56:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>David Colker</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-me-joanne-carson-20150509-story.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-me-joanne-carson-20150509-story.html">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/41008f3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2048x1769+0+0/resize/320x277!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb9%2Fc2%2Fe1f5ad53402e4ec05829d874f588%2Fla-ca-c1-1007-capote-pictures-005 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/17eb54b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2048x1769+0+0/resize/568x491!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb9%2Fc2%2Fe1f5ad53402e4ec05829d874f588%2Fla-ca-c1-1007-capote-pictures-005 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8a3bfe8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2048x1769+0+0/resize/768x664!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb9%2Fc2%2Fe1f5ad53402e4ec05829d874f588%2Fla-ca-c1-1007-capote-pictures-005 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/910f701/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2048x1769+0+0/resize/1024x885!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb9%2Fc2%2Fe1f5ad53402e4ec05829d874f588%2Fla-ca-c1-1007-capote-pictures-005 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/cdcb5b2/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2048x1769+0+0/resize/1200x1037!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb9%2Fc2%2Fe1f5ad53402e4ec05829d874f588%2Fla-ca-c1-1007-capote-pictures-005 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Johnny Carson with wife Joanne in the mid-1960s. Joanne Carson died Friday at age 83."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8dc7232/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2048x1769+0+0/resize/320x277!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb9%2Fc2%2Fe1f5ad53402e4ec05829d874f588%2Fla-ca-c1-1007-capote-pictures-005 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4f252c6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2048x1769+0+0/resize/568x491!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb9%2Fc2%2Fe1f5ad53402e4ec05829d874f588%2Fla-ca-c1-1007-capote-pictures-005 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9e3bb0d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2048x1769+0+0/resize/768x664!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb9%2Fc2%2Fe1f5ad53402e4ec05829d874f588%2Fla-ca-c1-1007-capote-pictures-005 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/47ec85b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2048x1769+0+0/resize/1024x885!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb9%2Fc2%2Fe1f5ad53402e4ec05829d874f588%2Fla-ca-c1-1007-capote-pictures-005 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ac4fe0d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2048x1769+0+0/resize/1200x1037!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb9%2Fc2%2Fe1f5ad53402e4ec05829d874f588%2Fla-ca-c1-1007-capote-pictures-005 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="1037"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ac4fe0d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2048x1769+0+0/resize/1200x1037!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fb9%2Fc2%2Fe1f5ad53402e4ec05829d874f588%2Fla-ca-c1-1007-capote-pictures-005"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption"><p>Johnny Carson with wife Joanne in the mid-1960s. Joanne Carson died Friday at age 83.</p></div><div class="figure-credit">(Getty Images)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Joanne Carson dies at 83; ex-wife of &#x27;Tonight Show&#x27; host </h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/la-bio-david-colker-staff.html">        David Colker    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="May 8, 2015">May 8, 2015</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>She was a struggling model and he was the host of a TV game show who shyly asked her if she wanted to watch some film clips of his comedy.</p><p>It was the first date in 1960 in New York City for the future Joanne Carson and Johnny Carson, long before he became the king of late-night television.</p><p>"Johnny kind of said to me on our first date, 'You love comedy so much, would you like to come up and see a show that I did?'" Joanne Carson said on CNN's "Larry King Live" in 2007.</p><p>"And I said, 'Is this a new way of saying come up and see my etchings?' "</p><p>Johnny Carson turned "bright red," she said, but it was the beginning of a romance and marriage that extended through the years when he vaulted to fame in New York as the host of "The Tonight Show."</p><p>Joanne Carson, 83, who later in life became a close confidant of Truman Capote, died Friday at home in Los Angeles. She had been in declining health and was in hospice care, said Ed Rada, executor of her estate.</p><p><b>For the Record</b></p><p><b>May 9, 5:15 p.m.:</b> An earlier version of this article said Joanne Carson was 84. She was 83 when she died. It also misspelled the name of one of Carson's half sisters as Alters. The correct spelling is&nbsp;Shirlee Alpers.</p><p>Johnny Carson, who hosted "The Tonight Show" from 1962 to 1992, died in 2005.</p><p>Their marriage, which was turbulent at times, lasted from 1963 to 1972, when it ended in divorce. By then, she had moved back to her native California and purchased the home on the fringe of Bel-Air where she lived the rest of her life.</p><p>Several years before they met, Joanne Carson had her own chance to get into show business. In the mid-1950s, she was a Pan Am stewardess and helped calm a passenger in first class listed as Mr. Howard. It turned out to be Howard Hughes.</p><p>A few weeks later, she told the Pittsburgh Post Gazette in 1984, she got a call from Hughes' RKO studio offering her a screen test. She worked at the studio briefly, she said, but turned down a long-term contract and eventually moved to New York.</p><p>The kinescopes that Johnny Carson showed her were from his daytime program, "The Johnny Carson Show," that originated from Los Angeles in the mid-1950s.</p><p>"Johnny said to me, when we were watching the films, 'There's me, without the polish,' " she said in a 2007 Associated Press interview. He was rail-thin and wore ill-fitting suits on the show, but she said he was already poised, charming on screen and hilarious in sketches.</p><p>They were inseparable, she said, but both were opinionated and had tempers, according to friends at the time. "There were a lot of arguments," TV announcer and host Jack Narz said in a 1989 interview with the St. Petersburg Times.</p><p>They married in 1963 and took an apartment at the United Nations Plaza that was home to several celebrities, including, eventually, Capote. Outwardly, the Carsons were a model couple.</p><p>But arguments and accusations flared, friends said. And after a few years, she tired of the celebrity wife life.</p><p>"I was living this ivory tower lifestyle that's not really me," she told Larry King. Eventually, they separated and she moved into a hotel, then back West.</p><p>"I loved Johnny," she told King, "but I really needed to go home. I needed to come back to California."</p><p>Joanne Copeland was born Oct. 20, 1931. She was raised in Los Angeles, but at an early age, her parents' marriage grew rocky and she was sent to a convent school.</p><p>When she was about 9, she moved back in with her father, who had remarried. She said her father introduced her to Carson.</p><p>After the breakup of her marriage, she and Capote grew especially close. He urged her to write an autobiography and she started on it. "I was going to write a lovely story about my friendship with all these people," she said in a Times interview last year. Capote even edited, heavily, a sample chapter.</p><p>But a book editor assigned to the project wanted dirt on celebrities, and she wasn't willing to do that.</p><p>"When I saw the 'dishy' kind of autobiographies selling in the '80s, I knew my simple book of friendships would not be interesting."</p><p>Capote had a writing room at her house. He died there Aug. 25, 1984, at the age of 59.</p><p>Joanne Carson worked as a television talk show host for a time and supported several causes, including those that involved care for dogs. She auctioned off several pieces of memorabilia, including some related to Capote and to her former husband.</p><p>In 2006, she found, in the back of a wine cabinet where they had been stored for many years, the films of "The Johnny Carson Show" with which he had wooed her. She had them converted to DVDs and made available to the public.</p><p>Joanne Carson had a second marriage late in her life to Richard Rever that also ended in divorce. She had no children and is survived by two half sisters, Barbara Abernathy and Shirlee Alpers.</p><a href="mailto:david.colker@latimes.com">david.colker@latimes.com</a>Twitter&nbsp;<a href="https://twitter.com/davidcolker" target="_blank">@davidcolker</a>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>James Kavanaugh dies at 81; former Catholic priest wrote book calling for church reform</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-xpm-2010-jan-09-la-me-james-kavanaugh9-2010jan09-story.html</link>
      <description>James Kavanaugh dies at 81; former Catholic priest wrote book calling for church reform</description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2010 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-xpm-2010-jan-09-la-me-james-kavanaugh9-2010jan09-story.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-xpm-2010-jan-09-la-me-james-kavanaugh9-2010jan09-story.html">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                                            <h1>James Kavanaugh dies at 81; former Catholic priest wrote book calling for church reform</h1>                                                                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="Jan. 9, 2010">Jan. 9, 2010</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p> James Kavanaugh, a former Catholic priest who came to fame in 1967 with his controversial bestseller calling for reform in the church and later wrote bestselling books of poetry and other works, has died. He was 81.</p><p> Kavanaugh, who underwent surgery for an aortic aneurysm in July, died Dec. 29 in a hospice in Kalamazoo, Mich., said his wife, Cathy.</p><p> Ordained in 1954, Kavanaugh served as a parish priest in Lansing and Flint, Mich., and earned a doctorate at the Catholic University of America in Washington, D.C., before the publication of "A Modern Priest Looks at His Outdated Church" in 1967.</p><p> The book, in which he called for church reforms on issues such as birth control, divorce, premarital sex and celibacy for priests, quickly became a national bestseller.</p><p> A New York Times reviewer called it "a personal cry of anguish that goes to the heart of the troubles plaguing the Catholic Church."</p><p> "I was naive enough to think that 'Modern Priest' would turn things around in the church and that I could still stay in the priesthood," Kavanaugh told the San Diego Union-Tribune in 1984. "I had no idea the book would have the impact it did."</p><p> Look magazine purchased the serial rights, and Kavanaugh made the rounds of talk shows, including Johnny Carson's "Tonight Show." He also was in great demand to speak on college campuses around the country.</p><p> The book followed up an article Kavanaugh had written for the Saturday Evening Post's "Speaking Out" page. Written under the pseudonym Father Stephen Nash, it was titled "I am a Priest and I Want to Marry."</p><p> The article reportedly generated "Speaking Out's" heaviest reader response, and the magazine forwarded the missives to Kavanaugh.</p><p> "He got so many thousands of letters, it filled up half my garage," recalled his brother, Dr. Philip Kavanaugh.</p><p> The vast majority of the letters were positive, he said, "the most notable" being one from "Dear Abby" advice columnist Abigail Van Buren.</p><p> "She wrote a brief letter saying, 'I've received hundreds of thousands of letters, but this is the first fan letter I've ever written,' " he said.</p><p> For both the clergy and the laity, Philip Kavanaugh said, "Jim was a spiritual permission-giver to question authority and to trust their own instincts and beliefs. It had been suppressed previously in the church."</p><p> Kavanaugh left the priesthood several months after his book's publication.</p><p> "He resigned formally on the stage at Notre Dame University," where he was delivering a speech to a large audience made up mostly of priests and nuns, said Philip Kavanaugh. At one point, "he ripped off his collar, threw it on the ground, stamped on it and said, 'I will never wear this again!' "</p><p> In a 1985 interview with The Times, James Kavanaugh explained that midway through his talk at Notre Dame, "I got carried away. . . . The church had done a lot of damage to people's personal lives, and I felt compelled to say so."</p><p> In the early '70s, Kavanaugh published his first book of poetry, the bestselling "There Are Men Too Gentle to Live Among Wolves."</p><p> "I am one of the searchers," he wrote in the prologue. "There are, I believe, millions of us. We are not unhappy, but neither are we really content. We continue to explore life, hoping to uncover its ultimate secret."</p><p> Kavanaugh's spiritual journey began in Kalamazoo, Mich., where he was born Sept. 17, 1928.</p><p> The fourth of seven sons of an Irish Catholic family, he entered St. Joseph's <b></b>Seminary in Grand Rapids at age 15. (His brother, Robert, also became a priest, and they both left the priesthood within a month of each other).</p><p> Kavanaugh published more than two dozen books, including works of poetry, nonfiction and allegories ("Celebrate the Sun: A Love Story" and "A Village Called Harmony -- A Fable") and two novels ("A Coward for Them All" and "The Celibates").</p><p> Kavanaugh, who suffered bouts of depression over the years, was not a big fan of self-help books.</p><p> "I burn all self-help books or tapes in which hyped heroes tell me how easy it is to put one's life together," he wrote in the newsletter of the James Kavanaugh Institute, which was launched in the early '80s to promote his inspirational book "Search: A Guide for Those Who Dare to Ask of Life Everything Good and Beautiful" and associated workshops.</p><p> "I need those who are still wading through pain, who must struggle at times just to hang on," he wrote. "I don't believe in quick fixes and I'm outraged when anyone promises one."</p><p> In addition to his wife and brother Philip, the twice-divorced Kavanaugh is survived by a stepdaughter, Katherine Markel; a stepson from a previous marriage, Chris Grove; and brothers Dr. Thomas Kavanaugh and Dr. Daniel Kavanaugh.</p><p> A <a href="https://james-kavanaugh.memory-of.com/About.aspx">virtual memorial service</a> is online at </p>james-kavanaugh.memory-of.com<p>.</p><p> <a href="mailto:dennis.mclellan@latimes.com">dennis.mclellan@latimes.com</a></p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pioneering L.A. performance artist Rachel Rosenthal dies at 88</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-me-ln-performance-artist-rachel-rosenthal-dies-88-20150512-story.html</link>
      <description>Pioneering performance artist Rachel Rosenthal wasn’t out to simply shock audiences, though her performances were filled with arresting moments.</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 02:08:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>David Colker</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-me-ln-performance-artist-rachel-rosenthal-dies-88-20150512-story.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-me-ln-performance-artist-rachel-rosenthal-dies-88-20150512-story.html">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c3ca1d7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1255x798+0+0/resize/320x203!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F3c%2F60%2F9982606d5b7bfdfcfbbdd2aea4dc%2Fla-me-ln-rachel-rosenthal-d-001 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0879f0d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1255x798+0+0/resize/568x361!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F3c%2F60%2F9982606d5b7bfdfcfbbdd2aea4dc%2Fla-me-ln-rachel-rosenthal-d-001 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0afce2b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1255x798+0+0/resize/768x488!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F3c%2F60%2F9982606d5b7bfdfcfbbdd2aea4dc%2Fla-me-ln-rachel-rosenthal-d-001 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8cf055c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1255x798+0+0/resize/1024x651!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F3c%2F60%2F9982606d5b7bfdfcfbbdd2aea4dc%2Fla-me-ln-rachel-rosenthal-d-001 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/14e6ed0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1255x798+0+0/resize/1200x763!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F3c%2F60%2F9982606d5b7bfdfcfbbdd2aea4dc%2Fla-me-ln-rachel-rosenthal-d-001 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Rachel Rosenthal&#x27;s last solo performance."                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/77db33b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1255x798+0+0/resize/320x203!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F3c%2F60%2F9982606d5b7bfdfcfbbdd2aea4dc%2Fla-me-ln-rachel-rosenthal-d-001 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c8dafc5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1255x798+0+0/resize/568x361!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F3c%2F60%2F9982606d5b7bfdfcfbbdd2aea4dc%2Fla-me-ln-rachel-rosenthal-d-001 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3dae3bb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1255x798+0+0/resize/768x488!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F3c%2F60%2F9982606d5b7bfdfcfbbdd2aea4dc%2Fla-me-ln-rachel-rosenthal-d-001 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f1369d6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1255x798+0+0/resize/1024x651!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F3c%2F60%2F9982606d5b7bfdfcfbbdd2aea4dc%2Fla-me-ln-rachel-rosenthal-d-001 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/43d399f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1255x798+0+0/resize/1200x763!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F3c%2F60%2F9982606d5b7bfdfcfbbdd2aea4dc%2Fla-me-ln-rachel-rosenthal-d-001 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="763"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/43d399f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1255x798+0+0/resize/1200x763!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F3c%2F60%2F9982606d5b7bfdfcfbbdd2aea4dc%2Fla-me-ln-rachel-rosenthal-d-001"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption"><p>Rachel Rosenthals last solo performance.</p> </div><div class="figure-credit">(Clarence Williams)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Pioneering L.A. performance artist Rachel Rosenthal dies at 88</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/la-bio-david-colker-staff.html">        David Colker    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="May 12, 2015">May 12, 2015</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Pioneering performance artist Rachel Rosenthal wasnt out to simply shock audiences, though her performances were filled with arresting moments.</p><p>She had hot wax poured over her shaved head, buried herself in artificial snow, read alternately from the ancient Kabbalah and car magazines, and shared the stage with more than 40 animals,&nbsp; including her beloved pet rat, who could often be found perched on her shoulder when she was off-stage.</p><p>But no matter how varied her performances  which ranged from solo pieces to ones that had 50 actors  her politically flavored works, spiked with humor, had an overriding theme.</p><p>Its about our relationship to the Earth. It deals with who we are as a species and how we belong on this planet, she said in a 1995 Times interview.</p><p>And what was her assessment of that relationship?</p><p>In a word, lousy.</p><p>Rosenthal, 88, who was performing well into her 70s, died Sunday at her home in West Los Angeles. She had been in declining health and died of congestive heart failure, said Kate Noonan, managing director of the Rachel Rosenthal Company, which presents improvised works.</p><p>Noonan said Rosenthal, though frail, attended a company rehearsal as recently as last week.</p><p>Rosenthal, who cut an exotic figure with her bald head (she had it shaved during a 1981 performance and kept it that way), colorful makeup and multiple earrings, was a familiar presence on the arts scene in Los Angeles, especially in the 1970s, 1980s and 1990s when she performed at a variety of venues, including the Museum of Contemporary Art.</p><p>She also presented works in numerous cities in Europe and in New York, where her Rachels Brain won an off-Broadway Obie award in 1989.</p><p>Her pieces made feminist statements and took up the cause of animal rights  Rosenthal was known to leave rehearsals to help find a home for an abandoned pet.</p><p>Her impassioned works didnt always get great reviews, but even critics who found her pieces disjointed praised her ability to create moments of stillness among chaos.</p><p>When she grabs your attention for individual fragments of the narrative, Nancy Churnin wrote in The Times in 1991 in a review of Rosenthals Pangaean Dreams, she grabs it and shakes it like Jove playing with thunderbolts.</p><p>Writing in the New York Times about the same work, Stephen Holden said, Rosenthal can be growlingly ominous.... She can also be very funny.</p><p>Typical of Rosenthal, the piece  which was performed in Los Angeles, San Diego, New York and other cities  drew from a panoply of narratives, weaving together Earth geography before the breakup of the continents, her own aging body, birth, death and the Persian Gulf War.</p><p>Rosenthal often used projections, movies and sound imaging in the pieces. They all came together at a point in Pangaean Dreams in which she held a white robe around her head that suddenly became a screen for projections.</p><p>As the images of the Earth move around that head, Churnin wrote, one gets an impression of one person as a distinct island in a world of movement.</p><p>Movement was always a primary factor for Rosenthal. She was born in Paris on Nov. 9, 1926, into a wealthy Russian Jewish family. Her father was a successful gem merchant and one of the top philanthropists in the country.</p><p>But during World War II, the family fled the Nazis, losing much of its fortune. The Rosenthals landed in Portugal, then Rio de Janeiro and finally in New York, where Rachel Rosenthal graduated from the High School of Music and Art.</p><p>She was a dancer and fell in with an avant garde crowd at a time of artistic fervent in the 1950s. She grew close to painters Robert Rauschenberg and Jasper Johns, and joined the dance company headed by Merce Cunningham.</p><p>The person who most influenced her was composer and writer John Cage. She was drawn to his creations derived from chance operations, including the I Ching.</p><p>Chance is very risky for some people, she said in a 2009 Times interview. To feel comfortable with chance gives you a one-upmanship over the lot. It gives you courage; you are not afraid to make mistakes.</p><p>When she came to Los Angeles in the mid-1950s, she started a theater group, Instant Theatre, that used chance operations to create performances not only for adults, but also for children. Indeed, it was the childrens performances that sustained the company, financially, during its decade-long run.</p><p>Her more edgy work began in the 1970s. Although her works were generally seen by only a few hundred people at a time, Rosenthal was also seen by millions by picking up occasional roles on television sitcoms and other programs. She played an artist, for laughs, on Frasier in 1993, a tarot card reader on Ellen in 1998 and even had a part in the western The Virginian in 1970.</p><p>She didnt go out and audition, Noonan said. People would think of her and ask her to appear, and she always said yes. She had a great time.</p><p>Rosenthals marriage to actor King Moody ended in divorce and she had no immediate family survivors. Her last dog, Fanny, will be cared for by Noonan.</p><p>david.colker@latimes.com</p><p>&nbsp;</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marc Christian MacGinnis dies at 56; Rock Hudson's ex-lover</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-me-marc-christian5-2009dec05-story.html</link>
      <description>He won a multimillion-dollar settlement in 1991 from the actor's estate after convincing a jury that Hudson had knowingly exposed him to AIDS.</description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2009 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Elaine Woo</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-me-marc-christian5-2009dec05-story.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/local/obituaries/la-me-marc-christian5-2009dec05-story.html">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a4a94bd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/300x432+0+0/resize/320x461!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7c%2Fc6%2F10a2dc78164602f24088b8cb3e62%2Fla-me-marc-christian-ku5ap0nc 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/124b64f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/300x432+0+0/resize/568x818!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7c%2Fc6%2F10a2dc78164602f24088b8cb3e62%2Fla-me-marc-christian-ku5ap0nc 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1285973/2147483647/strip/true/crop/300x432+0+0/resize/768x1106!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7c%2Fc6%2F10a2dc78164602f24088b8cb3e62%2Fla-me-marc-christian-ku5ap0nc 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6fe18e4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/300x432+0+0/resize/1024x1475!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7c%2Fc6%2F10a2dc78164602f24088b8cb3e62%2Fla-me-marc-christian-ku5ap0nc 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ed89361/2147483647/strip/true/crop/300x432+0+0/resize/1200x1728!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7c%2Fc6%2F10a2dc78164602f24088b8cb3e62%2Fla-me-marc-christian-ku5ap0nc 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Marc Christian, seen in 1989, never developed AIDS. His sister says he died as a result of his heavy smoking, which began in 1998, &quot;the day he found out Frank Sinatra died. He loved Frank Sinatra.&quot;"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/935d8fc/2147483647/strip/true/crop/300x432+0+0/resize/320x461!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7c%2Fc6%2F10a2dc78164602f24088b8cb3e62%2Fla-me-marc-christian-ku5ap0nc 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/20cbd10/2147483647/strip/true/crop/300x432+0+0/resize/568x818!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7c%2Fc6%2F10a2dc78164602f24088b8cb3e62%2Fla-me-marc-christian-ku5ap0nc 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/00969bd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/300x432+0+0/resize/768x1106!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7c%2Fc6%2F10a2dc78164602f24088b8cb3e62%2Fla-me-marc-christian-ku5ap0nc 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8f8336e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/300x432+0+0/resize/1024x1475!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7c%2Fc6%2F10a2dc78164602f24088b8cb3e62%2Fla-me-marc-christian-ku5ap0nc 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/17baa99/2147483647/strip/true/crop/300x432+0+0/resize/1200x1728!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7c%2Fc6%2F10a2dc78164602f24088b8cb3e62%2Fla-me-marc-christian-ku5ap0nc 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="1728"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/17baa99/2147483647/strip/true/crop/300x432+0+0/resize/1200x1728!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7c%2Fc6%2F10a2dc78164602f24088b8cb3e62%2Fla-me-marc-christian-ku5ap0nc"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Marc Christian, seen in 1989, never developed AIDS. His sister says he died as a result of his heavy smoking, which began in 1998, the day he found out Frank Sinatra died. He loved Frank Sinatra.</div><div class="figure-credit">(Kirk McKoy / Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Marc Christian MacGinnis dies at 56; Rock Hudson&#x27;s ex-lover</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/la-bio-elaine-woo-staff.html">        Elaine Woo    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="Dec. 5, 2009">Dec. 5, 2009</time>                                                                    </header>                     Marc Christian MacGinnis, who won a multimillion-dollar settlement in 1991 from the estate of his ex-lover, actor Rock Hudson, after convincing a jury Hudson had knowingly exposed him to AIDS, has died. He was 56.  Known as Marc Christian, he died of pulmonary problems June 2 at Providence Saint Joseph Medical Center in Burbank. The details were confirmed Friday by his sister, Susan Dahl, who said  <a href="https://latimesblogs.latimes.com/afterword/2009/12/marc-christian-rock-hudsons-ex-an-update.html">she did not publicly announce his death earlier</a> because of her brother's wish for privacy.  Christian, who went by his mother's maiden name, made headlines in 1985 when he sued Hudson's estate and his secretary, Mark Miller, for $10 million, alleging that he had suffered severe emotional distress after hearing on a news broadcast that the former matinee idol and television star had AIDS, which was claiming lives throughout the gay community.  Hudson was diagnosed in 1984 but did not publicly acknowledge his illness until July 1985; he died three months later at age 59. Christian tested negative for acquired immune deficiency syndrome several times after learning of Hudson's diagnosis but contended that the star put him at risk of contracting the disease by concealing his illness and continuing to have sexual relations with him. Christian included Miller in the suit because he said Miller lied to him when asked if Hudson had AIDS.  In 1989, a Los Angeles County Superior Court jury said Hudson had displayed "outrageous conduct" and awarded Christian $21.75 million in damages, later reduced to $5.5 million. The $5.5-million award was upheld by a state Court of Appeal, which called it just compensation for the "ultimate in personal horror, the fear of slow, agonizing death."  After the California Supreme Court, citing requests from both sides in the dispute, decided not to hear the case, a private settlement was reached for an amount Christian later said was less than $6 million.  He was portrayed by Hudson estate lawyers as a gold-digging hustler and criticized in the gay community, which at the time had little understanding of the need for sexual responsibility.  "It was obviously a groundbreaking case," said Tammy Bruce, a former president of the National Organization for Women's Los Angeles chapter and an openly gay conservative talk-show host. "It was the first public acknowledgment that gay relationships are complicated, important, and that responsibility is attached to them. . . . A lot of people owe a great deal to that man and the way he handled it with particular grace, not only at the trial but in the years afterward."  Several years after the sensational case ended, Christian told People magazine that his purpose was "not to sleaze Rock. It was to say that if you have AIDS, you ought to tell your partner, whether you're a movie star or a postman."  He later often found himself defending Hudson's reputation against those who viewed the late actor's conduct as reprehensible. "You can't dismiss a man's whole life with a single act. This thing about AIDS was totally out of character for him," Christian said in the People interview.  Christian was born in Hollywood on June 23, 1953, and grew up in Orange County. After graduating from Villa Park High School, he attended Cal State Fullerton, where he earned a business degree.  After college, he worked as a waiter and learned about sound engineering, his sister said. He was interested in acting, but his two greatest passions were music and politics.  Christian met Hudson in late 1982 at a fundraiser for then-senatorial candidate Gore Vidal.  "I heard this voice, 'Where the hell's the booze?' I turned and saw Rock Hudson standing next to me," he testified in 1989.  He and Hudson became lovers about five months later. By late 1983, they were living together in Hudson's Beverly Hills mansion.  When Hudson began losing weight and looking ill, he told Christian, who was about 27 years his junior, that he was merely dieting; later, associates said he was anorexic.  Christian said he learned the true cause of his partner's increasing gauntness the way the rest of the world did -- from a 1985 television broadcast from Paris, where Hudson had flown to seek treatment for AIDS.  "I thought I was a dead man," Christian recalled thinking at the time.  He tested negative for the disease after several tests. Told by medical experts that the best treatment would cost $100,000 a year with a life expectancy of three years, he approached Hudson's managers after the actor's death and asked them to place $300,000 in a trust fund to cover his care if he developed AIDS, with the funds returning to the estate if he remained AIDS-free.  When the managers turned him down, "That's when he went to Marvin Mitchelson," the famous palimony attorney who filed the lawsuit against Hudson's estate, said Brent Beckwith, who was Christian's lover and best friend for nine years.  After the settlement, Christian bought and renovated a mid-century modern house in the Hollywood Hills, filling it with his collection of musical instruments, antique Edison phonographs and tens of thousands of vintage 78s, LPs and CDs. He restored old recordings and was famous among friends for his ability to name almost any tune.  Contrary to Internet reports that said he had died of drug abuse or AIDS, which he never developed, Christian's death was the result of his heavy smoking, which began in 1998, "the day he found out Frank Sinatra died," Dahl said. "He loved Frank Sinatra."   <a href="mailto:elaine.woo@latimes.com">elaine.woo@latimes.com</a>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
