<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>World &amp; Nation</title>
    <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation</link>
    <description>World &amp; Nation</description>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 20:48:09 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation.rss" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" />
    <item>
      <title>Mexico sets new work-from-home rules, including that employers pay for internet</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/mexico-sets-new-work-from-home-rules-including-that-employers-pay-internet</link>
      <description>Mexico's Labor Department has issued new rules requiring employers to pay for internet and provide ergonomic chairs for employees working from home.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 20:48:09 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/mexico-sets-new-work-from-home-rules-including-that-employers-pay-internet</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/mexico-sets-new-work-from-home-rules-including-that-employers-pay-internet">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                                            <h1>Mexico sets new work-from-home rules, including that employers pay for internet</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">Mexico &amp; the Americas</h3>                                                                                                    <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Mexicos Labor Department issued new rules Friday requiring employers to pay for internet </p> service<p> and provide <a href="https://www.latimes.com/business/newsletter/2020-07-28/work-from-home-tax-write-off-business">ergonomic chairs</a> for employees working from home. </p><p>The new rules also mandate a right to disconnect for employees who work at least 40% of their time from remote locations. Remote workers often complain that, because they are constantly reachable at home, they are also constantly asked to work.</p><p>Mexico, like many other countries, saw a big increase in remote working during the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020 and 2021. While office space occupancy is inching back up, remote work seems to be a trend that has caught on. </p><p>The trend is so pronounced that some office buildings on bustling downtown boulevards are being converted into apartments, hospitals and stores.</p><p>The Labor Department said bosses are responsible for paying for the electricity, printers and other equipment used when working at home. According to the new rules, if an employee's home isn't safe, well-</p> lightedlit <p>and well-ventilated, they can't be forced to work there.</p><p>Inspectors can visit a worker's home, or employees may be asked to take pictures of their home, to prove that it meets labor requirements. </p><p>Remote workers cannot be paid less than those who go to an office, and they must have set work hours.</p><p>According to the commercial real estate firm Newmark, Mexico City's office market has shown slight signs of recovery since the pandemic. In a first-quarter 2023 research report, it said the city's office vacancy rate had declined to 23.4%, from 24.5% one year ago.</p><p>As in many parts of the world, some employers have adopted a mixed or hybrid model in which workers come into the office only part of the week. The new rules apply only to those who work remotely at least 40% of the week.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The coronavirus has made itself at home in animals. Why that ramps up the risk for people</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/science/story/2023-06-09/coronavirus-is-spreading-among-animals-that-ramps-up-risk-to-people</link>
      <description>Coronavirus infections have been found in at  least 32 animal species in 39 countries. Some can transmit the virus to humans.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 13:00:32 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/science/story/2023-06-09/coronavirus-is-spreading-among-animals-that-ramps-up-risk-to-people</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One party has governed Mexico's biggest state for a century. It looks as if that is about to change</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-04/mexico-pri-amlo-morena</link>
      <description>Sunday’s election for governor of the state of Mexico could spell the end of the long-dominant Institutional Revolutionary Party and further cement the dominancy of President Andrés Manuel López Obrador’s Morena party.</description>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2023 10:00:18 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Kate Linthicum</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-04/mexico-pri-amlo-morena</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-04/mexico-pri-amlo-morena">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c6a037b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F55%2Fb9%2F209b1ccb410ea45deee5cd4a4212%2Fmexico-election-16893.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/270de5b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F55%2Fb9%2F209b1ccb410ea45deee5cd4a4212%2Fmexico-election-16893.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/bb580fb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F55%2Fb9%2F209b1ccb410ea45deee5cd4a4212%2Fmexico-election-16893.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/69a43fe/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F55%2Fb9%2F209b1ccb410ea45deee5cd4a4212%2Fmexico-election-16893.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3c9b7ac/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F55%2Fb9%2F209b1ccb410ea45deee5cd4a4212%2Fmexico-election-16893.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Delfina Gomez, left, MORENA political party gubernatorial candidate, greets supporters as she campaigns in Valle de Chalco, Mexico, Sunday, May 28, 2023. Voters in the state of Mexico go to the polls on June 4 to elect a new governor. (AP Photo/Marco Ugarte)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/eaa74df/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F55%2Fb9%2F209b1ccb410ea45deee5cd4a4212%2Fmexico-election-16893.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/924b54e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F55%2Fb9%2F209b1ccb410ea45deee5cd4a4212%2Fmexico-election-16893.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a2bc817/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F55%2Fb9%2F209b1ccb410ea45deee5cd4a4212%2Fmexico-election-16893.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8ff63d4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F55%2Fb9%2F209b1ccb410ea45deee5cd4a4212%2Fmexico-election-16893.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c4eac78/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F55%2Fb9%2F209b1ccb410ea45deee5cd4a4212%2Fmexico-election-16893.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c4eac78/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F55%2Fb9%2F209b1ccb410ea45deee5cd4a4212%2Fmexico-election-16893.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Delfina Gomez, left, MORENA political party gubernatorial candidate, greets supporters as she campaigns in Valle de Chalco, Mexico, Sunday, May 28, 2023. Voters in the state of Mexico go to the polls on June 4 to elect a new governor. (AP Photo/Marco Ugarte)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Marco Ugarte / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>One party has governed Mexico&#x27;s biggest state for a century. It looks as if that is about to change</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">Mexico &amp; the Americas</h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/kate-linthicum">        Kate Linthicum    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 4, 2023">June 4, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>For nearly a century, one party has governed Mexico's most populous state.</p><p>The Institutional Revolutionary Party, known as the PRI, dominated political life in Mexico for decades by rigging elections, buying off labor unions and suppressing dissent. Even after its nationwide </p> monopoly <p>was <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-2000-jul-03-mn-47441-story.html">broken</a> in 2000, the party</p> <p>maintained a tight grip on power here in the state of</p> <p>Mexico.</p><p>But in gubernatorial elections </p>this<p> Sunday, what was long seen as unthinkable is now widely expected: </p>t<p> The party will lose one of its last strongholds.</p><p>"The extinction of the PRI," as the Mexican media have </p>has <p>been putting it, seems in some ways the inevitable result of its long history of corruption and the self-enrichment of its leaders.</p><p>Multiple former PRI governors in other parts of the country have been convicted of graft in recent years, and a news <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2023/may/31/mexico-corruption-journalist-investigation-kidnapped" target="_blank">report</a> last </p>this time element <p>week implicated the current governor of the state of Mexico in a $300-million embezzlement scheme.</p><p>"They made themselves millionaires," said Vito Baltazar, a 66-year-old retiree. "They governed only for themselves."</p><p>But perhaps a bigger factor in the demise of the PRI is the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2022-06-06/mexico-president-lopez-obrador-party-wins-governorships">swift rise</a> of Morena, the party that Baltazar said he plans to vote for.</p><p>Founded less than a decade ago, the party has taken over much of Mexico. It boasts a wide majority in both chambers of Congress, and with a win in the race for governor here, the party and its allies will control </p>23 22<p> of Mexico's </p>32 31<p> states</p> , along with the federal district of&nbsp;Mexico City.<p> The PRI will </p> probablylikely<p> be left with just two.</p><p>Morena has become so dominant that some critics warn that it is ushering Mexico into </p>to<p> a new kind of one-party rule  or perhaps one-man rule.</p><p>The party's success rests squarely</p> <p>on its founder, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world/la-fg-mexico-election-20171211-story.html">President Andrs Manuel Lpez Obrador</a>, the populist widely known as AMLO whose vows to combat corruption and put the poor first have inspired a <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2022-12-19/why-is-mexicos-amlo-one-of-the-worlds-most-popular-politicians-we-took-a-road-trip-to-find-out">fervent following</a>.</p><p>"AMLO could put a sock puppet up as a candidate and the sock puppet would win," said Carlos Bravo Regidor, a professor at </p> the Center for Economic Research and Teaching, CIDE, <p>a public </p>research center institution <p>in Mexico City. "This is obviously about AMLO and the intensity of his support."</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/04/12/db91e5bc43e5a50226a42b2be297/https-delivery-gettyimages.com/downloads/1069526286"></figure><p>That seemed clear at a Morena campaign rally on a cloudy morning last week</p>wednesday 5/31<p> in Jilotepec, a small town </p>a few hours <p>north of Mexico City.</p><p>The president's </p> pictureimage <p> tan skin, silver hair, prominent front teeth  was everywhere, printed on T-shirts, pins and bags. Vendors hawked AMLO dolls as attendees sporadically broke out into chants of "it's an honor to be with Obrador." </p><p>Many in the crowd acknowledged that they didn't know much about the gubernatorial candidate, Delfina Gmez, a former schoolteacher and mayor who was once fined by election officials for docking the pay of city workers to raise cash for Morena.</p><p>Still, polls show Gmez with a double-digit lead over Alejandra del Moral, a lifelong </p> member of the <p>PRI</p> , whichmember whose party <p>has held the governorship for 94 years straight. </p> GmezShe <p>is running with a coalition of parties that once opposed the PRI, including the center-right National Action Party and the leftist Party of the Democratic Revolution. </p><p>That three former enemies have now united in an attempt to defeat Morena says a lot about how the political landscape in Mexico has shifted since Lpez Obrador swept into power in 2018. </p><p>That year, his party won big nationally and made significant inroads at the local level in the state of Mexico. Morena won even in Atlacomulco, the municipality whose name has long been synonymous with a group of PRI elites, including former President Enrique Pea Nieto.</p><p>There have been a lot of presidents that have come from here, but what have they done for us? asked Katy Montoya, 40, a street vendor of sweet bread in Atlacomulco who voted against the PRI for the first time in 2018 and who plans to support Gmez on Sunday. </p><p>Like many Mexicans, her favorite policy change under Lpez Obrador is a program that sends cash welfare payments to students, young workers and the elderly. "It's given them dignity," she said of older Mexicans. "With the money they get from the government, they can fix up their homes or come here and buy bread."</p><p>Support for Lpez Obrador tends to fall along class lines, which helps explain why Morena is so far ahead in polling in the state of Mexico. </p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/9b/1b/18d6260d422b974b5373d14d4d47/dji-0838.jpg"></figure><p>A sprawling patchwork of suburbs, urban slums, farmland and industry, the state is home to 1 in 8 Mexicans and is an economic powerhouse, contributing 9% to the country's GDP. </p><p>Yet it is also plagued by crime and hardship, with nearly half of residents living below the poverty line and 9 in 10 reporting that they feel unsafe.</p><p>"We obviously need a change," said Reina Isabel Reyes, a 22-year-old teacher who like many people here has been the victim of armed robbery on public transportation. "We just want peace."</p><p>The PRI, meanwhile, has become a party of people who are fearful of the change that Lpez Obrador seems to represent.</p><p>Catalina Plata Arzate, a 71-year-old resident of Atlacomulco, said she would be voting for the PRI candidate </p>on<p> Sunday "because I'm middle class." She suggested that Lpez Obrador's expansion of entitlement programs was leading the country toward communism.</p><p>Its all the people from the bottom who vote for him," Plata said. They all think hes the second coming. But we dont want another Venezuela. </p><p>With the PRI likely headed for defeat and the opposition </p>in a<p> shambles, many have wondered what it means that Mexico is again dominated by one party. </p><p>"We do seem to be heading in a way towards a new hegemony," Bravo said</p> .<p>While noting that Morena has won its elections democratically, without the vote-rigging of the PRI, he and other analysts say that the lack of well-organized opposition isn't healthy for the country.</p><p>Many of Lpez Obrador's proposals have sailed through Congress</p> <p>largely unchallenged, including a controversial measure to keep the army on the streets until 2028, part of the president's <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world/mexico-americas/la-fg-mexico-military-law-20171215-story.html">larger push</a> toward militarization. </p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/4a/0f/cadce018441e8e0e06ac22f346e0/https-delivery.gettyimages.com/downloads/1176565074.jpg"></figure><p>The</p> <p>only thing standing in his way on many issues is the Supreme Court, which Lpez Obrador has relentlessly attacked as part of an antidemocratic "mafia of power" that rules in favor of the rich. It's a criticism he tends to levy against anyone, </p>from  be it a <p>journalist</p>sto  or<p> member</p>s<p> of civil society, who </p> dares deign <p>to critique him. </p><p>The president's recent efforts to overhaul the country's electoral institute  which critics say would reduce its autonomy and concentrate power in the hands of the ruling party  prompted cries of authoritarianism. At a march in Mexico City opposing the changes, some people held signs calling Lpez Obrador a dictator. Others compared him to the PRI. </p><p>"I had to live when the PRI was the only party that governed, and we all suffered," said Rosa Maria Velazquez, a 52-year-old who manages a sports club. "AMLO is doing the same. He wants to return Mexico to an old, retrograde, undemocratic country where a single party ruled."</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/14/32/f9eb646345a79524ce6060bbe2a6/mexico-us-fentanyl-54991.jpg"></figure><p>Lpez Obrador insists that he will respect Mexico's constitution  which </p> limits <p>presidents </p> to <p>a single six-year term  and will step down next year.</p><p>The process of choosing Morena's presidential nominee could weaken the party, with </p> followers of the three main hopefuls  fault lines already forming between those who support <p>Mexico City Mayor Claudia Sheinbaum, Foreign </p> Secretary Minister<p> Marcelo Ebrard and Interior</p>  SecretaryMinister <p>Adn Augusto Lpez Hernndez </p>  already starting to split into camps.<p>Still, polls suggest that a Morena victory is inevitable in 2024. A recent survey predicted that a Morena candidate would win 55% of the vote, compared with 22% for the National Action Party and 14% for the PRI, with the rest of the votes scattered among smaller parties. </p><p>Jorge Zepeda Patterson, who recently wrote a book about Lpez Obrador, told El Pais newspaper that he thinks the Morena primary process will, in effect, "be the presidential election in Mexico."</p><p>And although Morena has a formal nominating process, there is no doubt that Lpez Obrador is the one guiding it. "It is not that he is the leader of a party," Zepeda said. "It is that the party practically belongs to him."</p>Cecilia Snchez Vidal in The Times Mexico City bureau contributed to this report.                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lawmakers propose to weaken Obama rule requiring airlines to advertise full airfare price</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-06-09/lawmakers-propose-to-weaken-obama-rule-requiring-airlines-to-advertise-full-airfare-price</link>
      <description>Congress will consider rolling back an Obama-era rule that requires airlines to show the total cost of a ticket when advertising fares.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 22:04:53 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>DAVID KOENIG</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-06-09/lawmakers-propose-to-weaken-obama-rule-requiring-airlines-to-advertise-full-airfare-price</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2023-06-09/lawmakers-propose-to-weaken-obama-rule-requiring-airlines-to-advertise-full-airfare-price">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a0d9f6b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5527x3684+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fe4%2F5c%2Fd338cde1d240aa7eb8b4d4f741ca%2Fad9d2f01c08245148250a85541f6b7a2 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3d23ea9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5527x3684+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fe4%2F5c%2Fd338cde1d240aa7eb8b4d4f741ca%2Fad9d2f01c08245148250a85541f6b7a2 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8e4eee3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5527x3684+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fe4%2F5c%2Fd338cde1d240aa7eb8b4d4f741ca%2Fad9d2f01c08245148250a85541f6b7a2 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0903679/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5527x3684+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fe4%2F5c%2Fd338cde1d240aa7eb8b4d4f741ca%2Fad9d2f01c08245148250a85541f6b7a2 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/64ba00f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5527x3684+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fe4%2F5c%2Fd338cde1d240aa7eb8b4d4f741ca%2Fad9d2f01c08245148250a85541f6b7a2 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="FILE - Travelers use the kiosk by the ticketing gate as they prepare for travel from Love Field airport, May 19, 2023, in Dallas. Lawmakers are considering rolling back an Obama-era rule that requires airlines to show the total price of a ticket upfront in advertising, while also tweaking training requirements for airline pilots and making other changes in a massive bill covering the Federal Aviation Administration. (AP Photo/Tony Gutierrez, File)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/340ce33/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5527x3684+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fe4%2F5c%2Fd338cde1d240aa7eb8b4d4f741ca%2Fad9d2f01c08245148250a85541f6b7a2 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7775519/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5527x3684+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fe4%2F5c%2Fd338cde1d240aa7eb8b4d4f741ca%2Fad9d2f01c08245148250a85541f6b7a2 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d6098ef/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5527x3684+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fe4%2F5c%2Fd338cde1d240aa7eb8b4d4f741ca%2Fad9d2f01c08245148250a85541f6b7a2 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/78ce14b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5527x3684+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fe4%2F5c%2Fd338cde1d240aa7eb8b4d4f741ca%2Fad9d2f01c08245148250a85541f6b7a2 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/03e47dd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5527x3684+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fe4%2F5c%2Fd338cde1d240aa7eb8b4d4f741ca%2Fad9d2f01c08245148250a85541f6b7a2 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/03e47dd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5527x3684+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fe4%2F5c%2Fd338cde1d240aa7eb8b4d4f741ca%2Fad9d2f01c08245148250a85541f6b7a2"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">FILE - Travelers use the kiosk by the ticketing gate as they prepare for travel from Love Field airport, May 19, 2023, in Dallas. Lawmakers are considering rolling back an Obama-era rule that requires airlines to show the total price of a ticket upfront in advertising, while also tweaking training requirements for airline pilots and making other changes in a massive bill covering the Federal Aviation Administration. (AP Photo/Tony Gutierrez, File)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Tony Gutierrez / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Lawmakers propose to weaken Obama rule requiring airlines to advertise full airfare price</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" >        DAVID KOENIG    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Lawmakers are considering rolling back an Obama-era rule that requires airlines to show the total price of a ticket upfront in advertising, while also tweaking training requirements for airline pilots and making other changes in a massive bill covering the Federal Aviation Administration.</p><p>On Friday, Republicans and Democrats on the House Transportation Committee released a 773-page proposal to reauthorize FAA programs for the next five years.</p><p>Rep. Rick Larsen (D-Wash.) described the proposal as a compromise and said many issues could still be fought out when congressional committees begin considering changes in the legislation next week.</p><p>The FAA is under fire for a shortage of air traffic controllers, <a href="https://apnews.com/article/flight-delays-us-faa-updates-5805d15f520de8eadf52abb7b170487f">aging technology</a> and <a href="https://apnews.com/article/airplanes-close-call-san-francisco-southwest-ec9df0e1a2ff8038992c4d152d8b2449">close calls between planes</a>. The agency has a <a href="https://apnews.com/article/faa-acting-administrator-biden-buttigieg-079bbc6c1abb13b404946c75a06ec311">new acting administrator</a> with no aviation experience. It has lacked a Senate-confirmed leader for more than a year, since the <a href="https://apnews.com/article/joe-biden-business-stephen-dickson-federal-aviation-administration-8785ab0a556dbb20eec2d04638b2dd53">last one resigned</a> halfway through his term.</p><p>One provision of the House bill would let airlines advertise the base airfare  excluding taxes and fees  as long as they include a link to the all-in price or disclose it some other way. That would weaken an Obama administration rule that airlines have long fought to kill, and consumer advocates are unhappy about the House move.</p><p>These protections were hard fought and took years to enact, said William McGee, an aviation expert at the American Economic Liberties Project. Any consumer can tell you that online airline bookings are confusing enough. The last thing we need is to roll back an existing protection that provides effective transparency.</p> 'It was horrible': Stranded Southwest passengers still waiting to recoup costs from airline meltdown<p>The House committee leaders also propose to let people become airline pilots with less time in the cockpit. The bill would not change the requirement for 1,500 hours of training, but it would allow 250 hours  up from the current 100 hours  to occur in simulators rather than flying a plane.</p><p>Airlines, particularly the smaller ones that operate regional flights, have long fought against the 1,500-hour rule, which already has exemptions that let military pilots and graduates of some aviation schools qualify with fewer hours. The rule was put in <a href="https://apnews.com/article/ae9faf4921d34189acfcc895ea48f677">after a 2009 crash that killed 50 people.</a></p><p>Garth Thompson, head of the Air Line Pilots Assn. </p>Association<p> unit at United Airlines, said it is a horrible idea" to weaken the rule.</p><p>That rule, like so many federal aviation regulations, is written in blood, literally, Thompson said. That regulation came about because of the <a href="https://www.ntsb.gov/investigations/accidentreports/reports/aar1001.pdf" target="_blank">Colgan Air crash</a> and other crashes that involved experience issues.</p><p>Asked about changes in airfare advertising and pilot training, Larsen said, It's something we can live with. The change in pilot training rules, he said, is a priority of the Transportation Committee's Republican chairman, Sam Graves of Missouri, and both sides had to compromise during drafting of the bill.</p><p>Elsewhere in the bill, Larsen said, Democrats were able to include provisions they wanted, such as those covering wheelchair accessibility.</p><p>The bill also includes provisions aimed at improving airport infrastructure and the supply of sustainable aviation fuel. It would require airline planes to be outfitted with better cockpit voice recorders and, for the first time, cockpit video recorders to improve accident investigations. Pilots have opposed the video recorders.</p><p>Some other contentious topics were left out, including raising the mandatory retirement age of 65 for pilots and easing restrictions on flights from Reagan Washington National Airport in northern Virginia. </p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oregon, mecca of weed, to crack down on illegal pot growers by holding landowners responsible</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/oregon-mecca-of-weed-to-crack-down-on-illegal-pot-growers-by-holding-landowners-responsible</link>
      <description>Oregon has long been known as a mecca for high-quality marijuana, but that reputation has come with a downside.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 19:50:03 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>ANDREW SELSKY</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/oregon-mecca-of-weed-to-crack-down-on-illegal-pot-growers-by-holding-landowners-responsible</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/oregon-mecca-of-weed-to-crack-down-on-illegal-pot-growers-by-holding-landowners-responsible">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/74043a3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/8000x5333+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F73%2F0b%2Fcbcbf115ba55ae707817122301d0%2Feeb2a3337ef7423ba61e9e89ed955484 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8b4c55d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/8000x5333+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F73%2F0b%2Fcbcbf115ba55ae707817122301d0%2Feeb2a3337ef7423ba61e9e89ed955484 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/680988b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/8000x5333+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F73%2F0b%2Fcbcbf115ba55ae707817122301d0%2Feeb2a3337ef7423ba61e9e89ed955484 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c0079e5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/8000x5333+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F73%2F0b%2Fcbcbf115ba55ae707817122301d0%2Feeb2a3337ef7423ba61e9e89ed955484 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3968221/2147483647/strip/true/crop/8000x5333+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F73%2F0b%2Fcbcbf115ba55ae707817122301d0%2Feeb2a3337ef7423ba61e9e89ed955484 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="FILE - A marijuana grow is seen on Sept. 2, 2021, in an aerial photo taken by the Deschutes County Sheriff&#x27;s Office in the community of Alfalfa, Ore. Oregon has long been known as a mecca for high-quality marijuana, but that reputation has come with a downside: illegal growers who offer huge amounts of cash to lease or buy land and then leave behind pollution, garbage and a drained water table. (Deschutes County Sheriff via AP, File)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/89f273c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/8000x5333+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F73%2F0b%2Fcbcbf115ba55ae707817122301d0%2Feeb2a3337ef7423ba61e9e89ed955484 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5ee6380/2147483647/strip/true/crop/8000x5333+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F73%2F0b%2Fcbcbf115ba55ae707817122301d0%2Feeb2a3337ef7423ba61e9e89ed955484 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c32df06/2147483647/strip/true/crop/8000x5333+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F73%2F0b%2Fcbcbf115ba55ae707817122301d0%2Feeb2a3337ef7423ba61e9e89ed955484 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5196f1e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/8000x5333+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F73%2F0b%2Fcbcbf115ba55ae707817122301d0%2Feeb2a3337ef7423ba61e9e89ed955484 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/593e5d4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/8000x5333+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F73%2F0b%2Fcbcbf115ba55ae707817122301d0%2Feeb2a3337ef7423ba61e9e89ed955484 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/593e5d4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/8000x5333+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F73%2F0b%2Fcbcbf115ba55ae707817122301d0%2Feeb2a3337ef7423ba61e9e89ed955484"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">FILE - A marijuana grow is seen on Sept. 2, 2021, in an aerial photo taken by the Deschutes County Sheriffs Office in the community of Alfalfa, Ore. Oregon has long been known as a mecca for high-quality marijuana, but that reputation has come with a downside: illegal growers who offer huge amounts of cash to lease or buy land and then leave behind pollution, garbage and a drained water table. (Deschutes County Sheriff via AP, File)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Uncredited / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Oregon, mecca of weed, to crack down on illegal pot growers by holding landowners responsible</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" >        ANDREW SELSKY    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Oregon has long been known as a mecca for high-quality marijuana, but that reputation has come with a downside: <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-09-08/reality-of-legal-weed-in-california-illegal-grows-deaths">illegal growers</a> who offer huge amounts of cash to lease or buy land and then leave behind pollution, garbage and a drained water table. </p><p>Now, a bill passed by the Oregon Legislature seeks to tackle that by making the landowners themselves responsible for the aftermath. The bill also prohibits the use of rivers or groundwater at the illegal site, as well as criminalizes seizing the identity papers of migrant workers who tend the plants or threatening to report them for deportation.</p><p>Under the bill, local governments are authorized to file a claim of lien against property used for illicit marijuana, if the owner doesnt pay for the cleanup. </p><p>A leader of the states <a href="https://www.latimes.com/topic/cannabis">cannabis</a> and alcohol regulatory agency has said southern Oregon is to marijuana what Bordeaux is to wine. But the state faces challenges on two fronts: The regulated industry has a glut of product that has slashed prices and profit margins, and there has been huge growth in illegal pot farms operating under the guise of growing hemp, which became legal nationally in 2018. </p><p>After passing the Senate and House, the House Speaker Dan Rayfield signed the measure Wednesday, over the objections of some Republicans. Democratic Gov. Tina Kotek is expected to sign it next week.</p><p>This is just an assault on property rights here in the state of Oregon, GOP Sen. Dennis Linthicum said on the Senate floor. </p><p>But Democratic Sen. Jeff Golden, of Ashland, said property owners should know something is amiss when they are approached at the beginning of the growing season with requests to lease their property for tens, sometimes hundreds of thousand dollars for a single year.</p><p>Witnesses have described backpacks with thousands of dollars in cash being handed over to landowners and getting numerous offers to buy.</p><p>We pay CASH and offer a fast close, says one letter received by a landowner last year, one of three offers. </p><p>Jackson County Sheriff Nathan Sickler told lawmakers that after police raid illegal pot farms, neither landowners nor the suspects make efforts to remove the cheaply built greenhouses, known as hoop houses, latrines, and other debris, including plastics and chemicals.</p><p>Frankly, it's an eyesore for our community, with no means to deal with it, Sickler said.</p><p>Some two years ago, the ideal growing conditions began attracting criminal gangs from Mexico, Russia and other countries, police said. Thousands of hoop houses cropped up and police were overwhelmed, nailing only a fraction of the sites. Workers at these farms often live in squalid conditions and use open latrines, and they are sometimes cheated out of their pay.</p><p>Due to persistent police raids, which netted over 100 tons of illegal marijuana across the state last year, the grow sites have become smaller and more dispersed. For example, on Thursday, Josephine County Sheriff's deputies and other officers raided a property in Cave Junction and destroyed about 2,000 marijuana plants and 100 pounds of processed marijuana.</p><p>Landowners who have been intimidated and suffered environmental damage from illegal grow sites are applauding the bill.</p><p>At least most of the landowners knew what they were doing was wrong. I believe this measure will help to stem the tide, said Jack Dwyer, who has a house near the community of Selma. In 2021, Dwyer said a large illegal grow site nearby siphoned all the water from a creek that runs through his property, causing it to run dry. </p><p>Christopher Hall, who works to engage the public in water stewardship, said the bill shows that Oregon officials understand the problem of large-scale illicit cannabis operations and are committed to solving it. </p><p>The illicit sites not only turn streams into gravel roads but also lead to serious human rights violations and dumping of trash, sewage, chemicals, and other waste into ditches, riparian areas, and streams," he said.</p><p>The Senate approved the measure before <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-05-31/gop-walkout-in-oregon-senate-hits-record-fourth-week">GOP senators began a walkout </a>on May 3 over Democratic measures on abortion, gender-affirming care and gun safety. The House passed the marijuana bill on a 53-3 vote on May 31. The bill will now go to Kotek to sign into law, taking immediate effect.</p><p>"The governor supports cracking down on illegal cannabis operations that have been prevalent in southern Oregon, said Elisabeth Shepard, Kotek's spokesperson.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boris Johnson quits as U.K. lawmaker, faces sanctions for misleading Parliament</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/boris-johnson-quits-as-uk-lawmaker-after-being-told-he-will-be-sanctioned-for-misleading-parliament</link>
      <description>Former U.K. Prime Minister Boris Johnson says he’s quitting as a lawmaker after being told he will be sanctioned for misleading Parliament.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 19:47:21 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>JILL LAWLESS</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/boris-johnson-quits-as-uk-lawmaker-after-being-told-he-will-be-sanctioned-for-misleading-parliament</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/boris-johnson-quits-as-uk-lawmaker-after-being-told-he-will-be-sanctioned-for-misleading-parliament">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9e4ab08/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4678x3119+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F41%2Feb5ba34eb96fe95a9b863adf8cd4%2F1928e98670404d269c002dbccdf56c77 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4861428/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4678x3119+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F41%2Feb5ba34eb96fe95a9b863adf8cd4%2F1928e98670404d269c002dbccdf56c77 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/805a5da/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4678x3119+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F41%2Feb5ba34eb96fe95a9b863adf8cd4%2F1928e98670404d269c002dbccdf56c77 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3bb533c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4678x3119+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F41%2Feb5ba34eb96fe95a9b863adf8cd4%2F1928e98670404d269c002dbccdf56c77 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f9fddd1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4678x3119+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F41%2Feb5ba34eb96fe95a9b863adf8cd4%2F1928e98670404d269c002dbccdf56c77 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="FILE - Boris Johnson leaves his house in London, on March 22, 2023. Several dozen allies of former British Prime Minister Boris Johnson received honors from King Charles III on Friday June 9, 2023, a list that drew cries of cronyism from opponents of the ousted leader. Resignation honors, bestowed by the monarch but chosen by the government, are an established but contentious way for departing leaders to reward loyal lieutenants. (AP Photo/Alberto Pezzali, File)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5f11a5b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4678x3119+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F41%2Feb5ba34eb96fe95a9b863adf8cd4%2F1928e98670404d269c002dbccdf56c77 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3a6531d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4678x3119+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F41%2Feb5ba34eb96fe95a9b863adf8cd4%2F1928e98670404d269c002dbccdf56c77 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/95a72dd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4678x3119+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F41%2Feb5ba34eb96fe95a9b863adf8cd4%2F1928e98670404d269c002dbccdf56c77 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c178b99/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4678x3119+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F41%2Feb5ba34eb96fe95a9b863adf8cd4%2F1928e98670404d269c002dbccdf56c77 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d74355f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4678x3119+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F41%2Feb5ba34eb96fe95a9b863adf8cd4%2F1928e98670404d269c002dbccdf56c77 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d74355f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4678x3119+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F41%2Feb5ba34eb96fe95a9b863adf8cd4%2F1928e98670404d269c002dbccdf56c77"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">FILE - Boris Johnson leaves his house in London, on March 22, 2023. Several dozen allies of former British Prime Minister Boris Johnson received honors from King Charles III on Friday June 9, 2023, a list that drew cries of cronyism from opponents of the ousted leader. Resignation honors, bestowed by the monarch but chosen by the government, are an established but contentious way for departing leaders to reward loyal lieutenants. (AP Photo/Alberto Pezzali, File)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Alberto Pezzali / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Boris Johnson quits as U.K. lawmaker, faces sanctions for misleading Parliament</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" >        JILL LAWLESS    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2022-10-21/boris-johnson-comeback-bid-uk-prime-minister">Former U.K. Prime Minister Boris Johnson</a> shocked Britain on Friday by quitting as a lawmaker after being told he will be sanctioned for misleading Parliament. He departed with a ferocious tirade at his political opponents  and </p>at<p> his successor, Rishi Sunak  that could blast open tensions within the governing Conservative Party.</p><p>Johnson resigned after receiving the results of an investigation by lawmakers into misleading statements he made to Parliament about partygate," a series of rule-breaking government parties during the COVID-19 pandemic.</p><p>In a lengthy resignation statement, Johnson accused opponents of trying to drive him out  and hinted that his roller coaster political career might not be over</p> yet<p>.</p><p>"It is very sad to be leaving Parliament  at least for now," he said.</p><p>Johnson, 58, said he had received a letter from the Privileges Committee making it clear  much to my amazement  that they are determined to use the proceedings against me to drive me out of Parliament.</p><p>He called the committee investigating him, which has members from both government and opposition parties, a kangaroo court.</p> Britain's Boris Johnson resigns after months of scandal and criticism<p>"Their purpose from the beginning has been to find me guilty, regardless of the facts," Johnson said.</p><p>The resignation will trigger a special election to replace Johnson </p>as a lawmaker for in <p>a suburban London seat in the House of Commons.</p><p>Johnson, whose career has seen a series of scandals and comebacks, led the Conservatives to a landslide victory in 2019 but was forced out by his own party </p> fewer less<p> than three years later.</p><p>He had been awaiting the outcome of an investigation by a House of Commons standards committee over misleading statements he made to Parliament about </p>a slew of<p> gatherings </p>in government buildings <p>in 2020 and 2021 </p> in government buildings <p>that breached pandemic lockdown rules.</p><p>Police eventually issued 126 fines over the </p>late-night boozy <p>soirees</p>, boozy parties<p> and wine time Fridays, including one to Johnson.</p>, and<p> The scandal </p>helped<p> hasten</p> ed<p> the end of his premiership.</p><p>Johnson has acknowledged misleading Parliament when he assured lawmakers that no rules had been broken but </p>he<p> said he didn't do so deliberately.</p> 'Hand on heart ... I did not lie' about 'partygate,' former U.K. premier Boris Johnson says<p>He told the committee he honestly believed the five events he attended, including a send-off for a staffer and his own surprise birthday party, were lawful work gatherings intended to boost morale among overworked staff members coping with </p> the a deadly<p> pandemic.</p><p>The committee had been expected to publish its report in the next few weeks, and Johnson could have faced suspension from the House of Commons if he was found to have lied deliberately.</p><p>By quitting, he avoids a suspension that could have seen him ousted from his Commons seat by his constituents, leaving him free to run for Parliament again</p> in future<p>. His resignation statement suggested he was mulling that option. </p> The statement is It was<p> highly critical of Sunak, who served as Treasury chief in Johnson's government before jumping ship with many other colleagues in July 2022  resignations that forced Johnson out.</p><p>Johnson took aim at Sunak, who was chosen by the Conservatives in October to steady the government after the terms of Johnson and his </p>briefly serving<p> successor Liz Truss, who stepped down after six weeks when her tax-slashing policies caused financial turmoil.</p>Johnson claimed that<p> When I left office last year the government was only a handful of points behind in the polls</p> ," Johnson claimed<p>. "That gap has now massively widened."</p> From Brexit to Partygate, a timeline of Boris Johnson's career<p>Conservative poll ratings went into decline during the turbulent final months of Johnson's term and have not recovered. Opinion polls regularly put the opposition Labour Party </p> ahead by <p>20 points or more</p> ahead<p>. A national election must be held by the end of 2024.</p><p>"Just a few years after winning the biggest majority in almost half a century, that majority is now clearly at risk," Johnson said. Our party needs urgently to recapture its sense of momentum and its belief in what this country can do."</p>Johnson He <p>resigned hours after King Charles III rewarded dozens of his loyal aides and allies with knighthoods and other honors  a political tradition for former prime ministers that drew cries of cronyism from</p>  Johnson's<p> opponents</p> of the ousted leader<p>.</p><p>Johnson's dramatic exit is the latest  but maybe not the last  chapter in a career of extremes. The rumpled, Latin-spouting populist with a mop of blond hair had held major offices, including London mayor, but also spent periods on the political sidelines before Britain's exit from the European Union propelled him to the top.</p> Boris Johnson leaves complicated legacy after resigning  but he's not done yet <p>Johnson's bullish boosterism helped persuade 52% of Britons to vote to leave the EU, and he was elected prime minister in 2019 on a vow to get Brexit done.</p><p>Johnson was less suited to the hard work of governing, and the pandemic  he landed in intensive care with COVID-19  was a major challenge. Johnson's government won plaudits for its rapid vaccine rollout, but the U.K. </p>also<p> had one of the highest </p>coronavirus<p> COVID-19 death tolls in Europe and some of the longest lockdowns.</p><p>The final straw came when details emerged of parties held in Johnsons Downing Street office and home while the country was in lockdown. Partygate caused outrage and </p>finally<p> pushed the Conservative Party to oust its election-winning but erratic leader.</p><p>Angela Rayner, deputy leader of the opposition Labour Party, responded to Johnson's resignation with: Enough is enough.</p><p>The British public are sick to the back teeth of this never ending Tory soap opera played out at their expense," she said.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>'All life should be valued': Volunteers rush to save animals after Ukraine dam collapse</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/all-life-should-be-valued-volunteers-rush-to-save-animals-after-ukraine-dam-collapse</link>
      <description>Dozens of volunteers for a Ukrainian animal rescue group are racing to save as many animals as possible after a dam collapse caused flooding.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 19:31:13 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>VASILISA STEPANENKO</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/all-life-should-be-valued-volunteers-rush-to-save-animals-after-ukraine-dam-collapse</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/all-life-should-be-valued-volunteers-rush-to-save-animals-after-ukraine-dam-collapse">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/cc6139c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4240x2832+0+0/resize/320x214!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F2e%2F3d%2F42a57b589d0c3ef16bd640e2383a%2Ffd736ccdcfe542e1b4a5aa2dbb591060 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e0991f2/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4240x2832+0+0/resize/568x380!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F2e%2F3d%2F42a57b589d0c3ef16bd640e2383a%2Ffd736ccdcfe542e1b4a5aa2dbb591060 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/473e393/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4240x2832+0+0/resize/768x513!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F2e%2F3d%2F42a57b589d0c3ef16bd640e2383a%2Ffd736ccdcfe542e1b4a5aa2dbb591060 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/aec9c3d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4240x2832+0+0/resize/1024x684!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F2e%2F3d%2F42a57b589d0c3ef16bd640e2383a%2Ffd736ccdcfe542e1b4a5aa2dbb591060 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a1630c1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4240x2832+0+0/resize/1200x802!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F2e%2F3d%2F42a57b589d0c3ef16bd640e2383a%2Ffd736ccdcfe542e1b4a5aa2dbb591060 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="An animal rescue team on a boat with a rescued dog in the flooded area after the dam collapse in Kherson, Ukraine, Thursday, June 8, 2023. (AP Photo/Vasilisa Stepanenko)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3d4d80f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4240x2832+0+0/resize/320x214!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F2e%2F3d%2F42a57b589d0c3ef16bd640e2383a%2Ffd736ccdcfe542e1b4a5aa2dbb591060 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9426da0/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4240x2832+0+0/resize/568x380!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F2e%2F3d%2F42a57b589d0c3ef16bd640e2383a%2Ffd736ccdcfe542e1b4a5aa2dbb591060 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6146c1c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4240x2832+0+0/resize/768x513!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F2e%2F3d%2F42a57b589d0c3ef16bd640e2383a%2Ffd736ccdcfe542e1b4a5aa2dbb591060 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/27e2011/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4240x2832+0+0/resize/1024x684!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F2e%2F3d%2F42a57b589d0c3ef16bd640e2383a%2Ffd736ccdcfe542e1b4a5aa2dbb591060 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8fe645f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4240x2832+0+0/resize/1200x802!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F2e%2F3d%2F42a57b589d0c3ef16bd640e2383a%2Ffd736ccdcfe542e1b4a5aa2dbb591060 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="802"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8fe645f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4240x2832+0+0/resize/1200x802!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F2e%2F3d%2F42a57b589d0c3ef16bd640e2383a%2Ffd736ccdcfe542e1b4a5aa2dbb591060"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">An animal rescue team on a boat with a rescued dog in the flooded area after the dam collapse in Kherson, Ukraine, Thursday, June 8, 2023. (AP Photo/Vasilisa Stepanenko)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Vasilisa Stepanenko / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>&#x27;All life should be valued&#x27;: Volunteers rush to save animals after Ukraine dam collapse</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" >        VASILISA STEPANENKO    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>The rescue volunteer holds out his hand, but the dog, stranded on a floating island of debris in a southern Ukrainian city inundated by flooding, is too traumatized to approach. Volodymyr Holubnichii offers the scared animal some food; the dog sniffs and relaxes.</p><p>Dont be scared, Holubnichii soothingly tells the animal, which eventually accepts a leash and being carried to safety.</p><p>Holubnichii, a volunteer with Animal Rescue Kharkiv, spent days cruising the flooded streets of Kherson city after the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-06/ukraine-accuses-russia-destroying-major-dam-warns-disaster">Kakhovka dam collapsed</a> on Tuesday and submerged entire towns. He is one among the organization's 70 volunteers determined to rescue as many animals as possible, plucking them from the rooftops and garages of flooded homes before they die of dehydration and hunger.</p><p>The <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-06/ukraine-accuses-russia-destroying-major-dam-warns-disaster">flooding has killed civilians</a>, ruined crops, displaced landmines, and caused widespread environmental damage. Kyiv accused Moscow of blowing up the </p>Dnieper  Dnipro<p> River dam and its hydropower plant, which the Kremlins forces controlled. Russia in turn blamed Ukraine for the catastrophe.</p><p>Bisected by the river, southern Ukraine's Kherson province is an important fault line in the war that started with Russia's invasion of the neighboring country more than 15 months ago. Russian forces withdrew from the western bank, including the regional capital also named Kherson, but part of the eastern side remain under Russian occupation.</p>.<p>Ukrainian authorities scrambled to evacuate <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/ukraine-dam-collapse-thousands-await-help-russian-occupied">stranded residents</a>; officials on both sides said at least 14 people died in the flooding and thousands</p>  of<p> others were homeless, while tens of thousands were without drinking water. </p><p>Upon hearing news of the flooding, Holubnichii immediately thought of the animals. All life should be valued, he said. It doesnt matter if its an animal or a person or something else.</p><p>Animal Rescue Kharkiv's volunteers, based in northern Ukraine's Kharkiv province, began packing their gear. By Wednesday morning, they were in the Kherson region looking for animals.</p><p>So far, they have saved 107 animals since the dams collapse: 45 dogs, 36 cats, five kittens, 18 chickens and three goats that will go to shelters across Ukraine. Many were pets of evacuated civilians, according to Yaryna Vintoniuk, a spokesperson for the nongovernmental organization. </p><p>From rescue boats, the team reached remote areas of Kherson and extracted animals from rooftops, apartments and garages of submerged homes. On Thursday, the volunteers came under Russian shelling as they worked. </p><p>The animals, unwillingly abandoned by their panicked owners, were terrified. Some barely had the strength to get up. </p><p>Holubnichii picked up a small dog that was trapped under the floating rubble and nearly unconscious. He heard the barking of another dog and made his way to the animal, stuck on a rooftop of a flooded home.</p><p>Dont be afraid, giant, Holubnichii said in a soft voice. </p><p>The </p>NGO  nongovernmental organization<p> founded eight years ago is 90-year-old Valentyna Timofeevnas best hope for being reunited with her dog and cat. Timofeevna had to leave her pets behind when she was evacuated from her home. Weeping, she wonders if they will be found alive. </p><p>Maybe they are already dead, the woman wailed. A volunteer tried to comfort her, telling her not to rush to conclusions.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>U.S. announces new $2.1-billion package of military aid to Ukraine</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/us-announces-new-2-1-billion-package-of-military-aid-to-ukraine</link>
      <description>The Biden administration has provided more than $37.6 billion in security assistance to Ukraine since Russia invaded in February 2022.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 19:18:31 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>LOLITA C. BALDOR</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/us-announces-new-2-1-billion-package-of-military-aid-to-ukraine</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/us-announces-new-2-1-billion-package-of-military-aid-to-ukraine">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0eee626/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6540x4360+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F9c%2F02%2F4fadddf9281e9e817c0c336b8f16%2Fb6b11d78401a4def922203d0ce332869 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/853d4ce/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6540x4360+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F9c%2F02%2F4fadddf9281e9e817c0c336b8f16%2Fb6b11d78401a4def922203d0ce332869 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/cf1f68e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6540x4360+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F9c%2F02%2F4fadddf9281e9e817c0c336b8f16%2Fb6b11d78401a4def922203d0ce332869 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/80e3403/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6540x4360+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F9c%2F02%2F4fadddf9281e9e817c0c336b8f16%2Fb6b11d78401a4def922203d0ce332869 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b1a78d5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6540x4360+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F9c%2F02%2F4fadddf9281e9e817c0c336b8f16%2Fb6b11d78401a4def922203d0ce332869 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Pentagon spokesman U.S. Air Force Brig. Gen. Patrick Ryder arrives for a media briefing at the Pentagon, Thursday, June 8, 2023, in Washington. (AP Photo/Alex Brandon)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d453ddc/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6540x4360+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F9c%2F02%2F4fadddf9281e9e817c0c336b8f16%2Fb6b11d78401a4def922203d0ce332869 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3753307/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6540x4360+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F9c%2F02%2F4fadddf9281e9e817c0c336b8f16%2Fb6b11d78401a4def922203d0ce332869 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c2bea70/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6540x4360+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F9c%2F02%2F4fadddf9281e9e817c0c336b8f16%2Fb6b11d78401a4def922203d0ce332869 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/72aaf0b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6540x4360+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F9c%2F02%2F4fadddf9281e9e817c0c336b8f16%2Fb6b11d78401a4def922203d0ce332869 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/cb2ab24/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6540x4360+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F9c%2F02%2F4fadddf9281e9e817c0c336b8f16%2Fb6b11d78401a4def922203d0ce332869 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/cb2ab24/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6540x4360+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F9c%2F02%2F4fadddf9281e9e817c0c336b8f16%2Fb6b11d78401a4def922203d0ce332869"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Pentagon spokesman U.S. Air Force Brig. Gen. Patrick Ryder arrives for a media briefing at the Pentagon, Thursday, June 8, 2023, in Washington. (AP Photo/Alex Brandon)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Alex Brandon / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>U.S. announces new $2.1-billion package of military aid to Ukraine</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">Ukraine</h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" >        LOLITA C. BALDOR    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>The Pentagon announced Friday that it will provide an additional $2.1 billion in long-term weapons aid for Ukraine. The <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-04-04/us-is-providing-ukraine-with-2-6-billion-in-military-aid">new assistance package</a> will include funding for more Patriot missile battery munitions, Hawk air defense systems and missiles, and small Puma drones that can be launched by hand.</p><p>The latest <a href="https://www.latimes.com/politics/story/2022-05-10/house-approves-40b-in-ukraine-aid-beefing-up-biden-request">infusion of funding,</a> one of the larger packages the U.S. has provided, comes as there are signs that Ukraine is beginning  or about to begin  the much anticipated counteroffensive to try to take back territory that has been seized by Russia. </p><p>Unlike the U.S. equipment, weapons and ammunition that are more frequently sent from Pentagon stocks and delivered quickly to Ukraine, this money would be provided under the Ukraine Security Assistance Initiative and is meant to be spent over the coming months or even years to ensure Ukraines future security needs.</p> Biden announces nearly $3 billion in new Ukraine military aid for the years ahead<p>In a statement, the Pentagon said the package shows America's continued commitment to both Ukraines critical near-term capabilities as well as the enduring capacity of Ukraines Armed Forces to defend its territory and deter Russian aggression over the long term.</p><p>The aid also will include munitions for laser-guided rockets, an undisclosed amount of artillery rounds, and funding for training and maintenance support. </p><p>A number of administration officials have acknowledged that the fighting in Ukraine has intensified in recent days, but much of the focus turned early this week to the collapse of the Kakhovka dam on the </p>Dnieper  Dnipro <p>River. The White House and the Pentagon insisted Thursday they are still working to determine who caused the damage, which set off a scramble to evacuate residents in dozens of flooded areas and get aid to those still there.</p><p>Although the U.S. has been willing to provide billions of dollars in military weapons and other aid, the Biden administration has been clear that there will be no U.S. combat forces inside Ukraine. In that vein, Brig. Gen. Pat Ryder, the Pentagon press secretary, said Thursday the military had no plans to directly provide transportation or other support to the areas damaged by the dam collapse.</p><p>The Biden administration has provided more than $37.6 billion in security assistance to Ukraine since Russia invaded in February 2022. </p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Florida woman accused of fatally shooting neighbor is granted $154,000 bond</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/florida-woman-who-fatally-shot-neighbor-granted-154-000-bond</link>
      <description>A judge has granted a $154,000 bond for a Florida woman charged in the fatal shooting of her neighbor.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 19:12:37 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/florida-woman-who-fatally-shot-neighbor-granted-154-000-bond</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/florida-woman-who-fatally-shot-neighbor-granted-154-000-bond">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c9c91af/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4684x3123+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F95%2F60635cc2460c8693c793b0d3aa41%2F7fb8b71d3e2f424faed1d47fbda7654a 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ee0b488/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4684x3123+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F95%2F60635cc2460c8693c793b0d3aa41%2F7fb8b71d3e2f424faed1d47fbda7654a 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a37e5d9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4684x3123+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F95%2F60635cc2460c8693c793b0d3aa41%2F7fb8b71d3e2f424faed1d47fbda7654a 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1081746/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4684x3123+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F95%2F60635cc2460c8693c793b0d3aa41%2F7fb8b71d3e2f424faed1d47fbda7654a 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b4e1c0c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4684x3123+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F95%2F60635cc2460c8693c793b0d3aa41%2F7fb8b71d3e2f424faed1d47fbda7654a 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Tmika Wilkerson, left, and Kimberly Wilkerson pray as mourners gather for a remembrance service at Immerse Church of Ocala for Ajike Owens, Thursday, June 8, 2023, in Ocala, Fla. Owens was fatally shot by her neighbor Susan Lorincz when she went to Lorincz&#x27;s door. Lorincz was arrested and charged in the shooting. (AP Photo/Alan Youngblood)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7807640/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4684x3123+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F95%2F60635cc2460c8693c793b0d3aa41%2F7fb8b71d3e2f424faed1d47fbda7654a 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ac88838/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4684x3123+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F95%2F60635cc2460c8693c793b0d3aa41%2F7fb8b71d3e2f424faed1d47fbda7654a 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/14c5cd8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4684x3123+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F95%2F60635cc2460c8693c793b0d3aa41%2F7fb8b71d3e2f424faed1d47fbda7654a 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/07f90c8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4684x3123+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F95%2F60635cc2460c8693c793b0d3aa41%2F7fb8b71d3e2f424faed1d47fbda7654a 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3874008/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4684x3123+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F95%2F60635cc2460c8693c793b0d3aa41%2F7fb8b71d3e2f424faed1d47fbda7654a 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3874008/2147483647/strip/true/crop/4684x3123+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F15%2F95%2F60635cc2460c8693c793b0d3aa41%2F7fb8b71d3e2f424faed1d47fbda7654a"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Tmika Wilkerson, left, and Kimberly Wilkerson pray as mourners gather for a remembrance service at Immerse Church of Ocala for Ajike Owens, Thursday, June 8, 2023, in Ocala, Fla. Owens was fatally shot by her neighbor Susan Lorincz when she went to Lorinczs door. Lorincz was arrested and charged in the shooting. (AP Photo/Alan Youngblood)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Alan Youngblood / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Florida woman accused of fatally shooting neighbor is granted $154,000 bond</h1>                                                                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>A judge granted a $154,000 bond Friday for a white Florida woman charged with <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-07/white-woman-fatally-shot-black-neighbor-arrested-florida">fatally shooting a Black neighbor through her front door.</a> </p><p>Susan Louise Lorincz, 58, of Ocala returned to court in Marion County a day after she pleaded not guilty to a first-degree felony charge of manslaughter with a firearm, as well as counts of culpable negligence, battery and assault. </p><p>As a condition of Lorincz's bond, Circuit Court Judge Robert Hodges ordered the woman to wear an ankle monitor and stay away from the family of her slain neighbor, 34-year-old Ajike Owens.</p><p>The courtroom was packed with relatives and supporters of Owens, a mother of four children. One of the family's attorneys, Anthony Thomas, told reporters after the Friday hearing that they would continue to push for Lorincz to face a more serious charge of second-degree murder. </p><p>We don't believe that Susan had any sort of respect at all for human life, Thomas said. "This wasnt something where she was cleaning a gun and the gun went off and it goes through the wall or the door and it accidentally hurts somebody. She meant to pull that trigger. She meant to point it at the door.</p><p>Owens was killed June 2 in Ocala, about 83 miles north of Orlando. Her funeral is scheduled for Monday.</p> Florida woman charged with killing neighbor appears in court; details of racist threats released<p>After the shooting, Lorincz told investigators she had had problems for two years with being disrespected by children in the neighborhood  including Owens' children, who are ages 12, 9, 7 and 3.</p><p>According to an arrest report from the Marion County Sheriff's Office, Lorincz said she had a headache the day of the shooting and children were running</p>,<p> and yelling outside her apartment. That night, while a few children were playing basketball, Lorincz threw a pair of roller skates at them, hitting one on the feet, the arrest report said.</p><p>Owens then came over and knocked on Lorincz's door. Lorincz told investigators that Owens threatened to kill her and banged on the door so hard that she feared Owens would break it down, the report said. </p><p>Lorincz fired a single round from her .380-caliber handgun, the sheriff's report says, which went through the closed door and fatally struck Owens.</p><p>Lorincz told investigators that she had called Owens' children racist slurs in the months before the killing. Authorities </p>had<p> delayed her arrest for several days while looking into a possible  stand your ground  claim. Detectives have since said that Lorinczs actions are not justifiable under Florida law.</p><p>Marion County <a href="https://www.facebook.com/mcsoflorida/videos/781918220110385/">Sheriff Billy Woods</a> said that since January 2021, deputies responded to at least a half-dozen complaints between Owens and Lorincz in Ocala.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making Turkey great again: How Erdogan rode to reelection on a nationalist wave</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-02/turkey-erdogan-rode-nationalism-wave-win-reelection</link>
      <description>Once expected to lose, Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan managed to parlay nationalism to win a historic third term after 20 years in power.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2023 17:19:35 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Nabih Bulos</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-02/turkey-erdogan-rode-nationalism-wave-win-reelection</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-02/turkey-erdogan-rode-nationalism-wave-win-reelection">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8be44f5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3710x2473+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa9%2Fc4%2Faee0a57842e990ce0b4dd54b17f6%2Fturkey-election-84782.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d60cb98/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3710x2473+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa9%2Fc4%2Faee0a57842e990ce0b4dd54b17f6%2Fturkey-election-84782.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c63ff85/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3710x2473+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa9%2Fc4%2Faee0a57842e990ce0b4dd54b17f6%2Fturkey-election-84782.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/acdb68c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3710x2473+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa9%2Fc4%2Faee0a57842e990ce0b4dd54b17f6%2Fturkey-election-84782.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f7769c1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3710x2473+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa9%2Fc4%2Faee0a57842e990ce0b4dd54b17f6%2Fturkey-election-84782.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Turkish President and People&#x27;s Alliance&#x27;s presidential candidate Recep Tayyip Erdogan makes a speech at the presidential palace, in Ankara, Turkey, Sunday, May 28, 2023. Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan has dissipated a challenge by an opponent who sought to reverse his increasingly authoritarian leanings, securing five more years to oversee the country at the crossroads of Europe and Asia that plays a key role in NATO. (AP Photo/Ali Unal)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/cabb6c5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3710x2473+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa9%2Fc4%2Faee0a57842e990ce0b4dd54b17f6%2Fturkey-election-84782.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/eefcb76/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3710x2473+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa9%2Fc4%2Faee0a57842e990ce0b4dd54b17f6%2Fturkey-election-84782.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/301d8a9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3710x2473+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa9%2Fc4%2Faee0a57842e990ce0b4dd54b17f6%2Fturkey-election-84782.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/fd8599f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3710x2473+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa9%2Fc4%2Faee0a57842e990ce0b4dd54b17f6%2Fturkey-election-84782.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a6625c9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3710x2473+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa9%2Fc4%2Faee0a57842e990ce0b4dd54b17f6%2Fturkey-election-84782.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a6625c9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3710x2473+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa9%2Fc4%2Faee0a57842e990ce0b4dd54b17f6%2Fturkey-election-84782.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Turkish President and Peoples Alliances presidential candidate Recep Tayyip Erdogan makes a speech at the presidential palace, in Ankara, Turkey, Sunday, May 28, 2023. Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan has dissipated a challenge by an opponent who sought to reverse his increasingly authoritarian leanings, securing five more years to oversee the country at the crossroads of Europe and Asia that plays a key role in NATO. (AP Photo/Ali Unal)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Ali Unal / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Making Turkey great again: How Erdogan rode to reelection on a nationalist wave</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/nabih-bulos">        Nabih Bulos    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 2, 2023">June 2, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Before Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan snatched victory in the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-05-13/campaigning-in-turkeys-pivotal-elections-nearing-end">hardest fight of his two decades</a> in power, a ubiquitous campaign poster showed him in dark sunglasses and a black aviator jacket with military patches alongside images of drones, ships, tanks and a ghostly national flag.</p><p>He wont leave the homeland unprotected, the posters slogan said. Go with the right man.</p><p>Its a martial persona that has come to occupy an ever-larger part of the political identity Erdogan has constructed over the last 20 years <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world/europe/la-fg-turkey-erdogan-20170416-story.html">as Turkeys president or prime minister</a>. To an already-potent cocktail of Islamist and neo-liberal elements, Erdogan  who will be sworn in for a historic third presidential term Saturday  has added a large measure of muscular nationalism, which he channeled into a masterful, nostalgia-filled campaign that won him reelection and set him up to realize the vision he calls Turkeys Century.</p><p>That vision taps not only into the countrys 100-year-old history as a secular republic but also into a honey-dipped view of its Ottoman Empire past. In Erdogans telling, the next 100 years will see Turkey restored to its former glory as a mighty actor on the world stage, an <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world/la-fg-turkey-adhan-call-to-prayer-20181121-story.html">unabashedly Muslim military power</a> capable of standing up to its adversaries and inspiring oppressed nations around the world.</p><p>In short: Make Turkey great again.</p><p>Nations that were once great powers have a malleable and inflatable sense of their heyday, said Soner Cagaptay, director of the Turkish Research Program at the Washington Institute for Near East Policy. With this comes an inclination to be inspired by leaders who can speak to this narrative and embody it, and thats Erdogan in Turkey.</p> With an Erdogan win, Turkey would continue to play both sides of the U.S.-Russia divide<p>Erdogan, 69, has pledged to catapult Turkey, a NATO member with the alliances second-largest army, into the worlds top 10 nations in all fields of politics, economy, technology, military and diplomacy. Its an all-out development drive involving energy independence, gargantuan  and controversial  infrastructure projects like the Kanal Istanbul, an artificial waterway to reduce traffic in the Bosporus, and, crucially, a homegrown weapons industry to make Turkey militarily stronger.</p><p>The last point is a particularly sore one: In 2019, the U.S. expelled Turkey from its fifth-generation F-35 fighter jet program after Erdogans government bought missiles from Russia. More recently, his <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-01-23/turkeys-president-says-no-support-for-swedens-nato-bid">refusal to accept Sweden into NATO</a> over what he says is its harboring of Kurdish militants led Congress to block sales of F-16 fighter jets.</p><p>During his reelection campaign, he inaugurated the countrys first aircraft carrier, which was designed for the F-35 program but will instead deploy Turkish drones and helicopters. He also touted Turkeys first tank and electric car as achievements that would propel the country into the next century.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/e6/f2/2c079f2a4a9894acfbecaab3e492/turkey-election-95781.jpg"></figure><p>Behind the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2022-10-05/turkey-oks-sending-troops-to-qatar-for-world-cup-security">displays of military power</a>, said Asli Aydintasbas, a Turkish policy expert and visiting fellow at the Brookings Institution in Washington, is Erdogans recognition of a rising tide of nationalism in the country.</p><p>The trend is pointing to nationalism as the dominant force in Turkish society  a force that cuts across both Erdogans ruling Justice and Development Party, or AKP, and the opposition groups ranged against him, Aydintasbas said.</p><p>Ahead of the elections May 14 first round, the increasingly authoritarian Erdogan  at last  seemed vulnerable. His early years in power had seen unprecedented economic growth. His government funded vast infrastructure projects  airports, bridges, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2020-07-10/turkish-court-rules-to-let-hagia-sophia-return-to-its-previous-status-as-mosque">elaborate mosques</a>  that helped lift people into the middle class and propelled the country of 85 million into the worlds 20 top economies.</p> Turkey is holding a momentous election. Here's what's at stake<p>But the Turkish liras value plunged in 2018, and Erdogans stubborn refusal to raise interest rates saw inflation skyrocket to 80% before settling down to a little more than half that this year; in cities, it remains in the triple digits. His governments lackluster rescue efforts in <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-02-23/turkey-syria-earthquake-death-toll-47000">Februarys disastrous earthquakes</a>  which killed at least 50,000 people and left millions homeless  enraged many.</p><p>Polls predicted his quick defeat to a coalition of six opposition parties that had united to defeat him. Instead, he led in a nail-biting first round before defeating challenger Kemal Kilicdaroglu in an unprecedented runoff election Sunday with 52% of the vote.</p><p>To be sure, some credit for that victory goes to Erdogans control of the media and his use of state levers  raising the minimum wage and pensions, offering free gas  to win votes. International monitors judged the election <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-05-08/turkey-opposition-denounces-election-fairness-erdogan">to be free but not fair</a>.</p><p>But he also hammered home a message that cast him as Turkeys primary protector and the only one who could restore it to its Ottoman grandeur.</p> 'Syrians will go!' As Turkey's election runoff nears, refugees face new threats<p>His vision of Turkeys Century draws its inspiration from the thousand-year-old glorious past of our ancestors as well as the modern republic, he said in a speech late last year. Erdogan named himself in the line of succession of important Turkish rulers, including, most notably, Osman Bey, the Ottoman Empires founder, and Kemal <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/blogs/babylon-beyond/story/2008-12-18/turkey-ataturks-grave-head-scarves-and-the-call-to-prayer">Ataturk, the founder of the republic</a>.</p><p>Lets transform our country into a locomotive instead of a cog in the global wheel, he said.</p><p>Throughout his campaign, Erdogan railed against a host of enemies, both within and without, who have hindered [Turkeys] enormous potential: secularists; segments of the Kurdish minority; activists, writers and scholars who disagree with his politics; <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world/la-fg-turkey-gay-pride-20160626-snap-story.html">the LGBTQ+ community</a>.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/f3/9c/2bb7db3941a590723ab611a4c636/turkey-erdogan-explainer-88564.jpg"></figure><p>The fear of those who suffocate us  is that Turkeys Century, of which we are giving the good news today, will one day come to their doorstep, Erdogan said in a victory speech to his supporters after the election. All the traps set in front of Turkey for the last 10 years, all the games played on it, all the daggers in its back, all the trips in its feet are to prevent today.  This is that day. You are here for it.</p><p>The rhetoric echoes that of other leaders who have ridden similar waves of nationalism and nostalgia, such as former President Trump with his MAGA promises, former British Prime Minister <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2019-12-19/queen-boris-johnson-brexit-plan">Boris Johnson and his Brexit cheerleading</a>, and President Vladimir Putins revanchism in Russia.</p><p>You have this conception of a golden past and youre trying to retrieve it. You have a community you blame for having robbed you of this golden past, and you organize your politics in opposition to them, said Selim Koru, a Turkey-based political analyst.</p><p>It also promotes a paranoid view of the opposition, under which Erdogans supporters need to be constantly vigilant for any sign of his enemies conniving against him.</p><p>The idea is always that history is derailed from its original path in which youre the good guys  youre supposed to win  but the bad guys have won, and you need to reverse things, Koru said.</p><p>In a challenge for Washington and Europe, the list of antagonists <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world/middleeast/la-fg-turkey-referendum-20170417-story.html">increasingly includes the West</a>.</p><p>Two days before the runoff, Interior Minister Suleyman Soylu, an Erdogan ally, said that after the election, whoever pursues a pro-American policy in Turkey will be labeled a traitor.</p> Housing shortage plus earthquake risk? It's not just a problem in L.A.<p>During his victory speech, Erdogan gloated that German, French and English magazines published covers to bring down Erdogan? They also lost.</p><p>With <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world/la-fg-turkey-kurdish-prisoner-20190520-story.html">so much talk of adversaries</a>, whether real or imagined, Erdogan is shifting Turkeys traditional stance on the geopolitical stage, said Aydintasbas of the Brookings Institution.</p><p>Thats possibly Erdogans legacy: He has rebranded Turkey as a rising, nonaligned power  a power that has no friends but only enemies, she said.</p><p>Beyond military prowess, Erdogans vision encompasses a new constitution and social changes, such as enshrining womens right to wear headscarves  a central issue for many conservatives in the country  and protecting the family institution from the threat of deviant currents.</p> Turkish police in Syria capture man allegedly linked to deadly Istanbul bombing<p>Erdogans promise of Turkish exceptionalism strikes a chord with voters like Ali Ozman, a 63-year-old mechanic from Istanbul who has been a devotee of Erdogans since he began his political career as <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world/la-fg-istanbul-mayor-election-ekrem-imamoglu-20190623-story.html">the citys mayor</a> in 1994.</p><p>The other side doesnt have a project like he does, no plan that they share with people, said Ozman, who spoke rhapsodically of all the improvements  clearing away trash, building roads and hospitals  he attributes to Erdogan. I feel safe, and that the path for our youth is open now.</p><p>In the end, Erdogans rosy view of the countrys future resonated with voters more than the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-05-22/erdogan-wins-endorsement-for-turkish-election-runoff-from-third-place-candidate-ogan">oppositions focus on his missteps</a>, said Harun Kucuk, a director at the University of Pennsylvanias Middle East Center.</p><p>The opposition said all these problems were Erdogans making; they were a doctor curing a sickness, whereas Erdogan doesnt do that, he said.</p><p>I dont know how much of Erdogans constituency are ideologically well informed. But he does make them feel good about the future.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Man who told jurors he had 'fun' at the Capitol riot sentenced to 6 years in prison</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/man-who-told-jurors-he-had-fun-at-the-capitol-riot-is-sentenced-to-6-years-in-prison</link>
      <description>Markus Maly's prison sentence is significantly lower than the punishment that prosecutors sought for his role in the Jan. 6, 2021, insurrection.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 18:47:37 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>MICHAEL KUNZELMAN</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/man-who-told-jurors-he-had-fun-at-the-capitol-riot-is-sentenced-to-6-years-in-prison</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/man-who-told-jurors-he-had-fun-at-the-capitol-riot-is-sentenced-to-6-years-in-prison">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/463ccdb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5474x3649+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fca%2Ffa%2F343dc1035c8e6d53796c1554d0bc%2Ff154b9621861483a8b4e8b6e82dbdaaf 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/03614bb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5474x3649+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fca%2Ffa%2F343dc1035c8e6d53796c1554d0bc%2Ff154b9621861483a8b4e8b6e82dbdaaf 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ca4e317/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5474x3649+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fca%2Ffa%2F343dc1035c8e6d53796c1554d0bc%2Ff154b9621861483a8b4e8b6e82dbdaaf 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6b139f6/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5474x3649+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fca%2Ffa%2F343dc1035c8e6d53796c1554d0bc%2Ff154b9621861483a8b4e8b6e82dbdaaf 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/60e6b36/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5474x3649+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fca%2Ffa%2F343dc1035c8e6d53796c1554d0bc%2Ff154b9621861483a8b4e8b6e82dbdaaf 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="This image from police body-worn video, released and annotated by the Justice Department in the statement of facts supporting an arrest warrant for Markus Maly, shows Maly, circled in red, at the U.S. Capitol on Jan. 6, 2021, in Washington. (Justice Department via AP)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/a03e8ec/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5474x3649+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fca%2Ffa%2F343dc1035c8e6d53796c1554d0bc%2Ff154b9621861483a8b4e8b6e82dbdaaf 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/70a7732/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5474x3649+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fca%2Ffa%2F343dc1035c8e6d53796c1554d0bc%2Ff154b9621861483a8b4e8b6e82dbdaaf 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6415aa1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5474x3649+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fca%2Ffa%2F343dc1035c8e6d53796c1554d0bc%2Ff154b9621861483a8b4e8b6e82dbdaaf 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c83c5cd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5474x3649+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fca%2Ffa%2F343dc1035c8e6d53796c1554d0bc%2Ff154b9621861483a8b4e8b6e82dbdaaf 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3a39208/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5474x3649+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fca%2Ffa%2F343dc1035c8e6d53796c1554d0bc%2Ff154b9621861483a8b4e8b6e82dbdaaf 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3a39208/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5474x3649+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fca%2Ffa%2F343dc1035c8e6d53796c1554d0bc%2Ff154b9621861483a8b4e8b6e82dbdaaf"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">This image from police body-worn video, released and annotated by the Justice Department in the statement of facts supporting an arrest warrant for Markus Maly, shows Maly, circled in red, at the U.S. Capitol on Jan. 6, 2021, in Washington. (Justice Department via AP)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Uncredited / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Man who told jurors he had &#x27;fun&#x27; at the Capitol riot sentenced to 6 years in prison</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" >        MICHAEL KUNZELMAN    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>A Virginia man who told his wife  and a federal jury  that he had fun at the U.S. Capitol riot was sentenced </p>on <p>Friday to six years in prison for attacking police as he stormed the building.</p><p>Markus Maly's prison sentence is significantly lower than the punishment that prosecutors sought for his role in the Jan. 6, 2021, insurrection. The Justice Department had recommended a prison sentence of 15 years and eight months for Maly, a flooring installer.</p><p>A prosecutor described Maly, 49, as a lifelong criminal with 33 prior convictions on his record, including two for battery of a law enforcement officer. But the judge who sentenced Maly noted that most of his crimes date back to his 20s.</p><p>Maly told U.S. District Judge Amit Mehta that he regrets traveling to Washington and following the mob of then-President </p>Donald <p>Trump's supporters to the Capitol. But he insisted that he merely occupied space in the crowd and denied attacking and pepper-spraying police.</p><p>I went to a rally. That's what I did," he told the judge.</p><p>The judge said jurors had ample evidence to convict Maly of assaulting police.</p> Enrique Tarrio, 3 other Proud Boys members convicted of sedition in Jan. 6 riot<p>"It's not that you were there and occupying space. It's that you did these things and kept doing them that day, the judge told him.</p><p>Prosecutors say Maly is one of many Capitol rioters who have tried to profit from their notoriety, portraying themselves as patriots, martyrs or political prisoners as they solicit donations from supporters. While prosecutors acknowledge that defendants have a right to raise money for legal defenses, they're increasingly asking judges to impose fines on top of prison terms to claw back donations used for personal expenses.</p><p>Maly has raised more than $16,500 through a GiveSendGo donation page, referring to himself as a January 6 P.O.W." Prosecutors asked the judge to fine him an amount commensurate with his fundraising haul, noting that he had a public defender and didn't owe any legal fees.</p><p>The judge declined to impose a fine. He said Maly's fundraising activities may have been unseemly, but he questioned whether there was a legal basis for clawing back the money. </p><p>Maly testified at his trial that participating in the Capitol riot was fun for him. He also described the events of Jan. 6 as fun and awesome in messages sent to his wife and others.</p><p>Maly admitted to being proud of what he had done at the Capitol and that he had bragged about it, prosecutor Stephen Rancourt wrote in <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.dcd.228318/gov.uscourts.dcd.228318.204.0.pdf">a court filing</a>. Despite seeing police officers assaulted, injured, and distressed on January 6, and knowing that it was a bad day for members of Congress and the police officers who had to live through the riot, Maly reiterated that his experience that day was fun. </p> Oath Keepers founder Stewart Rhodes convicted of seditious conspiracy in Jan. 6 case<p>The judge at Maly's trial previously handed down the longest sentence for a Capitol riot case: 18 years for Oath Keepers founder Stewart Rhodes, who was convicted of orchestrating a violent plot to keep Trump, a Republican, in the White House after he lost the 2020 presidential election to Joe Biden, a Democrat.</p><p>Maly has been jailed since a jury convicted him in December of all eight charges against him, including felony counts of civil disorder and assaulting, resisting or impeding police using a dangerous weapon.</p><p>On the morning of Jan. 6, Maly took a bus from his home in Fincastle, V</p>irgini<p>a., to Washington to attend Trump's Stop the Steal rally. He later joined the mob that attacked police on the Capitol's Lower West Terrace, one of the most violent clashes of the day.</p><p>Maly sprayed a chemical, possibly pepper spray, at Metropolitan Police Department Officer Christopher Boyle as he and other officers retreated into a tunnel and guarded an entrance. Maly passed a spray can</p>n<p>ister from one rioter to another, joined a coordinated heave-ho push against police and left the tunnel with a stolen riot shield as a trophy, Rancourt said.</p><p>Maly was charged and tried with co-defendants <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.dcd.228319/gov.uscourts.dcd.228319.1.1.pdf">Peter Schwartz</a> and <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.dcd.236943/gov.uscourts.dcd.236943.1.1.pdf">Jeffrey Scott Brown</a>. Schwartz passed the spray canister to Maly, who passed it to Brown. The jurors who convicted Maly also found Schwartz and Brown guilty of related charges.</p> Prosecutor: Proud Boys viewed themselves as 'Trump's army'<p>The judge sentenced Schwartz last month to 14 years and two months in prison, the longest for a Jan. 6 case before Rhodes, and sentenced Brown in April to four years and six months in prison.</p><p>Prosecutors say Maly lied on the witness stand when he testified that he only showed a can</p>n<p>ister to Boyle but didnt spray the officer.</p><p>Maly claimed that the stream of liquid coming out of the canister was actually a piece of fringe on his hat. However, his hat didnt have a fringe, Rancourt wrote.</p><p>Defense attorney Benjamin Schiffelbein said Maly believed that the 2020 presidential election was stolen from Trump. </p><p>He fervently believed that he was protesting in the name of liberty and freedom. His motives, however [factually] wrong they may have been, were based in values this country celebrates, <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.dcd.240029/gov.uscourts.dcd.240029.206.0_1.pdf">Schiffelbein wrote</a>. "What is more American than fervently defending democracy  even from ones own government  and perhaps especially then?"</p><p>More than 100 police officers were injured during the riot. More than 1,000 people have been charged with federal crimes related to Jan. 6. </p>Over  More than<p> 500 of them have been sentenced, with more than half getting terms of imprisonment, according to an Associated Press review of court records.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chief suspect in Natalee Holloway disappearance pleads not guilty</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/chief-suspect-in-natalee-holloway-disappearance-pleads-not-guilty</link>
      <description>The chief suspect in the 2005 disappearance of Natalee Holloway pleaded not guilty to charges that he tried to extort the missing teen's mother.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 18:21:31 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>KIM CHANDLER</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/chief-suspect-in-natalee-holloway-disappearance-pleads-not-guilty</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/chief-suspect-in-natalee-holloway-disappearance-pleads-not-guilty">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/11bfc91/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3204x2136+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F71%2Fd7%2Fda981164fd3689c77cca43560136%2Fcb3dda666a2e4a7cbdade5097b51db9d 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/65e3255/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3204x2136+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F71%2Fd7%2Fda981164fd3689c77cca43560136%2Fcb3dda666a2e4a7cbdade5097b51db9d 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/83a5a7c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3204x2136+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F71%2Fd7%2Fda981164fd3689c77cca43560136%2Fcb3dda666a2e4a7cbdade5097b51db9d 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/bfca6ed/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3204x2136+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F71%2Fd7%2Fda981164fd3689c77cca43560136%2Fcb3dda666a2e4a7cbdade5097b51db9d 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/439bde9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3204x2136+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F71%2Fd7%2Fda981164fd3689c77cca43560136%2Fcb3dda666a2e4a7cbdade5097b51db9d 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Dutch citizen Joran van der Sloot is driven in a police vehicle from the Ancon I maximum-security prison, outskirts of Lima, Peru, Thursday, June 8, 2023. The main suspect in the unsolved 2005 disappearance of American student Natalee Holloway on the Caribbean island of Aruba is expected to be extradited Thursday from Peru to the United States. (AP Photo/Martin Mejia)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d4180df/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3204x2136+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F71%2Fd7%2Fda981164fd3689c77cca43560136%2Fcb3dda666a2e4a7cbdade5097b51db9d 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8004b2d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3204x2136+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F71%2Fd7%2Fda981164fd3689c77cca43560136%2Fcb3dda666a2e4a7cbdade5097b51db9d 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8915ada/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3204x2136+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F71%2Fd7%2Fda981164fd3689c77cca43560136%2Fcb3dda666a2e4a7cbdade5097b51db9d 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c1d23ba/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3204x2136+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F71%2Fd7%2Fda981164fd3689c77cca43560136%2Fcb3dda666a2e4a7cbdade5097b51db9d 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f324a02/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3204x2136+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F71%2Fd7%2Fda981164fd3689c77cca43560136%2Fcb3dda666a2e4a7cbdade5097b51db9d 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f324a02/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3204x2136+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F71%2Fd7%2Fda981164fd3689c77cca43560136%2Fcb3dda666a2e4a7cbdade5097b51db9d"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Dutch citizen Joran van der Sloot is driven in a police vehicle from the Ancon I maximum-security prison, outskirts of Lima, Peru, Thursday, June 8, 2023. The main suspect in the unsolved 2005 disappearance of American student Natalee Holloway on the Caribbean island of Aruba is expected to be extradited Thursday from Peru to the United States. (AP Photo/Martin Mejia)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Martin Mejia / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Chief suspect in Natalee Holloway disappearance pleads not guilty</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" >        KIM CHANDLER    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Joran van der Sloot, the chief suspect in the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/blogs/nation-now/story/2012-01-12/natalee-holloway-declared-legally-dead-at-fathers-request">2005 disappearance of Natalee Holloway,</a> pleaded not guilty Friday to federal charges that he tried to extort money from the missing teens mother in exchange for revealing the location of </p>her  Natalee's <p>body.</p><p>Van der Sloot, 35, was extradited to the United States on Thursday from Peru, where he is serving a 28-year prison sentence after confessing to killing a Peruvian woman. He was arraigned in Birmingham, not far from the suburb where Holloway grew up, in his first court appearance in the case.</p><p>Natalees mother, Beth Holloway, watched the brief proceeding from the third row of the courtroom. She stared occasionally at </p>v V<p>an der Sloot but showed no obvious emotion. </p><p>For 18 years, I have lived with the unbearable pain of Natalees loss, she said in a statement Thursday. Each day has been filled with unanswered questions and a longing for justice that has eluded us at every turn. But today ... I am hopeful that some small semblance of justice may finally be realized.</p> Main suspect in Natalee Holloway disappearance arrives in U.S. from Peru to face charges<p>Afterward, she hugged friends who had come to offer their support along with Natalees father and brother. She declined to comment to reporters outside the courthouse.</p><p>Shackled and wearing jeans and a white T-shirt, </p>v<p>Van der Sloot declined to use a Dutch interpreter offered to him at Fridays arraignment. He sat beside his court-appointed attorney, Kevin Butler, who entered the not guilty pleas on his behalf.</p><p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/blogs/nation-now/story/2012-01-13/natalee-holloway-justice-joran-van-der-sloot-gets-28-years">Van der Sloot</a> is charged with one count each of extortion and wire fraud  the only charges to have ever linked the Dutch citizen to Holloways disappearance on the Caribbean island of Aruba. </p><p>Natalee Holloway, 18, was on a high school graduation trip with classmates in Aruba when she vanished in 2005. She was last seen leaving a bar with </p>v<p>Van der Sloot, who was a student at an international school on the island. Van der Sloot was identified as a main suspect and detained weeks later for questioning, along with two Surinamese brothers, but no charges were filed in the case. </p> Suspect in Natalee Holloway's 2005 disappearance to be extradited from Peru to U.S.<p>A judge declared Holloway dead, but her body has never been found. </p><p>The mysterious disappearance sparked years of news coverage and countless true-crime podcasts.</p><p>U.S. prosecutors say that in 2010, </p>v<p>Van der Sloot reached out to Beth Holloway, seeking $250,000 to lead her to the young woman's body and reveal the circumstances of her death. A grand jury indicted him that year.</p><p>In 2012, </p>v<p>Van der Sloot pleaded guilty in Peru to killing 21-year-old Stephany Flores, a business student from a prominent Peruvian family. She was killed in 2010  five years to the day after Holloways disappearance.</p><p>Van der Sloot married a Peruvian woman in July 2014 in a ceremony at a maximum-security prison. He was shuffled between prisons in response to reports he enjoyed privileges like television, internet access and a cellphone, and accusations he threatened to kill a warden.</p> In reversal, suspect in Natalee Holloway's disappearance will fight extradition to U.S.<p>A 2001 treaty between Peru and the U.S. allows a suspect to be temporarily extradited to face trial in the other country. Van der Sloots attorney, Mximo Altez, initially indicated his client would not challenge his extradition but that changed Monday when he filed a writ of habeas corpus. A judge ruled against </p>v<p>Van der Sloot the following day.</p><p>Peru has agreed to let </p>v<p>Van der Sloot remain in U.S. custody until the Alabama case is concluded, including any appeal if he is convicted, according to a resolution published in Perus federal register. U.S. authorities agree to return him to Peru's custody after that, the resolution states.</p><p>Van der Sloot's arrival at the Birmingham courthouse</p>, about 10 miles (16 kilometers) from Mountain Brook High School,<p> was something of a day of reckoning for a state and a city that blames him for Holloways disappearance.</p><p>It made me sick. I gasped, but Im so grateful that hes here, said Cindy Rysedorph, a friend of the Holloway family, as she described her first glimpse of </p>v<p>Van der Sloot in the courtroom.</p><p>Were not trying him for murder  which we know he committed, she said. Were trying him for the extortion. But yeah, its progress. </p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump indicted on 37 charges including Espionage Act violations in classified records case</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/politics/story/2023-06-09/trump-indictment-details-espionage-obstruction-charges</link>
      <description>Indictment accuses Trump of keeping classified and top-secret documents regarding defense and weapons capabilities of U.S. and foreign countries.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 18:08:49 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Sarah D. Wire</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/politics/story/2023-06-09/trump-indictment-details-espionage-obstruction-charges</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/politics/story/2023-06-09/trump-indictment-details-espionage-obstruction-charges">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/06e842c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffb%2F9d%2F4460960b4b35a8130cbd4d343118%2Ftrump-fla-indictment-03.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d070f89/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffb%2F9d%2F4460960b4b35a8130cbd4d343118%2Ftrump-fla-indictment-03.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/289072a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffb%2F9d%2F4460960b4b35a8130cbd4d343118%2Ftrump-fla-indictment-03.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8eda70a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffb%2F9d%2F4460960b4b35a8130cbd4d343118%2Ftrump-fla-indictment-03.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f6c4f79/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffb%2F9d%2F4460960b4b35a8130cbd4d343118%2Ftrump-fla-indictment-03.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Photo illustration of Donald Trump rear view with screenshots of the Florida indictment papers"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/f13f460/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffb%2F9d%2F4460960b4b35a8130cbd4d343118%2Ftrump-fla-indictment-03.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d8ec3c3/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffb%2F9d%2F4460960b4b35a8130cbd4d343118%2Ftrump-fla-indictment-03.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/baaff98/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffb%2F9d%2F4460960b4b35a8130cbd4d343118%2Ftrump-fla-indictment-03.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6b70e0f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffb%2F9d%2F4460960b4b35a8130cbd4d343118%2Ftrump-fla-indictment-03.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4908e74/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffb%2F9d%2F4460960b4b35a8130cbd4d343118%2Ftrump-fla-indictment-03.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4908e74/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3000x2000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Ffb%2F9d%2F4460960b4b35a8130cbd4d343118%2Ftrump-fla-indictment-03.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-credit">(Jim Cooke/Los Angeles Times, photo by Kent Nishimura/Los Angeles Times)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Trump indicted on 37 charges including Espionage Act violations in classified records case</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/sarah-d-wire">        Sarah D. Wire    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Former President Trump was indicted on </p> 37 charges, including 31 counts of violations of the Espionage Act<p>, as part of special counsel Jack Smiths investigation into </p> Trump's the mis<p>handling of classified documents from </p> his time in <p>the </p>Trump <p>White House</p> .<p>The 49-page indictment, released Friday by the Department of Justice, details accusations that Trump stored boxes containing classified documents in various locations at Mar-a-Lago, his Florida estate, including a ballroom, a bathroom and shower, his office, his bedroom and a storage room. </p><p>According to the indictment, among the top-secret and other classified records were details on foreign nations' nuclear capabilities, as well as information regarding defense and weapons capabilities of both U.S. and foreign countries, U.S. nuclear programs, potential vulnerabilities of the U.S. and its allies to military attack, and plans for possible retaliation in response to an attack.</p><p>The indictment includes several photos of the boxes in different locations around Mar-a-Lago, including on a ballroom stage, where they stayed for two months while the ballroom continued to be used for events, and a bathroom and shower. One of the photos shows a stack of boxes that had fallen over in a storage room. Visible in the photo are documents marked with a designation that the information can only be released to the closest allies of the U.S.: Australia, Canada, New Zealand and the United Kingdom.</p><p>Trump is charged with willful retention of national defense information; conspiracy to obstruct justice; withholding a document or record; corruptly concealing a document in a federal investigation; scheming to conceal; and false statements and representations.</p><p>In a brief televised statement, Smith urged the public to read the indictment in order to understand "the gravity of the crimes charged." He also said he was aiming for a speedy trial.</p><p>The men and women of the United States intelligence community and our armed forces dedicate their lives to protecting our nation and its people. Our laws that protect national defense information are critical to the safety and security of the United States and they must be enforced, Smith said. "We have one set of laws in this country and they apply to everyone."</p><p>The indictment details accusations that in two instances in 2021, Trump shared classified information with people who lacked security clearances. The indictment also confirms a CNN report on the existence of a recording in which Trump indicates understanding that he cannot declassify records after leaving office and acknowledges that he possesses a classified record.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/ff/67/601cc6bf424a8d142cb521c10425/trump-classified-documents-39430.jpg"></figure><p>The investigation began after the National Archives found classified records in a batch of documents Trump returned </p> in 2022,<p> a year after leaving office. Justice Department officials then sought a subpoena demanding that he return any other classified material in his possession. </p><p>The indictment cites notes from a May 23</p> , 2022, <p>conversation between Trump and his lawyer Evan Corcoran in which the former president questioned whether he had to fully comply with the subpoena, including making the statements, "I don't want anybody looking through my boxes. I don't want you looking through my boxes," "Wouldn't it be better if we just told them we don't have anything here?" and, "Well look, isn't it better if there are no documents?"</p><p>Trumps legal team ultimately produced about three dozen additional documents and a letter stating that a diligent search had turned up nothing more. But the indictment says Trump's lawyers didn't have access to all of the records for their search. </p><p>The indictment states that between May 23 and June 2 of last year  during the window after the subpoena was issued but before Corcoran could review the documents  Trump had his personal aide Waltine "Walt" Nauta move 64 boxes out of the Mar-a-Lago storage room to Trump's residence so the former president could go through the contents, and that Nauta later returned only 30 boxes to the storage room. This was hidden from Corcoran, according to the indictment.</p><figure> <img src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/e0/49/16c4128d448090e5829c95f52047/aptopix-trump-classified-documents-23595.jpg"></figure><p>The Justice Department learned of the move and the possibility that classified documents remained at the estate, and gained judicial approval for a search warrant. More than <a href="https://www.latimes.com/politics/story/2022-09-02/judge-unseals-detailed-inventory-of-mar-a-lago-search">100 documents with classified markings were found</a> during an FBI search of Mar-a-Lago that August. The indictment states that the recovered classified records came from the CIA, the Defense Department, the National Security Agency and the State Department, among other sources.</p><p>Nauta was indicted alongside Trump on charges of conspiracy to obstruct justice, withholding a document or record, corruptly concealing a document in a federal investigation, scheming to conceal and making false statements and representations.</p><p>Trump defended Nauta, a Navy veteran who was frequently by his side in the White House, in a Truth Social post before the indictment was made public.</p><p>"He has done a fantastic job! They are trying to destroy his life, like the lives of so many others, hoping that he will say bad things about 'Trump,' the former president said of Nauta.</p><p>The special counsel's investigation has focused in part on Nauta, who is reportedly seen on surveillance video helping a maintenance worker move boxes from the storage room before the FBI executed the search warrant at Mar-a-Lago.</p><p>According to the indictment, Nauta made multiple false statements, including saying he was not aware the boxes had been taken to Trumps residence for review before 15 of them were sent to the National Archives, and didn't know how boxes taken to a National Archives truck had come to be in the residence; and that he falsely denied knowing where the boxes had been stored before they were found in Trumps residence, saying, I wish I could tell you. I dont know. I dont  I honestly just dont know.</p><p>Trump announced<a href="https://www.latimes.com/politics/story/2023-06-08/trump-special-counsel-indictment-classified-documents"> in a social media post Thursday</a> that he had been indicted in connection with his handling of the records and had been ordered to appear in federal court in Miami on Tuesday afternoon. The indictment comes nearly a year after more than 100 documents with classified markings were found during the FBI's search of Mar-a-Lago.</p><p>The case appears to have been initially directed toward U.S. District Court Judge Aileen Cannon, a Trump appointee who handled his lawsuit last year over the FBI search. Cannons <a href="https://www.latimes.com/politics/story/2022-12-01/appeals-court-special-master-trump-documents">decision to appoint a special master</a> to review materials seized in the search delayed the investigation for several weeks.</p><p>Trump has repeatedly denied any wrongdoing, and claimed again late Thursday that he was innocent. On Friday he announced that he was shaking up his legal team, replacing attorneys Jim Trusty and John Rowley with New York-based Todd Blanche and a firm to be named later. Blanche is assisting with Trump's other indictment on <a href="https://www.latimes.com/politics/story/2023-03-30/trump-indictment-stormy-daniels">34 felony charges related to an alleged hush money payment</a> to porn actor Stormy Daniels in the final days of the 2016 campaign.</p><p>Trusty and Rowley said in a joint statement that they had resigned, calling it a logical moment to leave because the case had moved to Miami.</p><p>Trump and his allies quickly framed the new indictment as an attempt to diminish him as a political opponent, with some such as Sen. Josh Hawley (R-Mo.) misrepresenting the legal process.</p><p>"If the people in power can jail their political opponents at will, we dont have a republic," Hawley, a lawyer and former state attorney general, tweeted.</p><p>Such claims disregard that it was a grand jury that recommended the charges based on evidence presented to it, and that it will be a jury that decides Trump's guilt or innocence on the charges based on the evidence provided in court.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Colombia's government, largest remaining rebel group agree to cease-fire at talks in Cuba</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/colombias-government-largest-remaining-rebel-group-agree-to-cease-fire-at-talks-in-cuba</link>
      <description>Colombia’s government and the National Liberation Army, or ELN, declared a cease-fire agreement, the latest attempt to resolve a decades-long conflict.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 18:07:05 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>ANDREA RODRÍGUEZ</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/colombias-government-largest-remaining-rebel-group-agree-to-cease-fire-at-talks-in-cuba</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/colombias-government-largest-remaining-rebel-group-agree-to-cease-fire-at-talks-in-cuba">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/20b76a1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3988x2558+0+0/resize/320x205!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fae%2Fa5%2F170de0a74e7982a19fffedb344a6%2Fcuba-colombia-eln-peace-talks-66924.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c022d10/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3988x2558+0+0/resize/568x364!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fae%2Fa5%2F170de0a74e7982a19fffedb344a6%2Fcuba-colombia-eln-peace-talks-66924.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ee2385c/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3988x2558+0+0/resize/768x493!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fae%2Fa5%2F170de0a74e7982a19fffedb344a6%2Fcuba-colombia-eln-peace-talks-66924.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/447dcd1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3988x2558+0+0/resize/1024x657!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fae%2Fa5%2F170de0a74e7982a19fffedb344a6%2Fcuba-colombia-eln-peace-talks-66924.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/86e8b5e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3988x2558+0+0/resize/1200x770!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fae%2Fa5%2F170de0a74e7982a19fffedb344a6%2Fcuba-colombia-eln-peace-talks-66924.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Jose Otty Patio, chief negotiator for the Colombian government, left, Nicols Rodrguez Bautista alias &quot;Gabino,&quot; former commander of the Colombian National Liberation Army (ELN), center, and ELN Commander Pablo Beltran gather for a group photo at the inauguration of the third cycle of peace negotiations between the ELN and the Colombian government in Havana, Cuba, Tuesday, May 2, 2023. (AP Photo/Ramon Espinosa)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ea7c84f/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3988x2558+0+0/resize/320x205!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fae%2Fa5%2F170de0a74e7982a19fffedb344a6%2Fcuba-colombia-eln-peace-talks-66924.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/e70a449/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3988x2558+0+0/resize/568x364!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fae%2Fa5%2F170de0a74e7982a19fffedb344a6%2Fcuba-colombia-eln-peace-talks-66924.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/6bacb76/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3988x2558+0+0/resize/768x493!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fae%2Fa5%2F170de0a74e7982a19fffedb344a6%2Fcuba-colombia-eln-peace-talks-66924.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/814a63a/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3988x2558+0+0/resize/1024x657!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fae%2Fa5%2F170de0a74e7982a19fffedb344a6%2Fcuba-colombia-eln-peace-talks-66924.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/58678fb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3988x2558+0+0/resize/1200x770!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fae%2Fa5%2F170de0a74e7982a19fffedb344a6%2Fcuba-colombia-eln-peace-talks-66924.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="770"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/58678fb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3988x2558+0+0/resize/1200x770!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fae%2Fa5%2F170de0a74e7982a19fffedb344a6%2Fcuba-colombia-eln-peace-talks-66924.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Jose Otty Patio, chief negotiator for the Colombian government, left, Nicols Rodrguez Bautista alias Gabino, former commander of the Colombian National Liberation Army (ELN), center, and ELN Commander Pablo Beltran gather for a group photo at the inauguration of the third cycle of peace negotiations between the ELN and the Colombian government in Havana, Cuba, Tuesday, May 2, 2023. (AP Photo/Ramon Espinosa)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Ramon Espinosa / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Colombia&#x27;s government, largest remaining rebel group agree to cease-fire at talks in Cuba</h1>                                                                            <h3 class="op-kicker">Mexico &amp; the Americas</h3>                                                                            <address>    <a rel="author" >        ANDREA RODRGUEZ    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Colombias government and the countrys largest remaining guerrilla group declared a cease-fire agreement Friday at talks in Cuba, the latest attempt to resolve a conflict dating </p>back <p>to the 1960s.</p><p>The government and the National Liberation Army, or ELN, announced the accord at a ceremony in Havana attended by <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2022-06-20/petro-faces-challenges-to-deliver-colombians-promised-change">Colombian President Gustavo Petro</a>, top guerrilla commander Antonio Garca and Cuban officials. The cease-fire takes effect in phases and goes fully into effect in August. </p><p>This effort to look for peace is a light of hope that conflicts can be solved politically and diplomatically," top rebel negotiator <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-05-16/colombian-rebel-leader-peace-talks-on-pause">Pablo Beltrn</a> said at the ceremony.</p><p>The talks originally were scheduled to conclude with an official ceremony </p>on <p>Thursday, but were postponed as the parties asked for additional time to work on final details. Petro traveled to the island for the ceremony, saying it could herald an era of peace in Colombia.</p><p>Negotiations between the sides resumed in August, after being terminated in 2019 when the rebels set off a car bomb at a police academy in Bogota</p> ,<p> killing 21 people.</p><p>Following that incident, the government of then President Ivn Duque issued arrest warrants for ELN leaders in Cuba for the peace negotiations. But Cuba refused to extradite them, arguing that doing so would compromise its status as a neutral nation in the conflict and break with diplomatic protocols.</p><p>Talks relaunched in November shortly after <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2022-06-21/leftists-election-to-test-colombias-alliance-with-us">Petro was elected as Colombias first leftist president</a>.</p><p>Petro has pushed for what he calls a total peace that would demobilize all of the countrys rema</p> i<p>ning rebel groups as well as its drug trafficking gangs. He has questioned whether senior ELN leaders have full control of a younger generation of commanders who he has suggested are focused more on the illegal drug trade than on political goals. </p><p>The ELN was founded in the 1960s by union leaders, students and priests inspired by the Cuban revolution. It is Colombias largest remaining rebel group and has been notoriously difficult for previous Colombian governments to negotiate with.</p><p>In 2016, Colombias government <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world/mexico-americas/la-fg-colombia-disarmament-20170627-story.html">signed a peace deal with the larger FARC group</a> that ended five decades of conflict in which an estimated 260,000 people were killed.</p><p>But violence has continued to affect rural pockets of the country where the ELN has been fighting the Gulf Clan and FARC holdout groups for the control of drug trafficking routes and other resources.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>'They’re 100% not human': Las Vegas police investigate reports of extraterrestrial sightings</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-09/las-vegas-police-investigate-reports-of-alien-sightings</link>
      <description>Dispatchers last month received a 911 call from a Las Vegas area resident reporting extraterrestrial life in his backyard, about an hour after local police witnessed an object falling from the sky.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 17:16:04 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Alexandra E. Petri</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-09/las-vegas-police-investigate-reports-of-alien-sightings</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-06-09/las-vegas-police-investigate-reports-of-alien-sightings">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8bb26f4/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F60%2F0785bb924daaa855c571201f8e53%2Fap22137511012544.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/edda6fc/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F60%2F0785bb924daaa855c571201f8e53%2Fap22137511012544.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7e04586/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F60%2F0785bb924daaa855c571201f8e53%2Fap22137511012544.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/99145c1/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F60%2F0785bb924daaa855c571201f8e53%2Fap22137511012544.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c99ef41/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F60%2F0785bb924daaa855c571201f8e53%2Fap22137511012544.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Deputy Director of Naval Intelligence Scott Bray points to a video display of a UAP "                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/21bdd49/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F60%2F0785bb924daaa855c571201f8e53%2Fap22137511012544.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/fd3b315/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F60%2F0785bb924daaa855c571201f8e53%2Fap22137511012544.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/3790c33/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F60%2F0785bb924daaa855c571201f8e53%2Fap22137511012544.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0a14453/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F60%2F0785bb924daaa855c571201f8e53%2Fap22137511012544.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/54d6e06/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F60%2F0785bb924daaa855c571201f8e53%2Fap22137511012544.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/54d6e06/2147483647/strip/true/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F60%2F0785bb924daaa855c571201f8e53%2Fap22137511012544.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption">Deputy Director of Naval Intelligence Scott Bray points to a video display of a UAP during a hearing of the House Intelligence, Counterterrorism, Counterintelligence, and Counterproliferation Subcommittee hearing on Unidentified Aerial Phenomena, on Capitol Hill, Tuesday, May 17, 2022, in Washington. (AP Photo/Alex Brandon)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Alex Brandon/Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>&#x27;Theyre 100% not human&#x27;: Las Vegas police investigate reports of extraterrestrial sightings</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" href="https://www.latimes.com/people/alexandra-e-petri">        Alexandra E. Petri    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Big, shiny eyes. Towering nearly 10 feet tall. 100% not human. Aliens.</p><p>Thats the 911 call that came into dispatchers last month from a Las Vegas area resident reporting extraterrestrial life in his backyard, just about an hour after local police witnessed an object falling from the sky.</p><p>The paranormal investigation by police did not turn up any answers.</p><p>On May 1, 2023, at approximately 12:29 a.m. LVMPD dispatch received a call about a suspicious situation, the Las Vegas Police Department said in an email statement. Officer conducted a preliminary investigation and closed the event as unfounded."<b>&nbsp;</b></p><p>At around 11:50 p.m. on April 30, body camera footage from an officer with the Las Vegas Metropolitan Police <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=anW4N1Vl_ko" target="_blank">captured a bright, glowing object</a> cutting through the sky, <a href="https://abc7.com/las-vegas-aliens-ufo-alien-news/13359881/" target="_blank">according to local TV channel 8 News Now.</a></p><p>About 40 minutes later, a local resident placed a 911 call to report that something 100% not human was staring at him from his backyard shortly after he and his family saw an object fall from the sky, the station reported.</p><figure class="op-interactive"> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=anW4N1Vl_ko" width="560" height="315"></iframe></figure><p>Theres like an 8-foot person beside it, and another ones inside us, and it has big eyes and its looking at us  and its still there, the caller, who said that he and his family had seen something fall from the sky, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YWGOkut_-Xw" target="_blank">told the dispatcher</a>.</p><p>I swear to God this is not a joke, this is actually  were terrified, the caller said.</p><p>Local TV channel 8 News Now first reported the story and obtained the video and audio from that weird evening, including the 911 call and body camera footage.</p><p>The dispatcher clarified the situation with the caller, careful to choose the right words.</p><p>So, theres two people  theres two subjects in your backyard? the dispatcher asked.</p><p>Correct, and they're very large, the caller said. Theyre like 8 foot, 9 feet, 10 foot. They look like aliens to us. Big eyes. They have big eyes. Like, I cant explain it, and big mouth. Theyre shiny eyes and theyre human. Theyre 100% not human.</p><p>Two officers responded to the callers home, KLAS reported.</p><p>Im so nervous right now, one of the responding officers said while en route to the house. I have butterflies bro. He continues to say that people saw a shooting star, and now these people say theres aliens in their backyard.</p><p>Officers interviewed the family on their front lawn.</p><p>What did you see? one of the officers asks.</p><p>It was like a big creature, one witness said, adding it was around 10 feet tall.</p><p>The officer tells them about the incident his colleague saw just before the call came in.</p><p>Im not going to BS you guys. One of my partners said they saw something fall out of the sky, too, the officer said. So thats why Im kind of curious. Did you see anything land in your backyard?</p><p>A man in a robe said some of his family members saw a big something with light plummet from above.</p><p>Police continued to investigate that evening, asking neighbors if they too had witnessed any unusual objects fall from the sky. KLAS reported the investigation lasted for several days.</p><p>The Department of Defense is tracking more than 800 cases of "unidentified aerial phenomena," often called UFOs, from the past 27 years, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/31/us/politics/nasa-ufo-hearing.html" target="_blank">according to government officials</a>, who added that only 2% to 5% of cases can be explained. </p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>U.S. to Pay $18 Million for Nixon Tapes, Papers</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-2000-jun-13-mn-40455-story.html</link>
      <description>Archives: Government settles claim that materials were seized improperly; library to get about $6 million.</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2000 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-2000-jun-13-mn-40455-story.html</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-2000-jun-13-mn-40455-story.html">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                                            <h1>U.S. to Pay $18 Million for Nixon Tapes, Papers</h1>                                                                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 13, 2000">June 13, 2000</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>The federal government has agreed to pay $18 million to the estate of Richard Nixon to settle claims that the Watergate tapes and other presidential materials were improperly seized by the government in 1974 without compensation.</p><p>The out-of-court agreement, climaxing a five-month civil trial that ended last year, would result in $6 million in improvements and expansion for the Richard Nixon Library &amp; Birthplace in Yorba Linda, Calif., and paves the way for copies of his White House tape recordings and papers eventually to be made available at the Orange County facility, officials said.</p><p>Justice Department lawyers argued in federal court last year that placing any value on Nixon's materials was "speculative" and that in no case should payment exceed $2.2 million. Lawyers for Nixon's heirs sought compensation of $213 million for 3,700 hours of tapes and more than 4 million pages of historic White House documents.</p><p>David W. Ogden, the Justice Department official in charge of the case, called it "a fair resolution" that brings to a close 20 years of litigation surrounding Nixon's materials.</p><p>John H. Taylor, executive director of the Nixon Foundation, said in an interview Monday that the agreement was "a fair, equitable and good compromise negotiated in virgin legal territory."</p><p>Shortly after Nixon's resignation in 1974, Congress decreed that the General Services Administration, the parent agency of the National Archives, should seize all his White House recordings and papers to guarantee that Nixon would not destroy them.</p><p>Until that time, presidents traditionally were free to take all their papers and other historic materials with them into retirement. But Congress made an exception in Nixon's case because he was the first president to resign in a criminal scandal. His successor, Gerald R. Ford, granted him a full pardon from any possible future prosecution.</p><p>The Watergate tapes, which Nixon surrendered only when the Supreme Court ruled against him, documented conspiracy and obstruction of justice by Nixon and his top aides and led directly to his resignation on Aug. 9, 1974. His departure came after the House Judiciary Committee had voted articles of impeachment.</p><p>Nixon's lawyers spent subsequent years trying legally to block public access to the Watergate tapes, arguing that many of the conversations were private and privileged. When the Supreme Court rejected their efforts, the lawyers began fighting specific regulations proposed by the National Archives to make the tapes public.</p><p>Meanwhile, the U.S. Court of Appeals ruled in 1992 that Nixon was entitled to "just compensation" for his materials. While this issue still was being adjudicated, Nixon died in 1994 and his daughters began to loosen the family's grip on his materials, in hopes of a better understanding of their father's presidency.</p><p>The settlement must be approved by U.S. District Judge John Garrett Penn, who has had the compensation issue under advisement since closing arguments by the Justice Department and Nixon family lawyers ended last December.</p><p>The Nixon papers and tapes will remain at the National Archives facility in suburban College Park, Md. But the agreement signals that copies may eventually be housed in Orange County, even though the time element is uncertain.</p><p>Taylor said that Nixon's papers, tapes and other materials--if ultimately dispersed to the West Coast as well--will help ensure a better appreciation of Nixon's foreign policy achievements, including bringing the Vietnam War to an end.</p><p>Besides the $6 million for Nixon's library, Nixon's attorneys, led by Herbert J. Miller, will receive $7.4 million, and approximately $3.7 million will go for estate and other federal taxes. After administrative expenses, less than 0.5% will be distributed to Nixon's family.</p><p>Nixon's lawyers argued to Judge Penn that an award of $16 million last August to the heirs of amateur filmmaker Abraham Zapruder by a panel of government-approved arbiters showed that the Nixon tapes, by their sheer volume alone, were worth far more. The Zapruder film, only 26 seconds long, captured the assassination of President John F. Kennedy in Dallas in November, 1963.</p><p>However, the Justice Department contended that Nixon's tapes and other records "were created, retained, organized and processed ultimately for one purpose--to deposit them in a Richard Nixon presidential library open to the American people for research."</p><p>As a result, "these materials were dedicated to public use by Mr. Nixon from the earliest days of his administration . . . to be held in what Mr. Nixon called 'a public trust' " and so have little commercial value, government attorneys argued.</p><p>Additionally, they said, the judge should consider that American taxpayers already have spent about $21 million to keep and index all the materials as custodian for 25 years. "These are costs which Mr. Nixon would have borne had he retained the materials," the department said in its final legal brief.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Philippines evacuates people near the Mayon volcano amid signs of possible eruption</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/philippines-mayon-volcano-evacuations-indications-eruption</link>
      <description>The Philippines is evacuating residents near the Mayon volcano as its increasing unrest possibly indicates a violent eruption in weeks or days.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 08:20:35 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/philippines-mayon-volcano-evacuations-indications-eruption</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/philippines-mayon-volcano-evacuations-indications-eruption">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/ba9541d/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3872x2582+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fd7%2F70%2Ff459d95d29d1fa82d5869d3c4f18%2F845708e3b8b94b53bca83510622a80b4 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7fd0f85/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3872x2582+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fd7%2F70%2Ff459d95d29d1fa82d5869d3c4f18%2F845708e3b8b94b53bca83510622a80b4 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9d59d48/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3872x2582+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fd7%2F70%2Ff459d95d29d1fa82d5869d3c4f18%2F845708e3b8b94b53bca83510622a80b4 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2a031df/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3872x2582+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fd7%2F70%2Ff459d95d29d1fa82d5869d3c4f18%2F845708e3b8b94b53bca83510622a80b4 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b0511fa/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3872x2582+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fd7%2F70%2Ff459d95d29d1fa82d5869d3c4f18%2F845708e3b8b94b53bca83510622a80b4 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Mayon Volcano spews white smoke as seen from Daraga, Albay province, central Philippines on Thursday June 8, 2023. The Philippine Institute of Volcanology and Seismology raised Thursday the status of Mayon Volcano in Albay to Alert Level 3 due to &quot;increased tendency towards a hazardous eruption.&quot; (AP Photo/John Michael Magdasoc)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/5b43930/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3872x2582+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fd7%2F70%2Ff459d95d29d1fa82d5869d3c4f18%2F845708e3b8b94b53bca83510622a80b4 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/158510b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3872x2582+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fd7%2F70%2Ff459d95d29d1fa82d5869d3c4f18%2F845708e3b8b94b53bca83510622a80b4 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/78ace64/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3872x2582+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fd7%2F70%2Ff459d95d29d1fa82d5869d3c4f18%2F845708e3b8b94b53bca83510622a80b4 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8eb61b5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3872x2582+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fd7%2F70%2Ff459d95d29d1fa82d5869d3c4f18%2F845708e3b8b94b53bca83510622a80b4 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c983585/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3872x2582+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fd7%2F70%2Ff459d95d29d1fa82d5869d3c4f18%2F845708e3b8b94b53bca83510622a80b4 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/c983585/2147483647/strip/true/crop/3872x2582+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fd7%2F70%2Ff459d95d29d1fa82d5869d3c4f18%2F845708e3b8b94b53bca83510622a80b4"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Mayon Volcano spews white smoke as seen from Daraga, Albay province, central Philippines on Thursday June 8, 2023. The Philippine Institute of Volcanology and Seismology raised Thursday the status of Mayon Volcano in Albay to Alert Level 3 due to increased tendency towards a hazardous eruption. (AP Photo/John Michael Magdasoc)</div><div class="figure-credit">(John Michael Magdasoc / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>Philippines evacuates people near the Mayon volcano amid signs of possible eruption</h1>                                                                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>Philippine troops, police and rescue workers began forcibly evacuating residents <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world/la-fg-philippines-volcano-20180121-story.html">near the Mayon volcano</a> on Friday as its increasing unrest indicated that a violent eruption of one of the countrys most active volcanoes is possible within weeks or days.</p><p>The area within a nearly four-mile radius of Mayon's crater <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world/la-xpm-2013-may-07-la-fg-wn-philippines-volcano-hikers-killed-20130507-story.html">is supposed to be off limits</a> because of possible volcanic emissions, lava flows, rockfalls and other hazards. But many poor villagers have built houses and tended farms in Mayon's danger zone over the years.</p><p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2022-05-10/ferdinand-marcos-jr-wins-philippine-presidential-election">President Ferdinand Marcos Jr.</a> said an evacuation of residents from the permanent danger zone was underway and promised to provide aid to </p>the <p>displaced </p> people<p> until the crisis ended.</p><p>Right now, what we are doing is preparing and moving people away from the area so that, should the time come  were ready, Marcos told reporters, adding that he hoped Mayon would not erupt. But unfortunately, science tells us that may happen because the lid or the cap on top of the lava is slowly rising.</p><p>Authorities had raised the alert level for the volcano in northeastern Albay province Thursday after <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1993-02-13-mn-1358-story.html">superheated streams of gas, debris and rocks</a> cascaded down its upper slope, indicating activity below the surface that could precede a hazardous eruption.</p><p>Conditions advanced a little bit more Friday, although lava hasnt started to flow, Marcos said.</p> Booming eruptions, ash everywhere: What life is like under Mexico's most dangerous volcano<p>The numbers of residents being evacuated weren't immediately available.</p><p>A tourist draw for its picturesque conical shape, 8,077-foot-tall Mayon <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world/la-fg-philippines-volcano-20180121-story.html">last erupted violently in 2018</a>, displacing tens of thousands of villagers.</p><p>Government volcano experts raised the alert level around Mayon to the third in a five-step warning system Thursday after detecting an increasing number of rockfalls and at least two volcanic earthquakes in recent days. </p><p>Six brief volcanic gas and ash emissions streamed down the volcanos southern gullies about 1.2 miles from the crater Friday. Numerous rockfalls and thin ash and steam plumes that drifted south were also observed, the government volcanology institute said.</p> Volcano eruption on Russia's Kamchatka Peninsula spews ash clouds for miles <p>Mayon is at a relatively high level of unrest as magma is at the crater and hazardous eruption is possible within weeks or even days, the institute said in its latest update Friday morning. </p><p>Mayon is one of the most restive of <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2020-01-12/lava-gushes-from-philippine-volcano-as-ash-spreads-to-manila">two dozen active volcanoes</a> across the Philippines. </p><p>Officials also were closely monitoring Taal </p>V<p>volcano south of Manila and </p>Mount  Mt. <p>Kanlaon on central Negros island because of renewed signs of restiveness.</p><p>A number of villages in three towns near Taal suspended classes Wednesday because of thick smog emanating from the volcano, and residents were advised to limit outdoor activities and wear masks for protection.</p><p>The Philippines lies along the Pacific Ring of Fire, the area around the ocean rim where tectonic plates meet, making it prone to earthquakes and volcanic eruptions. A long-dormant volcano, </p>Mount  Mt.<p> Pinatubo, blew its top north of Manila in 1991 in <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1991-08-11-tm-798-story.html">one of the biggest volcanic eruptions of the 20th century</a>, killing hundreds of people.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>France hails 'hero with a backpack' who intervened in knife attack on young children</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/children-stabbed-french-alps-critical-condition</link>
      <description>French media are hailing 'the hero with a backpack' who grappled with an attacker during a stabbing rampage that critically wounded four children.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 11:41:31 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/children-stabbed-french-alps-critical-condition</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-09/children-stabbed-french-alps-critical-condition">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0fc98c7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5482x3655+0+0/resize/320x213!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc9%2Fa4%2F2cfc7dce4953a797d738a5a6968c%2Ffrance-knife-attack-77781.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/57a3843/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5482x3655+0+0/resize/568x379!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc9%2Fa4%2F2cfc7dce4953a797d738a5a6968c%2Ffrance-knife-attack-77781.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9535b47/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5482x3655+0+0/resize/768x512!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc9%2Fa4%2F2cfc7dce4953a797d738a5a6968c%2Ffrance-knife-attack-77781.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/4a99af7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5482x3655+0+0/resize/1024x683!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc9%2Fa4%2F2cfc7dce4953a797d738a5a6968c%2Ffrance-knife-attack-77781.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/78672a8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5482x3655+0+0/resize/1200x800!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc9%2Fa4%2F2cfc7dce4953a797d738a5a6968c%2Ffrance-knife-attack-77781.jpg 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="Henri, right, meets French President Emmanuel Macron in Annecy, French Alps, Friday, June 9, 2023. The 24-year-old man in France is being hailed as a hero after he intervened in a savage knife attack on very young children. Henri had a heavy backpack on his back and was holding another in his hand when the attacker slashed at him Thursday June 8, 2023. Henri was shown grappling with the assailant and charging after him during the knife attack that critically wounded four children between the ages of 22 months and 3 years old, and also injured two adults. (Denis Balibouse/Pool via AP)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/295cf93/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5482x3655+0+0/resize/320x213!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc9%2Fa4%2F2cfc7dce4953a797d738a5a6968c%2Ffrance-knife-attack-77781.jpg 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/8f1dad8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5482x3655+0+0/resize/568x379!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc9%2Fa4%2F2cfc7dce4953a797d738a5a6968c%2Ffrance-knife-attack-77781.jpg 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7ad5ab5/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5482x3655+0+0/resize/768x512!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc9%2Fa4%2F2cfc7dce4953a797d738a5a6968c%2Ffrance-knife-attack-77781.jpg 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/54bd4ce/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5482x3655+0+0/resize/1024x683!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc9%2Fa4%2F2cfc7dce4953a797d738a5a6968c%2Ffrance-knife-attack-77781.jpg 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2833dd8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5482x3655+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc9%2Fa4%2F2cfc7dce4953a797d738a5a6968c%2Ffrance-knife-attack-77781.jpg 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="800"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/2833dd8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/5482x3655+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fc9%2Fa4%2F2cfc7dce4953a797d738a5a6968c%2Ffrance-knife-attack-77781.jpg"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">Henri, right, meets French President Emmanuel Macron in Annecy, French Alps, Friday, June 9, 2023. The 24-year-old man in France is being hailed as a hero after he intervened in a savage knife attack on very young children. Henri had a heavy backpack on his back and was holding another in his hand when the attacker slashed at him Thursday June 8, 2023. Henri was shown grappling with the assailant and charging after him during the knife attack that critically wounded four children between the ages of 22 months and 3 years old, and also injured two adults. (Denis Balibouse/Pool via AP)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Denis Balibouse / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>France hails &#x27;hero with a backpack&#x27; who intervened in knife attack on young children</h1>                                                                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 9, 2023">June 9, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>The attacker slashed at him with the same knife that he had used to savagely <a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-08/knife-attack-france-annecy-alps-injures-children">stab one young child after another</a>. But rather than run, Henri held his ground  using a weighty backpack he was carrying to swing at the assailant and fend off his blade.</p><p>French media hailed Henri as the hero with a backpack on Friday after he was shown in a video grappling with the assailant and charging after him during the rampage that critically wounded four children between the ages of 22 months and 3 years old. The attack </p> Thursday added day<p>at a children's playground in the French Alpine city of Annecy also injured two adults.</p>2 new grafs Henri, 24, received personal words of gratitude Friday from <p><a href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-03-16/macron-bypasses-parliament-france-retirement-bill">     President Emmanuel Macron  </a></p> , who toured hospitals to meet victims and their families. In Annecy, the French leader thanked medical workers, police, firefighters, civilians  including Henri  and others whose first aid and swift interventions helped save lives during the attack in the town's lakeside park. You experienced very hard moments, traumatizing," Macron said. I am very proud of you. no more adds<p>Henri</p>, 24,<p> had a heavy backpack on his back and was holding another in his hand when the attacker slashed at him. Even after being slashed at, Henri continued to harry the attacker by pursuing him inside a playground  where the man repeatedly stabbed a child in a stroller  and then out of the park again, carrying his backpacks all the while. He appeared to hurl one of the packs at the assailant at one point and then pick it up again to take another swing.</p><p>Henri's father, Franois, said he believed that his son's dogged pursuit helped dissuade the attacker from stabbing more victims before police wrestled him to the ground.</p> From the archives: 16 bodies found in the French Alps after suspected cult ritual<p>He took a lot of risks when he wasnt armed, with just his backpacks, the father told the Associated Press. He didnt stop running after him for many minutes, to stop him from coming back and massacring the kids even more. I think he prevented carnage by scaring him off. Really very courageous.</p><p>Franois asked that his and his son's last name not be published, expressing concerns about their family being thrust suddenly and inadvertently into the public eye at a time of shock and outrage in France provoked by the viciousness of Thursday's attack and the helplessness of its young victims.</p><p>The profile of the suspected attacker, a 31-year-old Syrian refugee, also fueled renewed political debate about French migration policies. Critics on the right and far-right of French politics quickly dusted off their arguments that French migration controls are too lax.</p><p>For his part, Henri shied away from the hero label. He said he tried to act as all French people should act, or would act.</p> Thousands await help  if it ever comes  in Russian-occupied Ukraine after dam burst<p>In that moment, you unplug your brain and react a bit like an animal by instinct," he told broadcaster BFMTV. "It was impossible for me to witness that without reacting.</p><p>I am far from alone in having reacted. Many other people around started, like me, to run after him to try to scare him, push him away. And other people immediately went over to the children to take care of the injured.</p><p>Henri added: I remember there was also a municipal worker who arrived from the right with a large plastic shovel to try to hit him.</p><p>French Prime Minister Elisabeth Borne said Friday that all four children underwent surgery for their life-threatening knife wounds and are under constant medical surveillance.</p> Trump says he's been indicted in special counsel investigation into classified documents<p>Their situation is stable, she said.</p><p>Government spokesman Olivier Veran, a medical doctor by training, said that two of the children remained in critical condition.</p>President Emmanuel <p>Macron and his wife, Brigitte, traveled to a hospital treating three of the four children. Motives for the attack in and around the lakeside playground remained unexplained. </p><p>The suspect, who has refugee status in Sweden, remains in custody. Psychiatrists are evaluating him, Veran said.</p><p>Henri's father said </p>that in a phone conversation after the attack,<p> his son </p> told him after the attack<p> </p>told me <p>that the Syrian was incoherent, saying lots of strange things in different languages, invoking his father, his mother, all the gods.</p><p>In short, he was possessed by who knows what, but possessed by folly, thats certain, the father told the AP.</p><p>He said he did not show the disturbing video of the attack to his other children and his wife, and added that he and his wife had trouble sleeping even after learning that Henri was safe.</p><p>We thanked providence and his guardian angels, he said.</p> Mt. Whitney: A perilous trek to the top of California's record snowpack <p>Most of the injured children were rushed to a hospital in the <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1986-11-09-tr-24099-story.html">French Alpine city of Grenoble</a>  the first stop for Macron and his wife Friday morning. They didn't speak to reporters as they went inside.</p><p>The fourth wounded child was being treated in Geneva, in neighboring Switzerland.</p><p>Two of the four children are French, and the other two are tourists  one British, the other Dutch.</p><p>Two adults also suffered knife wounds  life-threatening for one them, authorities said. One of the adults was injured both with a knife and by a shot fired by police as they were detaining the suspected attacker.</p> One Metro worker revived 21 riders overdosing on opioids. He's not alone<p>Portugals Foreign Ministry said that a Portuguese citizen was one of the two adults wounded.</p><p>In the course of the tragic event, a Portuguese citizen, while trying to stop the attacker from fleeing from the police, was seriously injured and is now out of danger. For this act of courage and bravery, we thank him profoundly, the ministry said.</p><p>French authorities said the suspect had recently been refused asylum in France, because Sweden had already granted him permanent residency and refugee status a decade ago.</p><p>Lead prosecutor Line Bonnet-Mathis said the mans motives were unknown, but didn't appear to be terrorism-related. He was armed with a folding knife, she said.</p>                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>James Watt, sharp-tongued and pro-development interior secretary under Reagan, dies at 85</title>
      <link>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-08/james-watt-sharp-tongued-and-pro-development-interior-secretary-under-reagan-dies-at-85</link>
      <description>James Watt, the Reagan administration’s sharp-tongued, pro-development interior secretary, has died. He was 85.</description>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jun 2023 00:14:09 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>MEAD GRUVER</author>
      <guid>https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-08/james-watt-sharp-tongued-and-pro-development-interior-secretary-under-reagan-dies-at-85</guid>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<html lang="en">                    <head>                <meta charset="utf-8">                <meta property="op:markup_version" content="v1.0">                                    <link rel="canonical" href="https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2023-06-08/james-watt-sharp-tongued-and-pro-development-interior-secretary-under-reagan-dies-at-85">                                <meta property="fb:article_style" content="default">            </head>                            <body>                <article>                    <header>                                                    <figure class="figure">        <picture>                            <source    type="image/webp"    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7dea1bf/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/320x229!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/1146681/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/568x406!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/0dd9184/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/768x549!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/d78b089/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/1024x732!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/9c319dd/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/1200x858!/format/webp/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 1200w"            sizes="100vw"    />                    <img class="image" alt="FILE - Interior Secretary nominee James Watt, a Reagan nominee on talks on Dec. 23, 1980 in Washington. Reagan administration Interior Secretary James Watt has died at age 85. Reagan administration Interior Secretary James Watt has died at age 85. Watt died in Arizona on May 27, 2023, son Eric Watt said in a statement Thursday, June 8. (AP Photo/Taylor, File)"                    srcset="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/7c01a54/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/320x229!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 320w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/39f525b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/568x406!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 568w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/33cb7b7/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/768x549!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 768w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/cd3f1d9/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/1024x732!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 1024w,https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b3339a8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/1200x858!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f 1200w"                            sizes="100vw"                            width="1200"        height="858"        src="https://ca-times.brightspotcdn.com/dims4/default/b3339a8/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2998x2144+0+0/resize/1200x858!/quality/80/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fcalifornia-times-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fdd%2F84%2Fecfb95057d5e5d8f82247efb22c1%2F6dcc62c943024e96ae699aaba673bb0f"        decoding="async"            ></picture>                <div class="figure-content">    <div class="figure-caption" aria-hidden="true">FILE - Interior Secretary nominee James Watt, a Reagan nominee on talks on Dec. 23, 1980 in Washington. Reagan administration Interior Secretary James Watt has died at age 85. Reagan administration Interior Secretary James Watt has died at age 85. Watt died in Arizona on May 27, 2023, son Eric Watt said in a statement Thursday, June 8. (AP Photo/Taylor, File)</div><div class="figure-credit">(Taylor / Associated Press)</div>        </div>    </figure>                                                                            <h1>James Watt, sharp-tongued and pro-development interior secretary under Reagan, dies at 85</h1>                                                                                                    <address>    <a rel="author" >        MEAD GRUVER    </a></address>                                                                            <time class="op-published" dateTime="June 8, 2023">June 8, 2023</time>                                                                    </header>                    <p>James Watt, the Reagan administrations sharp-tongued, pro-development interior secretary who was beloved by conservatives but ran afoul of environmentalists, Beach Boys fans and eventually the president, has died. He was 85.</p><p>Watt died in Arizona on May 27, his son Eric Watt said in a statement Thursday.</p><p>In an administration divided between so-called pragmatists and hard-liners, few stood as far to the right at the time as Watt, who once labeled the environmental movement as preservation vs. people and the general public as a clash between liberals and Americans.</p><p>In that sense, Watt foreshadowed combative interior secretaries like Ryan Zinke and David Bernhardt, who, like Watt, aggressively pushed to grant oil, gas and coal leases on public land, increase offshore drilling and limit expansion of national parks and monuments. </p><p>While no ones death should be celebrated, he was the worst of MAGA before it was invented," tweeted David Donger of the environmental group Natural Resources Defense Council, referring to former President Trump's Make America Great Again slogan.</p><p>Watt and his supporters saw him as an upholder of President Reagans core conservative values, but opponents were alarmed by his policies and offended by his comments. In 1981, shortly after he was appointed, the Sierra Club collected more than 1 million signatures seeking Watts ouster and criticized such actions as clear-cutting federal lands in the Pacific Northwest, weakening environmental regulations for strip mining and hampering efforts to curtail air pollution in Californias Yosemite Valley.</p><p>With his bald head and thick glasses, he became the rare interior secretary recognizable to the general public, for reasons beyond the environment. He characterized members of a coal advisory panel using derogatory language and in 1983 tried to ban music from Fourth of July festivities on the National Mall, saying it attracted the wrong element.</p><p>The Beach Boys had been recent mall headliners, and their fans included President Reagan and First Lady Nancy Reagan. With Watts statement facing widespread mockery, the Reagans invited the Beach Boys for a special White House visit. Watt, meanwhile, was summoned to receive a plaster model of a foot with a hole in it.</p> Interior secretary seeks to rid U.S. of derogatory place names<p>In his 1985 book The Courage of a Conservative, Watt wrote that the controversy actually arose because I was a conservative. Members of a liberal press saw an opportunity to create a controversy by censoring the facts and avoiding the real issues. He said the initial stories about the rock music ban only mentioned that the Beach Boys had performed in the past. Yet before we knew what was happening, banner headlines proclaimed that I had banned the Beach Boys. I was astonished.</p><p>Cutting regulations was his primary mission. Between the time he was confirmed as interior secretary in 1981 until he resigned under pressure in 1983, Watt implemented an offshore leasing program that offered virtually the entire U.S. coastline for oil and gas drilling and held the largest coal lease sale in history, auctioning off 1.1 billion tons </p>(1 billion metric tons)<p> of coal in the Powder River Basin of Montana and Wyoming.</p><p>Watt tripled the amount of onshore land being leased for oil and gas exploration and doubled the acreage leased for geothermal resources.</p><p>Watt did spend $1 billion to restore and improve national parks and added 2,800 square miles </p>(7,300 square kilometers)<p> to the nations wilderness system. And his efforts to exploit natural resources made America stronger, he wrote to Reagan in October 1983.</p><p>Our excellent record for managing the natural resources of this land is unequaled  because we put people in the environmental equation, Watt wrote.</p><p>But eight days after writing to the president, he rode horseback into a cow pasture down the road from Reagans California ranch to announce his resignation. He was succeeded by a longtime Reagan aide, William Clark.</p><p>I had outworn my usefulness, Watt said of his decision, adding that others wouldn't get off my case about his insulting coal advisory panel comment.</p><p>Watt was born Jan. 31, 1938, in Lusk, Wyo., and his family later moved to Wheatland, Wyo., where his father practiced law. He attended the University of Wyoming, graduating in 1960 and obtaining a law degree two years later.</p> Interior Department adds $103 million for wildfire hazards and land rehabilitation<p>In 1962, Watt became a personal assistant to former Gov. Milward L. Simpson, and he went to Washington after Simpson was elected to the U.S. Senate later that year. In 1966-69, he helped develop policies on such issues as pollution, mining, public lands and energy for the U.S. Chamber of Commerce, then in early 1969 he joined the Nixon administration as an Interior Department undersecretary.</p><p>In 1975, President Ford appointed him to the Federal Power Commission.</p><p>While Jimmy Carter was president, Watt worked in the private sector as president and chief legal officer of the pro-development Mountain States Legal Foundation in Denver.</p><p>He did consulting work after leaving the Reagan administration, at one point turning heads when he agreed to represent </p>Indian Native American<p> tribes in oil operations and hotel developments after previously labeling </p>Indian Indigenous<p> reservations the failure of socialism. He also accepted six-figure consulting fees to represent developers of a federally subsidized housing project.</p><p>He moved back to Wyoming in 1986 and set up a law office in Jackson, taught at his alma mater and served as a legal consultant and speaker.</p><p>But his consulting work involving federal housing money came under scrutiny in the late 1980s when an investigation was launched into corruption in the Department of Housing and Urban Development.</p><p>In 1996, he pleaded guilty to a single misdemeanor for withholding documents from a grand jury investigating HUD. He was fined $5,000, put on five years probation and ordered to perform community service. He said he had made a serious mistake and hoped to get on with a constructive role in society.</p><p>Over the years, Watt expressed fears that unless they were stopped, radical environmental movements like Earth First! would persuade the cowards of Congress to ban all hunting, eliminate all logging and livestock grazing on public lands and further jeopardize the minerals industries.</p><p>He lived in his later years in Wickenburg, Ariz., with his wife, Leilani.</p>Associated Press writer Matthew Daly in Washington, D.C., contributed to this report.                                    </article>            </body>            </html>]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
